<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: publishing | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/publishing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-17T14:26:33-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Redmine Plugin Extension and Development Still In Demand]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2017/10/03/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development-still-in-demand/"/>
        <updated>2017-10-03T20:38:12-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2017/10/03/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development-still-in-demand</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[It's been a [while](/blog/2016/03/23/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development-is-apparently-still-relevant/) since I last wrote about [Redmine Plugin Extension and Development](http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book) so I thought I'd give a quick update.

I have been sharing sales numbers whenever possible as a way of (hopefully) encouraging other authors to see that there is some money out there, even for obscure niche topics.


| |Ebook|Print|
|-|-----|-----|
|Q2/2017|17|12|
|Q1/2017|16|8|

This isn't a super lucrative endeavour, but considering I published this book three years ago and it's still in demand, I can't complain.

If I had more time on my hands I might look into writing about something a bit more "in demand", like [Docker](https://www.docker.com/) or [.NET Core](https://www.microsoft.com/net/core) (random topics I'm currently interested in :P).]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fifth Royalty Statement: This time for profit!]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/08/04/fifth-royalty-statement/"/>
        <updated>2015-08-04T20:49:59-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/08/04/fifth-royalty-statement</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I've been meaning to write this post for a long time, as I officially got the royalty statement at the end of June, but I've been a bit busy with life, contracts and the occasional 16-bit era JRPG ...

As of this quarter, [Redmine Plugin Extension and Development](http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book) is officially earning me money!

<img class="left" src="/images/royalties-004.png">

Technically, the last statement was [in the black](https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/in_the_black), however since the terms laid out by Packt Publishing only pays out royalties greater than £75, those earnings were rolled into this quarter.

I've updated the table below with the numbers from the current quarter, but I'd really like to thank everyone who's bought a copy of this book for supporting the [Redmine](http://www.redmine.org/) project, and the vibrant plugin development community as well.

| |Ebook Mini|Subscription Packtlib Mini|Print Book Mini|Subscription (3rd Party Mini)|
|-|----------|--------------------------|---------------|-----------------------------|
|Q1/2014|18|3|18|0|
|Q2/2014|73|1|33|2|
|Q3/2014|25|2|24|4|
|Q4/2014|33|2|31|2|
|Q1/2015|90|0|25|2|

If you're just venturing onto this blog after having bought the book, please feel free to leave a comment on any of the posts, or just shoot me a message :)]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fourth Royalty Statement]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/05/14/fourth-royalty-statement/"/>
        <updated>2015-05-14T11:34:45-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/05/14/fourth-royalty-statement</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[It's been over a year since this book was published, and I didn't think it would see the type of success it has.

<img class="left" src="/images/20150329-001.png">

Based on this last statement, I'm officially eligible to start collecting royalties off this book.

This will have to wait until next quarter as Packt only pays out if the total proceeds exceed £75; which the USD$78 I earned last quarter doesn't ;)

[Redmine](http://redmine.org) is a very popular open source project management platform, but in order to extend it users need to be familiar with not only the [Ruby](https://www.ruby-lang.org) language, but the [Ruby on Rails](http://rubyonrails.org/) framework as well.

This can be quite the barrier to entry for new developers, as they need to have a fair amount of knowledge coming in.

Based on the sales figures I have access to, as well as feedback and inquiries I've received over the last year, it's safe to say that the Redmine community is thriving :)

I've updated the sales chart with my last royalty statement:

| |Ebook Mini|Subscription Packtlib Mini|Print Book Mini|Subscription (3rd Party Mini)|
|-|----------|--------------------------|---------------|-----------------------------|
|Q1/2014|18|3|18|0|
|Q2/2014|73|1|33|2|
|Q3/2014|25|2|24|4|
|Q4/2014|33|2|31|2|

If you're one of the people that bought the book, please leave a comment and let me know what you thought.

I'm in the process of updating the [knowledgebase plugin](https://github.com/alexbevi/redmine_knowledgebase) that served as the focal point of the book to be compatible with Redmine 3.0 and beyond. If you have any ideas for new features, or feel I should get cracking on the bug fixes, log an issue :)]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Third Royalty Statement]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/12/22/third-royalty-statement/"/>
        <updated>2014-12-22T08:11:36-05:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/12/22/third-royalty-statement</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I'd love to say Christmas came early this year, but it looks like sales of [Redmine Plugin Extension and Development](http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book) didn't quite hit the numbers needed to actually result in a royalty cheque. Ah well, there's always Q1 of 2015 :D

I've added the latest numbers to those from [my previous post](/blog/2014/09/22/second-royalty-statement/) in order to show the running total of units sold this year.

| |Ebook Mini|Subscription Packtlib Mini|Print Book Mini|Subscription (3rd Party Mini)|
|-|----------|--------------------------|---------------|-----------------------------|
|Q1/2014|18|3|18|0|
|Q2/2014|73|1|33|2|
|Q3/2014|25|2|24|4|

<!-- more -->

<img class="left" src="/images/20141222-ss01.png">

The main reason I've been sharing these numbers (without sharing that actual "numbers") is to show prospective authors what types of returns they can potentially expect.

The book I wrote falls into the "minibook" category, so the returns are lower than a full-on "book" (I think < 100 pages is a minibook), but at this rate, 2015 might result in a non-negative royalty statement that I can share :)

Happy Holidays Everyone!!!

<img class="left" src="/images/20141222-cat.png">
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Second Royalty Statement]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/09/22/second-royalty-statement/"/>
        <updated>2014-09-22T11:45:14-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/09/22/second-royalty-statement</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[Although I haven't really had much to write about lately, I just got another royalty update from Packt Publishing about [Redmine Plugin Extension and Development](http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book) so I wanted to share the latest sales figures ... sort of :P

In the table below, I've added the latest numbers to those from [my previous post](/blog/2014/07/15/8748os-first-royalty-statement/) in order to show the running total of units sold this year.

| |Ebook Mini|Subscription Packtlib Mini|Print Book Mini|Subscription (3rd Party Mini)|
|-|----------|--------------------------|---------------|-----------------------------|
|Q1/2014|18|3|18|0|
|Q2/2014|73|1|33|2|

<!-- more -->

<img class="left" src="/images/royalties20140630.png">

Once again, I've decided to remove the actual sales numbers from the statement, but I left in *TOTAL ROYALTIES TO BE PAID IN PERIOD* section. I did this to show the progress from time of publication to now in terms of how much of the advance has been consumed by **ACTUAL** sales.

At this rate, it's possible I'll see some additional money out of this title by the time 2014 is through .. which would be very exciting.

I'm sure there are others out there who have been approached by technical publications and asked to write about some topic or other. I'm sure the numbers I'm posting here will convince you it's not worth quitting your job and writing full time, but it looks like it *could* become profitable over time.

If you've had anything published and are seeing a decent return on your "investment", please share in the comments ;)]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
