<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-02-20T15:11:17-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ALEX BEVILACQUA</title><subtitle>Programming, MongoDB, Ruby and anything else I find interesting. Sometimes dabble in RPG/JRPG/Adventure game reviews.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Space Quest III: The Pirates of Pestulon (Sierra On-Line) - 1989</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/16/space-quest-iii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space Quest III: The Pirates of Pestulon (Sierra On-Line) - 1989" /><published>2024-02-16T16:27:05-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-20T07:26:20-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/16/space-quest-iii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/16/space-quest-iii/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>This review is part of the <a href="/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/">“Let’s Adventure!”</a> series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating <a href="/blog/2021/08/08/adventure-games-1980-1999-sorted-by-score/">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_Quest_III">Space Quest III: The Pirates of Pestulon</a> is a 1989 graphic adventure game by Sierra On-Line, and the third game in the Space Quest series. Players assume the role of Roger Wilco, a lowly space janitor, who becomes involved in rescuing a pair of computer programmers from a sinister video game company. The game received positive reviews from critics, and contributed further to the series’ commercial success for Sierra.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00017.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Narrowly escaping the events of <a href="/blog/2023/02/24/space-quest-2/">Space Quest II: Vohaul’s Revenge</a>, Roger Wilco’s escape pod floats through space. As just another metallic item of junk, it’s soon picked up by an interstellar garbage hauler. Waking up in a pile of trash, quite familiar for this janitor-turned-hero, Roger Wilco must somehow escape. Once given access to the rest of the galaxy, he’ll soon find himself having to avoid a collections cyborg for payments overdue, dealing with the corporate prison of software company Scummsoft, and having to digest the greasy food from the galaxy’s finest hamburger joint.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00022.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Like <a href="/blog/2023/02/21/police-quest-2/">Police Quest II</a> and <a href="/blog/2023/02/01/leisure-suit-larry-2/">Leisure Suit Larry II</a>, Space Quest III uses Sierra’s <a href="http://sciwiki.sierrahelp.com/index.php/Sierra_SCI_Release_List#SCI0_.28late.29">SCI0</a> engine, which requires you to interact with the game world via a text parser. Though you have a mouse cursor ever-present, this really only allows you to move around the screen the same way the arrow keys on the keyboard would.</p>

<p>The text parser allows you to enter noun/verb combinations and experience the results of your request via cheeky feedback from the game. Though this control mechanism may be a bit foreign to modern gamers, it’s incredibly well done in Space Quest III, and you’re encouraged to try <em>everything</em> to as you’ll almost always be rewarded with either a funny or snarky response.</p>

<p>If you’re interested in the internals of the engine I’d highly recommend giving the blog post <a href="https://www.benshoof.org/blog/sci-scripts"><em>“Sierra Creative Interpreter – Scripts”</em></a> a read, as it’s by one of the ScummVM authors (Chris Benshoof	aka. <em>sluicebox</em>) who’s invested heavily in tooling and decompilation of SCI resources and scripts.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00009.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>As you navigate the game world you’ll be treated to decent sound effects and atmospheric music. The best way to experience the sound effects and music in this game is by emulating the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roland_MT-32">Roland MT-32</a>.</p>

<p>It’s relatively easy to do this in ScummVM if you know where to find the the necessary ROMs to get <a href="https://bmaupin.github.io/wiki/archive/applications/games/scummvm.html#getting-roland-mt-32-emulation-working">MT-32 emulation working</a>. Though you had Adlib and Soundblaster available at the time, MT-32 was just so much better. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9NSV8_ItVwc&amp;list=PL_BhbJAAueZS-5vMC4m7jCfxqaWfypLmt">Check out this playlist on YouTube</a> to get a sense of how much better the audio sounded using this device!</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00012.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The first third of the game has you trying to escape from a Terminator-like cyborg that is out to collect on a dept Roger incurred in the previous game. After you find a ship in the initial stage and set a course for Phleebhut, the cyborg follows him there and attempts to hunt him down and capture him.</p>

<p>You’ve only got a limited amount of “time” to figure out how to defeat the cyborg (and steal the invisibility belt that he has). While you try to do this you’ll find myriad ways in which to get yourself killed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00014.png" alt="" />
<em>You know you want to watch a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oN32uIpg538">10 minute video</a> compilation of death scenes from SQ3.</em></p>

<p>Since this is a Sierra game, and death literally awaits you around every corner and on every screen it’s very much appreciated how much effort went into scripting the death sequences. Though I typically spend a disproportionate amount of time dying on purpose playing these games just to see what happens, I think I enjoyed the outcome more than usual with Space Quest III.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00018.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Once you escape the cyborg, you’ll travel to Monolith Burger. This section is pretty short as all you need to do is order a happy meal (or value meal or something like that), eat it to find a decoder ring - then play the Astro Chicken game. This game can be a pain in the ass as you have to land the falling chicken on the landing pad 10 times in a row without it bouncing off. This may sound easy at first, but timing the deceleration of the chicken while maneuvering it across the screen proved to be a lot more challenging than I expected.</p>

<p>After you succeed (or fail enough times that the game feels sorry for you) you’ll be presented with an encoded message. Lucky for you you just found a decoder ring, which you can use to find a secret message from the programmers of Astro Chicken - the <a href="https://spacequest.fandom.com/wiki/Two_Guys_From_Andromeda">two guys from Andromeda</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00024.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Turns out the two guys are being held captive on Pestulon, which is a moon of Ortega. First you need to navigate to Ortega, disable the shield generator around Pestulon, fly to Pestulon and deal with the pirates. What kind of pirates are we talking about? Well, that would be software pirates!</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00027.png" alt="" />
<em>Not what I expected based on the title of the game</em></p>

<p>Elmo Pug, the leader of the “Pirates of Pestulon” (aka. ScumSoft) abducted the 2 guys to force them to design awful games they can flood the galaxy with. There is definitely some light-hearted jabbing at LucasArts with some of the references here, but that just makes me appreciate the writing of this game even more.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00029.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The final sequence of the game involves a couple of mini games. You first have to defeat Elmo Pug in a rock ‘em sock ‘em robots style battle, then escape on your ship and win a space battle. Though not overly difficult, you can lose during both of these sequences, so make sure you have save games before each begin so you can reload when you inevitably die the first few times.</p>

<p>After the space battle you fly the 2 guys to Earth and land in the parking lot of Sierra Online, where Ken Williams hires the 2 guys to work for him as programmers.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00033.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>As I play through these games the main thing I typically look for is narrative strength. The graphics don’t need to be great, the music can be so-so and the input mechanics can be clunky, but if the experience of actually <em>playing through</em> the adventure is enjoyable I’ll rate it a lot higher.</p>

<p>Space Quest III is very short, but the writing is funny and the pacing is good. You don’t really need a walkthrough because every time you die you’ll be presented with a popup that typically (a) makes fun of you for dying and (b) nudges you in the right direction to avoid dying again.</p>

<p>Though I rated <a href="/blog/2021/08/09/space-quest-the-sarien-encounter/">Space Quest: The Sarien Encounter</a> pretty highly, it’s primitive and less accessible than this sequel. If you want to try your hand at a parser-driven adventure game I’d highly recommend Space Quest III.</p>

<h2 id="game-information">Game Information</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game</em></td>
      <td>Space Quest III: The Pirates of Pestulon</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Developer</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sierra_Entertainment">Sierra On-Line</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Publisher</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sierra_Entertainment">Sierra On-Line</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Release Date</em></td>
      <td>March 24, 1989</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Systems</em></td>
      <td>DOS, Macintosh, Amiga, Atari ST</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game Engine</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=SCI">SCI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="my-playthrough">My Playthrough</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://howlongtobeat.com/game/8865"><em>How Long To Beat?</em></a></td>
      <td>3 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Version Played</em></td>
      <td>DOS via <a href="https://www.scummvm.org/">ScummVM</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Notes</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://adventuredoor.net/walkthroughs/space-quest-iii-pirates-pestulon-walkthrough/">Walkthrough</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="score">Score</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/#scoring">here</a> for a refresher on how we’re scoring these games.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Atmosphere (20)</strong></td>
      <td>15</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Story (25)</strong></td>
      <td>19</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Experience (15)</strong></td>
      <td>11</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Impact (10)</strong></td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>70%</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gallery">Gallery</h3>

<div id="inline-gallery-container" class="inline-gallery-container"></div>
<script type="module">import lightGallery from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0";import lgZoom from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/zoom";import lgThumbnail from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/thumbnail";const $lgContainer = document.getElementById("inline-gallery-container");const inlineGallery = lightGallery($lgContainer, {  container: $lgContainer,  licenseKey: "C2D2C2BD-16BC4564-A4EAE653-401CB884",  dynamic: true,  hash: false,  closable: false,  showMaximizeIcon: true,  slideDelay: 10,  plugins: [lgZoom, lgThumbnail],  dynamicEl: [{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00000.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00000.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00001.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00001.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00003.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00003.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00004.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00004.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00005.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00005.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00006.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00006.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00007.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00007.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00008.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00008.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00010.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00010.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00011.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00011.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00013.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00013.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00015.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00015.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00016.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00016.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00019.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00019.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00020.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00020.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00021.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00021.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00023.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00023.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00025.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00025.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00026.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00026.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00028.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00028.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00030.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00030.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00031.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00031.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00032.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00032.png' },]});inlineGallery.openGallery();</script>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Description from <a href="https://www.mobygames.com/game/142/space-quest-iii-the-pirates-of-pestulon/">Moby Games</a></small> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Let&apos;s Adventure!" /><category term="adventure" /><category term="Sierra On-Line" /><category term="SCI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This review is part of the “Let’s Adventure!” series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00002.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/sq3/scummvm-sq3-00002.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Adventures of Willy Beamish (Dynamix) - 1991</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/12/the-adventures-of-willy-beamish/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Adventures of Willy Beamish (Dynamix) - 1991" /><published>2024-02-12T19:48:56-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-15T06:50:41-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/12/the-adventures-of-willy-beamish</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/12/the-adventures-of-willy-beamish/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>This review is part of the <a href="/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/">“Let’s Adventure!”</a> series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating <a href="/blog/2021/08/08/adventure-games-1980-1999-sorted-by-score/">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Adventures_of_Willy_Beamish">The Adventures of Willy Beamish</a> is a graphic adventure game developed by Dynamix and published in 1991 by Sierra On-Line. The game pioneered the use of in-game graphics drawn to resemble classic hand-drawn cartoon animation. It was initially released for MS-DOS and the Amiga and was ported to the Sega CD in 1993.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_044.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>You play Willy Beamish, an eight-year-old kid who is just trying to get through life without losing his lunch money. But he’ll have to deal with parents, teachers, babysitters, and bratty sisters. The player must solve different puzzles to ensure Willy can progress, get out of trouble and generally avoid ending up grounded.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_030.png" alt="" />
<em>He’s talking about his frog “Horny”</em></p>

<p>The in-game time progresses even if no action is taken. This means many puzzles have to be solved in a certain time frame or rely on being in the right place at the right time. A special aspect of this game is the bar which shows Willy’s relationship with his parents. It gets affected by the way certain situations are resolved, e.g. it increases if Willy refuses to play with his sister, and when it is full they send Willy to a military school and the game is lost.<sup id="fnref:1:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_015.png" alt="" />
<em>If that meter hits “Cadet School” it’s game over … literally</em></p>

<p>Avoiding getting in trouble is pretty easy as decisions in this game are typically made during dialogue tree option selection. Almost every character you interact with will present Willy with an option, and one of those options will be the “wrong” one which effects your <em>Trouble Meter</em>.</p>

<p>This will happen on almost every screen of the game for about the first half of the game, so save early - save often.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_002.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>For 1991, this game looks great. The cartoony style really draws you into the game world and gives the characters some emotional depth during conversations. The colours are mostly bright and vibrant and complement the youthful innocence of Willy and his friends. This is in stark contrast to Dynamix’s previous title, <a href="/blog/2023/02/13/rise-of-the-dragon/">Rise of the Dragon</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_008.png" alt="" />
<em>Your mom pawns your sister off on you a lot it seems</em></p>

<p>The story revolves around Willy trying to raise money for his entry fee into the Nintari world tournament (get it - “Nintendo + Atari” - so clever …). The family thinks his dad is about to get a huge promotion, but it turns out he gets laid off instead and they’ll need to live a little leaner until he finds work again. Though Willy can do some odd jobs around the house for money like mowing the lawn, walking the dog or washing the car - he’ll need to do something bigger for the $2500 he needs.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_028.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Willy has a pet frog (named “Horny”) that’s with him throughout the game, and there’s a frog-jumping competition on the second or third day of the game with a convenient grand prize of $2500. Your main goal is to get Horny trained up and entered into the competition so that he can compete.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_029.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The frog jumping competition is one of 2 minigames, though it’s sort of “on rails”. If you figure out that you can feed Horny cola to tweak him out, he’ll win first prize but random drug testing will surface that he was “chemically enhanced” and you’ll lose the game. Otherwise you’ll lose to Turbo Frog - which is what’s supposed to happen anyway - and Horny will escape into the Tootsweet factory to progress the plot.</p>

<p>The minigame here is just a distraction and isn’t really a “game”. It’s just a bit of button mashing between story dumps and isn’t really fun to “play” - it’s just there.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_032.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The secondary plot of the game revolves around the Tootsweet owners trying to take over the city you live in. Willy’s dad will apply for a job as their head of PR and get that, only to be thrown under the bus right away as the fall guy for the company. There’s a plumbers strike going on as well which is causing the water to turn brown, so you’ll need to resolve that as well I guess.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_022.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The inventory screen serves two purposes in this game: item storage and time management. Since there are scripted events that take place on various days you have the option of advancing time here to trigger those events. Honestly once I figured this out I’d just save my game at the beginning of the day and just advance time a bunch to see what triggered when on various screens - then reload and proceed incrementally if I found anything.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_037.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>You sort of figure this mechanic out for yourself, as the <a href="https://archive.org/details/AdventuresOfWillyBeamishManual/mode/2up">game manual</a> doesn’t allude to time-based events. Luckily you don’t really need to worry about this as there are only a couple of these events throughout the game, such as Willy having to go to bed at the end of the day.</p>

<p>Timing plays a bigger part in puzzles though as a number of these involve using items or pushing buttons in a specific order within a very short amount of time. This is where I died the most, as there certain puzzle sequences that you need to do extremely quickly or it’s game over.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_041.png" alt="" />
<em>Solve this quickly or the guards will catch you</em></p>

<p>Though frustrating at times, I did appreciate that these “real time” puzzles added a sense of urgency. Typically adventure games would give you infinite time to pick and combine items, select a target and execute some action. Willy generally has a few seconds to react if the puzzle he’s trying to solve involves escaping from a dangerous situation.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_039.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Most puzzles are pretty straightforward, though near the end of the game you’ll need to get a bouncer to leave his post at the door of the bar so you can go in. The solution to this puzzle is extremely convoluted and requires you to call a psychic hotline, record the message, call the bar, ask for the bouncer and play the message. None of this is intuitive, and I’m pretty sure without a walkthrough most people wouldn’t muddle their way through this today.</p>

<p>If you’re playing this game for the first time would you know that “432-SIGN” could be translated to “432-7446”? Remember pay phones? Remember phone numbers that would use the lettering on the numbers to form words? I’m sure they still exist …</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_018.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>There are maybe a dozen locations you can visit throughout the game, with some only becoming available on later days. You have limited time to explore as time continues to advance, and eventually Willy will have to go home to bed, but I didn’t find myself getting lost or stuck at any point.</p>

<p>Basically you just go to each location, talk to whoever is there, pick up anything that isn’t nailed down and try to use everything on … everything. It’s not always obvious what item combinations are required so there is a lot of trial and error involved.</p>

<p>You’ll also want to right-click multiple times on each item you pick up as some of them have a third function on certain screens.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_045.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Occasionally an item will allow you to shoot or throw it, in which case the cursor will be presented as a target or crosshair. I’m pretty sure this only occurs twice, but if you don’t know this is the case it can be frustrating as you die over and over trying to “use” an item in a situation when you actually need to “shoot” it.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/willy/willy_046.png" alt="" />
<em>You win the Nintari championship and call it a day</em></p>

<p>Overall I didn’t really like this game as much as I thought I would. I’m a huge fan of Rise of the Dragon, and I generally like their <a href="https://dynamix.fandom.com/wiki/VCR_Interface">VCR interface</a> they use for their games. The background music is fitting and helps enhance the gameplay, but the story is pretty thin and the pacing of the game is slowed by convoluted puzzles.</p>

<p>I played the original DOS release (not the CD ROM version) so I’m not sure if the voice acting they added made any meaningful difference to the experience. I thought the writing overall was pretty good and the general vibe of the game was “saturday morning cartoon come to life”, which I think is what they were going for.</p>

<p>If you’re looking for a goofy game starring a 9 year old kid and his frog, The Adventures of Willy Beamish has you covered. Just be prepared to reach for a walkthrough …</p>

<h2 id="game-information">Game Information</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game</em></td>
      <td>The Adventures of Willy Beamish</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Developer</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamix">Dynamix</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Publisher</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sierra_Entertainment">Sierra On-Line</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Release Date</em></td>
      <td>1991</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Systems</em></td>
      <td>Amiga, DOS, Macintosh, Sega CD</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game Engine</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=DGDS">DGDS</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="my-playthrough">My Playthrough</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://howlongtobeat.com/game/9758"><em>How Long To Beat?</em></a></td>
      <td>4.5 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Version Played</em></td>
      <td>DOS via <a href="https://dosbox-x.com/">DOSBox-X</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Notes</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://archive.org/details/AdventuresOfWillyBeamishManual">Manual</a>, <a href="https://www.walkthroughking.com/text/adventuresofwillybeamish.aspx">Walkthrough</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="score">Score</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/#scoring">here</a> for a refresher on how we’re scoring these games.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Atmosphere (20)</strong></td>
      <td>13</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Story (25)</strong></td>
      <td>16</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Experience (15)</strong></td>
      <td>8</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Impact (10)</strong></td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>59%</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gallery">Gallery</h3>

<div id="inline-gallery-container" class="inline-gallery-container"></div>
<script type="module">import lightGallery from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0";import lgZoom from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/zoom";import lgThumbnail from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/thumbnail";const $lgContainer = document.getElementById("inline-gallery-container");const inlineGallery = lightGallery($lgContainer, {  container: $lgContainer,  licenseKey: "C2D2C2BD-16BC4564-A4EAE653-401CB884",  dynamic: true,  hash: false,  closable: false,  showMaximizeIcon: true,  slideDelay: 10,  plugins: [lgZoom, lgThumbnail],  dynamicEl: [{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_000.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_000.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_001.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_001.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_001.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_001.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_002.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_002.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_003.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_003.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_004.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_004.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_005.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_005.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_006.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_006.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_007.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_007.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_009.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_009.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_010.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_010.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_011.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_011.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_012.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_012.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_013.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_013.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_014.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_014.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_016.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_016.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_017.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_017.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_019.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_019.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_020.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_020.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_021.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_021.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_023.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_023.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_024.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_024.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_025.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_025.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_026.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_026.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_027.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_027.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_031.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_031.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_033.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_033.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_034.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_034.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_035.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_035.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_036.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_036.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_038.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_038.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_040.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_040.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_042.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_042.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_043.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_043.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_047.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/willy/willy_047.png' },]});inlineGallery.openGallery();</script>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Description from <a href="https://www.mobygames.com/game/1916/the-adventures-of-willy-beamish/">Moby Games</a></small> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:1:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Let&apos;s Adventure!" /><category term="adventure" /><category term="Dynamix" /><category term="Sierra On-Line" /><category term="DGDS" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This review is part of the “Let’s Adventure!” series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/willy/willy_000.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/willy/willy_000.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Loom (Lucasfilm Games) - 1990</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/06/loom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Loom (Lucasfilm Games) - 1990" /><published>2024-02-06T16:24:23-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-07T17:58:28-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/06/loom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/06/loom/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>This review is part of the <a href="/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/">“Let’s Adventure!”</a> series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating <a href="/blog/2021/08/08/adventure-games-1980-1999-sorted-by-score/">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loom_(video_game)">Loom</a> is a 1990 fantasy-themed graphic adventure game by Lucasfilm Games. The project was led by Brian Moriarty, a former Infocom employee and author of classic text adventures Wishbringer (1985), Trinity (1986), and Beyond Zork (1987). It was the fourth game to use the SCUMM adventure game engine, and the first of those to avoid the verb–object interface introduced in Maniac Mansion.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00028.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Bobbin Threadbare is a young man from the Guild of Weavers. He is outcast from the guild and blamed for the lack of prosperity in recent times, though he does not know why. On his seventeenth birthday he is summoned by the Elders of the guild, who intend to decide his fate. However, shortly thereafter all the inhabitants of the village except Bobbin are turned into swans. Bobbin finds out that he is the child of the Great Loom, found by Lady Cygna, who tried to use the loom’s powers to save the guild. Bobbin’s stepmother Dame Hetchel teaches him the art of weaving magical drafts, and Bobbin embarks on a journey to find the lost flock, and the answers to his questions.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00014.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Loom is an adventure game that sets itself apart from other titles in the genre through its unique gameplay system: the player character does not carry items around, but rather manipulates objects through the use of spells (called “drafts” in the game). The drafts themselves are woven by playing magical notes on a special instrument called “distaff”. All the puzzles in the game are solved by learning and correctly applying these drafts.<sup id="fnref:1:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00004.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Each draft is a sequence of four notes within one octave. The player learns new drafts by exploring the environment and interacting with it through a simple point-and-click interface. Once a draft has been learned, it may be applied in a different situation in order to solve a problem. Drafts range from simple general actions (such as opening) to more specific and complex commands, e.g. turning straw into gold. Drafts can also be “reversed”, i.e. played backwards, in order to execute the opposite action (for example, closing something instead of opening). As the game progresses Bobbin learns to play higher notes on the distaff, allowing him to access more drafts.<sup id="fnref:1:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00003.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The game begins with an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BcydSMadbcw">audio drama (YouTube)</a> that you originally would have listened to on casette tape (as your parents kids). This audio drama sets the stage for the game world and lays out the history of the world and how everyone is a member of one of four guilds. Bobbin is a member of the Guild of Weavers.</p>

<p>There is a whole lot of backstory presented in this audio drama, and I’ll be honest - I didn’t listen to all of it because it’s 30 minutes long and my attention span is … shorter than that. I did however read the synopsis on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loom_(video_game)#Prologue">Wikipedia</a> which answers a lot of questions, such as “whats with these swans?”.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00008.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Though Loom has three difficulty settings (I played on “Standard”), it’s an extremely simple game. Unlike most adventure games, there is no inventory management to worry about, no dialogue trees to navigate and very little backtracking. Your goals are pretty straightforward and can all be accomplished by doing essentially the same thing on every screen.</p>

<p>You click the mouse around the screen until the thing you click on is called out in the lower right of the screen. If this happens, you’ll either hear four notes on your distaff indicating there’s a new draft you can learn, or you’ll interact with whatever you just clicked on.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00005.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Basically every draft you learn can be played either forwards or backwards. For example, once you learn the “Straw to Gold” draft, if you happen to select a pile of gold and play the draft backwards, it’ll now turn “Gold to Straw”. This mechanic is used throughout the game and in most cases presents a pretty obvious solution to a given puzzle.</p>

<p>It is important to write down the drafts you learn though, as the game doesn’t record them for you (unless you’re in “Tutorial” mode). If you play on the hardest difficulty you’ll need to listen to the drafts and try to remember the notes as there is no visual indicator as to what was just played on the distaff.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00016.png" alt="" />
<em>Remember to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LOOK</code> at everything by double-clicking before you select and cast a draft!</em></p>

<p>Being a LucasArts adventure there’s <em>supposed to be</em> no way to die or wind up in an unwinnable situation. I did find myself getting stuck at one point because I was following a walkthrough and I apparently jumped ahead a little too quickly. At one point you need to examine a pool to learn the “Reflect” draft, but before doing this I only single-clicked and inspected the pool - then cast a draft that drained the pool.</p>

<p>As a result, I never learned the necessary draft and found myself stuck once I reached the area where I needed to steal the young boy’s identity so I could sneak into the guild of blacksmith’s.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00019.png" alt="" />
<em>You’re responsible for that boy’s brutal murder. Actions have consequences Bobbin!</em></p>

<p>Though this is a LucasArts adventure game, the themes it deals with are actually pretty dark. Once you reflect your image onto the young boy so you can sneak into the guild of blacksmith’s, the dragon you escaped from finds the boy napping and mistaking him for you, kills him out of revenge. The ghost of that child is then used to solve a puzzle a little later in the game.</p>

<p>You do “heal” the boy to bring him back to life, but this was gorier than I anticipated.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00022.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The story advances through character closeups and general on-screen exposition dumps. Unlike other adventure games of this era, none of these interactions are … interactive. You aren’t actually conversing with a character, they’re just delivering one chunk of dialogue and letting you move on.</p>

<p>Since the story progresses in an extremely linear fashion it makes sense that these interactions would as well, but it does make this game feel a little like it’s on rails.</p>

<p>The world you’re exploring is interesting and there is a lot of lore here, but you miss a good chunk of it if you don’t invest the time to listen to that audio drama.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00025.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Once you reach the endgame things actually get extremely easy. The fabric of the world is torn open and you need to go around casting (“drafting”?) <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">HEAL</code> on all the tears after healing whoever is dead/dying on the other side of the tear. You’ll then end up by the loom and Chaos will start drafting songs you need to play in reverse.</p>

<p>Finally you cast the song that turns you into a swan and that’s the end of the game.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00030.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Loom is a very interesting game with a unique game mechanic at the time. The music is all <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pyotr_Ilyich_Tchaikovsky">Tchaikovsky</a> compositions, the visuals are all excellent and the story is compelling. You really do have to invest the time to dig into all the material that comes with the game before you play it in order to truly appreciate Bobbin Threadbare’s world, but if you don’t bother then this is just a relatively simple point-and-click adventure.</p>

<p>There aren’t that many areas in this game to explore, and each area <em>maybe</em> has 2-3 action areas that you could potentially interact with. The draft you need to use on each action area is generally intuitive, so if you remembered to write them down (and wrote them down properly), it’s not hard to burn through this game.</p>

<p>I would definitely rank this title pretty low on my list of favourites when it comes to LucasArts’ catalogue, but as an entry level adventure game it’s not that bad.</p>

<h2 id="game-information">Game Information</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game</em></td>
      <td>Loom</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Developer</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LucasArts">LucasArts</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Publisher</em></td>
      <td>LucasArts</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Release Date</em></td>
      <td>January 1990</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Systems</em></td>
      <td>DOS, Mac OS, Amiga, Atari ST, FM Towns, TurboGrafx-16, Steam</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game Engine</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=SCUMM">SCUMM</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="my-playthrough">My Playthrough</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://howlongtobeat.com/game/5367"><em>How Long To Beat?</em></a></td>
      <td>3 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Version Played</em></td>
      <td>FM Towns via <a href="https://www.scummvm.org/">ScummVM</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Notes</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://adventuregamers.com/walkthrough/full/loom">Walkthrough</a>, <a href="https://www.choicestgames.com/2013/07/list-of-drafts-for-loom.html">Drafts</a>, <a href="https://archive.org/details/vgmuseum_lucasfilm_loom-manual/mode/2up">Manual</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="score">Score</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/#scoring">here</a> for a refresher on how we’re scoring these games.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Atmosphere (20)</strong></td>
      <td>14</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Story (25)</strong></td>
      <td>13</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Experience (15)</strong></td>
      <td>8</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Impact (10)</strong></td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>56%</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gallery">Gallery</h3>

<div id="inline-gallery-container" class="inline-gallery-container"></div>
<script type="module">import lightGallery from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0";import lgZoom from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/zoom";import lgThumbnail from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/thumbnail";const $lgContainer = document.getElementById("inline-gallery-container");const inlineGallery = lightGallery($lgContainer, {  container: $lgContainer,  licenseKey: "C2D2C2BD-16BC4564-A4EAE653-401CB884",  dynamic: true,  hash: false,  closable: false,  showMaximizeIcon: true,  slideDelay: 10,  plugins: [lgZoom, lgThumbnail],  dynamicEl: [{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00001.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00001.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00002.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00002.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00006.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00006.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00007.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00007.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00009.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00009.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00010.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00010.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00011.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00011.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00012.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00012.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00013.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00013.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00015.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00015.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00017.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00017.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00018.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00018.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00020.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00020.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00021.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00021.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00023.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00023.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00024.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00024.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00026.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00026.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00027.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00027.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00029.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00029.png' },]});inlineGallery.openGallery();</script>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Description from <a href="https://www.mobygames.com/game/176/loom/">Moby Games</a></small> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:1:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a> <a href="#fnref:1:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>3</sup></a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Let&apos;s Adventure!" /><category term="adventure" /><category term="LucasArts" /><category term="SCUMM" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This review is part of the “Let’s Adventure!” series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00000.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/loom/scummvm-loom-fm-00000.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Node.js Driver failing to connect due to “unsafe legacy renegotiation disabled”</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/05/node-dot-js-driver-failing-to-connect-due-to-unsafe-legacy-renegotiation-disabled/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Node.js Driver failing to connect due to “unsafe legacy renegotiation disabled”" /><published>2024-02-05T09:06:53-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-05T17:44:54-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/05/node-dot-js-driver-failing-to-connect-due-to-unsafe-legacy-renegotiation-disabled</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/02/05/node-dot-js-driver-failing-to-connect-due-to-unsafe-legacy-renegotiation-disabled/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>

<p>In <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/community/forums/t/mongoserverselectionerror-c83200000a000152-ssl-routinesunsafe-legacy-renegotiation-disabled/262568">this community forum post</a> there was a report of the <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/docs/drivers/node/current/">MongoDB Node.js driver</a> failing to connect with the following error:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MongoServerSelectionError: C8320000:error:0A000152:SSL routines:final_renegotiate:unsafe legacy renegotiation disabled:c:\ws\deps\openssl\openssl\ssl\statem\extensions.c:922</code></p>
</blockquote>

<p>This error doesn’t smell like a MongoDB-specific error, so digging into <em>“<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">final_renegotiate:unsafe legacy renegotiation disabled</code>“</em> specifically lead to <a href="https://github.com/openssl/openssl/issues/21296">this <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">openssl</code> issue</a> that looks to elaborate on the meaning of the error message:</p>

<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>TLSv1.2 (and earlier) support the concept of renegotiation. In 2009 (i.e. after the TLSv1.2 RFC was published), a flaw was discovered with how renegotiation works that could lead to an attack. After the attack was discovered a fix was deployed to all TLS libraries. In order for the fixed version of renegotiation to work both the client and the server need to support it.</p>

  <p>The original (unfixed) version of renegotiation is known as “unsafe legacy renegotiation” in OpenSSL. The fixed version is known as “secure renegotiation”. So either a peer does not have the fix, in which case it will be using <em>“unsafe legacy renegotiation”</em>, or it does have the fix in which case it will be using <em>“secure renegotiation”</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So it seems that the error originated from OpenSSL, and “that flaw” they’re alluding to was likely <a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/cve-2009-3555">CVE-2009-3555</a>. What was particularly interesting about this issue is that it <em>only</em> occurred when the application was run using Node.js 20, while Node.js 16 didn’t exhibit any issues - so what’s different between those two versions? One notable change is that <a href="https://nodejs.org/en/blog/vulnerability/openssl-november-2022">Node.js 17+ use OpenSSL 3.0 by default</a> - and starting with 3.0 <a href="https://github.com/openssl/openssl/pull/15127">secure negotiation support is required by default</a>.</p>

<p>For more information on secure server-side renegotiation I’d highly recommend <a href="https://github.com/openssl/openssl/discussions/21747">this discussion</a>.</p>

<h2 id="configuring-openssl-via-the-nodejs-driver">Configuring OpenSSL via the Node.js Driver</h2>

<p>A similar issue was reported on Stack Overflow for the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/axios"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">axios</code> library</a>, and the <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/74600467/195509">solution</a> there was to pass <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">secureOptions: crypto.constants.SSL_OP_LEGACY_SERVER_CONNECT</code> during request creation. As <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">secureOptions</code> is an option passed to Node’s <a href="https://nodejs.org/api/tls.html#tlscreatesecurecontextoptions"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">tls.createSecureContext</code></a> API (which MongoDB <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/docs/drivers/node/current/fundamentals/connection/tls/#securecontext-example">documents an example of using</a>) it should be possible to do something similar with the Node.js driver.</p>

<div class="language-js highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="rouge-gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
</pre></td><td class="rouge-code"><pre><span class="k">import</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nx">MongoClient</span> <span class="p">}</span> <span class="k">from</span> <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">mongodb</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="k">import</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="nx">crypto</span> <span class="p">}</span> <span class="k">from</span> <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">crypto</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">client</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">MongoClient</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">mongodb+srv://...</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="na">secureContext</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="na">secureOptions</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="nx">crypto</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">constants</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">SSL_OP_LEGACY_SERVER_CONNECT</span>
  <span class="p">}</span>
<span class="p">});</span>
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></div></div>

<p>SUCCESS! The above example allows a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SecureContext</code> object to be created with the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">secureOptions</code> selected from the <a href="https://nodejs.org/api/crypto.html#openssl-options">enumerated OpenSSL options Node.js has defined</a>.</p>

<blockquote class="prompt-tip">
  <p>Though the Node.js driver allows direct configuration of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SecureContext</code> object, as other <a href="https://www.mongodb.com/docs/drivers/">MongoDB drivers</a> <em>may not</em>, <a href="https://jira.mongodb.org/browse/DRIVERS-2823">DRIVERS-2823</a> is being considered to ensure this type of configuration is available.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="alternative-configuration">Alternative Configuration</h2>

<p>Configuring the MongoDB Node.js driver’s OpenSSL options directly is likely the preferred approach, but the Node runtime can also be configured (via <a href="https://nodejs.org/api/cli.html#--openssl-configfile"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--openssl-config=file</code></a>). In this, when the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">node</code> process is executed the path to a custom OpenSSL configuration file could be provided as follows:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="rouge-gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
</pre></td><td class="rouge-code"><pre>node <span class="nt">--openssl-config</span><span class="o">=</span>/path/to/openssl.conf
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></div></div>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">openssl.conf</code> is setup similar to the example below:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="rouge-gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
</pre></td><td class="rouge-code"><pre>nodejs_conf = openssl_init

[openssl_init]
ssl_conf = ssl_sect

[ssl_sect]
system_default = system_default_sect

[system_default_sect]
Options = UnsafeLegacyRenegotiation
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="MongoDB" /><category term="mongodb" /><category term="drivers" /><category term="networking" /><category term="connections" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Overview]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/mongodb-logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/mongodb-logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Innocent Until Caught (Divide By Zero) - 1993</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/01/29/innocent-until-caught/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Innocent Until Caught (Divide By Zero) - 1993" /><published>2024-01-29T06:39:02-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-30T06:56:36-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/01/29/innocent-until-caught</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/01/29/innocent-until-caught/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>This review is part of the <a href="/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/">“Let’s Adventure!”</a> series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating <a href="/blog/2021/08/08/adventure-games-1980-1999-sorted-by-score/">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Innocent_Until_Caught">Innocent Until Caught</a> is a graphic adventure game with an icon-based point-and-click interface.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_004.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Jack T. Ladd is a thief, his hunting-ground is the whole galaxy, and at the moment, he’s in big trouble. He’s got 28 days to pay his taxes - or else the interstellar tax agency will hunt him down. Termination is a viable punishment for tax offenders in these days, you know. Stranded blank on the barren, run-down planet Tayte, Jack decides that he has to make some cash. Quick.</p>

<p>Innocent Until Caught is pretty standard in terms of design but introduces some innovations when it comes to the interface. It features a mini-window at the bottom left of the screen which is alternately a mini-map of the area (showing all exits) and a looking glass for detecting small items. The inventory is a box-window in which objects can be placed wherever player wants (even on top of others). Also, the plot is illustrated by a few rendered sequences, some of the first used in adventure games.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_002.png" alt="" />
<em>Not too shabby looking for a cutscene from 1993</em></p>

<p>From the minute I started playing this game I got <a href="/blog/2023/02/10/beneath-a-steel-sky/">Beneath a Steel Sky</a> vibes. I didn’t realize that game came out a year later, so maybe I should be saying the reverse, but regardless of semantics Innocent Until Caught struck a tone with me. I am a huge sucker for games that seem to take place in either a post-apocalyptic future, a dystopian future or a cyberpunk setting.</p>

<p>This game is set in a dystopian future, but right away you’re treated to the comedic undertones that highlight the entire plot. It doesn’t take much of a stretch to envision this game having been written by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al_Lowe">Al Lowe</a> as the backdrop for a slightly darker Leisure Suit Larry adventure.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_021.png" alt="" />
<em>You know you wanna know what happens next …</em></p>

<p>Innocent Until Caught offers a pretty straightforward interface, though it overloads each interface area to perform double-duty. The bottom left area is a mini-map, however when you’re <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LOOK</code>ing at something it will tell you what you’re hovering over. The mini-map also shows all exits to the current screen you can follow, which can be clicked on if you have <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">WALK</code> selected.</p>

<p>The middle area is your action/verb bar as well as the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">STATUS</code> button. The status area gives you details about your progress and is where you can find save/load and configuration options.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_033.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Your status screen also shows a profile of Jack T. Ladd which serves absolutely no purpose until the very end of the game, at which point you can use this to change your clothes to impersonate a guard.</p>

<p>Inventory management and item combinations are a massive part of this game. The third status area of the user interface which takes up about 2/3 of the screen is the inventory. There are just so many items you can pick up throughout this game - and I’m pretty sure ALL of them are required to progress.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_016.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>If there’s one thing I have to gripe about when it comes to this game it’s the <a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=moon%20logic">moon logic</a> you need to apply to certain puzzles and item combinations. If you thought <a href="https://musingsofanitpickinggirl.wordpress.com/2018/10/15/can-we-talk-about-the-monkey-wrench-puzzle/">Monkey Island’s “Monkey Wrench”</a> puzzle was obtuse, wait until you get a load of this game.</p>

<p>Need to break into a bank? Get the plans for it from the bank first, then <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">USE</code> those plans in the sewer to find your way to an alcove that shows where the wall is the weakest. To get through that wall you’ll need to blow a hole in it. Put a mushroom in front of the alcove, then release a fly that will fly into the mushroom causing it to explode. How do you catch that fly? First find a jar and a lid (make sure to combine them when you find them). How do you get the fly in the jar? Fill it with mayonnaise of course!</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_018.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Fly flies into the mushroom and BOOM goes the wall. Well that was easy … right?</p>

<p>I’m assuming there must have been some conversational hint or observation when you <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INSPECT</code> something somewhere because I read through the <a href="http://www.replacementdocs.com/download.php?view.6546">manual</a> and didn’t find any mention of the fly … or a mushroom. The manual does give you a couple clues to some of these puzzles though like <em>“Try to find an alternative way to enter the zoo. When you do, how you smell might mean the difference between life and death.”</em></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_001.raw1.png" alt="" />
<em>Yet another feat of mental gymnastics will be required to get past this monster</em></p>

<p>Though the puzzles can be ridiculously difficult to solve, the game as a whole is pretty forgiving. I didn’t die once - not did I find myself in an unwinnable situation. I don’t actually know if it’s possible to do either of these as I’m assuming the game just doesn’t let you advance until you have all the necessary items to progress past the area you’re trying to get to.</p>

<p>I leaned on the walkthrough pretty heavily during this playthrough so I’m not 100% sure if this is the case, but whenever I tried to put Jack in danger the game just sort of told me “you can’t do that”.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_017.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>When you’re not scanning every inch of every screen to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SEE</code> if there’s an item to pick up, you can progress the plot by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">TALK</code>ing to most characters. These interactions take place in a conversation view where you typically have 3 options you can choose from in any situation. You can also inspect what you’re being told to pull out keywords from a conversation to ask more about this (the cursor will turn to a question mark when you find a keyword in a response).</p>

<p>I only used this once or twice during the game so it’s not a major mechanic, but it does add some variety to these interactions.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_023.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The writing in this game is excellent, and it’s worth noting that the themes and dialogue of Innocent Until Caught are not for kids. I think this actually drew me in more as it felt like a more mature game and it gave the writers more leeway to inject adult humour and themes throughout.</p>

<p>I was very much sucked into this game world and enjoyed <em>most</em> of the experience … but then you try to break out of jail.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_024.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The jailbreak sequence involves navigating a maze. I HATE MAZES. This was just unnecessarily drawn out because there’s nothing to do but grind your way through using trial and error until you muddle your way to the end. I’m sure there are people that genuinely enjoy mazes, but I’m not one of those people so I call them out whenever I encounter them (as I did with <a href="/blog/2023/09/06/manhunter-san-francisco/">Manhunter 2: San Francisco</a>, <a href="/blog/2023/05/31/return-to-ringworld/">Return to Ringworld</a> and <a href="/blog/2023/11/24/the-legend-of-kyrandia/">The Legend of Kyrandia: Fables and Fiends</a>).</p>

<p>Thankfully this is only one sequence and you can burn through it in about 20-30 minutes (depending on how much backtracking you have to do).</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_013.png" alt="" />
<em>If you’re unable to board the train, you’re using DOSBox and your CPU cycles are below 6000</em></p>

<p>The majority of the initial act of the game takes place in 5 different areas which are accessible by subway. Once you visit each area (by waiting for the subway to get there) you’ll be able to “fast travel” by getting on the subway at any stop, looking at the subway map and just clicking the stop you want to go to. This is EXTREMELY convenient as it allows you to bypass the drawn out subway ride between stops.</p>

<p>One issue I had with the subway was that I found myself unable to progress the first time I played this game. Every time the subway car would stop and open the doors I clicked like a maniac to get Jack to board the train cycling through every verb/action available … but nothing worked. It turns out that this is a known (but poorly documented) issue you’ll run into if playing the game via DOSBox.</p>

<p>If you want to avoid the frustration, start the game as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Launch DOSBox</li>
  <li>Increase the <a href="https://www.dosbox.com/wiki/Performance#CPU_Cycles_.28speed_up.2Fslow_down.29">CPU cycles</a> beyond 6000 (default is 3000)</li>
  <li>Run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">INNOCENT.EXE</code> to start the game</li>
</ol>

<p>You can now board the train successfully. You have to follow this sequence as increasing the cycles once the game is already running doesn’t seem to work. Once you’ve done the above you can restore a game right before you board the train and you should board successfully.</p>

<p>Note that you <em>can’t</em> change your audio configuration and then load a save state. If you do so the audio just won’t work and you’ll have to play the rest of the game in silence. This was a bit frustrating as I wanted to play through using either the Soundblaster or Roland configuration … but I started with Adlib so that’s what I rolled with.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_020.png" alt="" />
<em>The game does give you A LOT of clues as to what you may need to do next</em></p>

<p>The music is atmospheric and appropriate - though limited. There are a handful of background songs that the game will cycle through based on the screen you’re on, and the samples are pretty short so you’ll notice the looping. This is a pretty minor complaint though as the songs are pretty good.</p>

<p>Aside from some technical challenges and a maze that I could have done without, this game came as a pleasant surprise. I’ve heard of it numerous times over the years but never took the time to try it out myself - but I’m really glad I did.</p>

<p>Since there’s a sequel (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guilty_(video_game)">Guilty</a>) that came out a couple years later I’m now looking forward to when I get to tackle that title as well.</p>

<p>I’d recommend this game, though you’ll likely need a walkthrough to solve some of the puzzles. Do yourself a favour though and setup your preferred audio device before you start the game ;)</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_035.png" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="game-information">Game Information</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game</em></td>
      <td>Innocent Until Caught</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Developer</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://www.mobygames.com/company/1104/divide-by-zero-ltd/">Divide By Zero</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Publisher</em></td>
      <td>Psygnosis</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Release Date</em></td>
      <td>1993</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Systems</em></td>
      <td>DOS, Amiga</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game Engine</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=Interspective">Interspective</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="my-playthrough">My Playthrough</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://howlongtobeat.com/game/16722"><em>How Long To Beat?</em></a></td>
      <td>5 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Version Played</em></td>
      <td>DOS via <a href="https://dosbox-x.com/">DOSBox-X</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Notes</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://www.walkthroughking.com/text/innocentuntilcaught.aspx">Walkthrough</a>, <a href="http://www.replacementdocs.com/download.php?view.6546">Manual</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="score">Score</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/#scoring">here</a> for a refresher on how we’re scoring these games.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Atmosphere (20)</strong></td>
      <td>16</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Story (25)</strong></td>
      <td>19</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Experience (15)</strong></td>
      <td>11</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Impact (10)</strong></td>
      <td>9</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>79%</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gallery">Gallery</h3>

<div id="inline-gallery-container" class="inline-gallery-container"></div>
<script type="module">import lightGallery from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0";import lgZoom from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/zoom";import lgThumbnail from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/thumbnail";const $lgContainer = document.getElementById("inline-gallery-container");const inlineGallery = lightGallery($lgContainer, {  container: $lgContainer,  licenseKey: "C2D2C2BD-16BC4564-A4EAE653-401CB884",  dynamic: true,  hash: false,  closable: false,  showMaximizeIcon: true,  slideDelay: 10,  plugins: [lgZoom, lgThumbnail],  dynamicEl: [{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_000.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_000.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_001.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_001.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_002.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_002.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_003.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_003.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_003.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_003.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_004.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_004.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_005.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_005.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_005.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_005.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_006.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_006.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_006.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_006.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_007.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_007.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_007.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_007.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_008.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_008.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_008.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_008.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_009.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_009.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_009.raw1.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_009.raw1.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_010.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_010.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_011.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_011.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_012.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_012.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_014.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_014.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_015.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_015.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_019.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_019.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_022.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_022.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_025.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_025.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_026.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_026.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_027.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_027.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_028.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_028.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_029.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_029.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_030.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_030.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_031.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_031.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_032.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_032.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_034.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_034.png' },]});inlineGallery.openGallery();</script>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Description from <a href="https://www.mobygames.com/game/2086/innocent-until-caught/">Moby Games</a></small> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Let&apos;s Adventure!" /><category term="adventure" /><category term="Divide By Zero" /><category term="Psygnosis" /><category term="Interspective" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This review is part of the “Let’s Adventure!” series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_000.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/iuc/innocent_000.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Maniac Mansion: Day of the Tentacle (LucasArts) - 1993</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/01/20/day-of-the-tentacle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Maniac Mansion: Day of the Tentacle (LucasArts) - 1993" /><published>2024-01-20T07:50:30-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-01T05:55:01-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/01/20/day-of-the-tentacle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2024/01/20/day-of-the-tentacle/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>This review is part of the <a href="/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/">“Let’s Adventure!”</a> series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating <a href="/blog/2021/08/08/adventure-games-1980-1999-sorted-by-score/">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maniac_Mansion:_Day_of_the_Tentacle">Day of the Tentacle</a> is a 1993 graphic adventure game developed and published by LucasArts and is the sequel to the 1987 game Maniac Mansion. The plot follows Bernard Bernoulli and his friends Hoagie and Laverne as they attempt to stop the evil Purple Tentacle - a sentient, disembodied tentacle - from taking over the world.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00000.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Day of the Tentacle is a point-and-click adventure game and a sequel to Maniac Mansion. The player controls Bernard, and later also Hoagie and Laverne, being able to switch between them at any time. By using the commands at the bottom of the screen, the character can pick up items, use them on other things, talk to people, and more. Any of the three friends can also send his items across time to another friend.</p>

<p>The game takes place in the same area, but in three different eras, and thus affecting history takes a vital part in some puzzles. For instance, Hoagie can hide an item in the 18th century, and Laverne discovers it in the 23rd century - but by then, the item may have been affected by time and changed its properties.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00005.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I’m not going to try to hide it - Day of the Tentacle is probably one of my favourite adventure games of all time. Though it can take 6-8 hours to finish without a walkthrough, I’ve played through it enough times that I was able to burn through it in about 45-50 minutes for this article.</p>

<p>Though I’ve played it countless times, from the moment you boot it up and the title sequence starts your attention is immediately grabbed and you are sucked into this weird world where tentacles can move around and talk. If you haven’t played Maniac Mansion the existence of the tentacles won’t really make any sense (I think it’s elaborated on there), but it’s not really all that important to the advancement of the plot.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00008.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Once you gain control of Bernard you’ll have a short sequence that encourages you to explore a single room until you realize you can open the clock to find Dr. Fred’s secret lab in the basement. I think this is meant to be a sort of tutorial sequence to get players used to the verbs available (bottom left) and the inventory system (bottom right).</p>

<p>Since this is a game from 1993 the interface and layout was pretty intuitive, so I appreciate that you could quickly progress beyond the scripted sequence, meet the other two characters you’d eventually be able to control and advance the plot to the time travel subplot.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00019.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The two characters that accompany Bernard on this adventure weren’t present in Maniac Mansion - though Hoagie seems to be a cross between <a href="http://www.maniacmansionfan.50webs.com/characters.html">Jeff and Razor</a>. Hoagie finds himself sent back in time where he gets to meet the founding fathers, and Laverne is shot into the future.</p>

<p>A large part of the games mechanics is to make changes in the past to create changes in the future. For example, as soon as the Cron-O-John sends everyone their separate ways Laverne lands in a tree and gets stuck. You only get access to Hoagie and Bernard as a result as you can’t actually use Laverne until she’s free.</p>

<p>To solve this puzzle you need to get rid of that tree - but this needs to be done in the past.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00015.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Hoagie strikes up a conversation with George Washington and challenges him to see if he’s “still got it” when it comes to chopping down cherry trees. If you’re not an American (I’m not) knowing this is the solution to a puzzle might be a bit confusing, but the game only gives you so many dialogue options so it’s not that hard to figure out (also, apparently <a href="https://www.mountvernon.org/library/digitalhistory/digital-encyclopedia/article/cherry-tree-myth/">this was a myth</a>).</p>

<p>You paint the fruit on the tree red, talk to Washington, he chops the tree down and Laverne is free!</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00026.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Dr. Fred’s relatives can be found throughout the time periods and they’ll help advance the story. Your goal is to recharge the Cron-O-John in each time period and get back to the present to stop the Purple Tentacle. You’ll do this though myriad fetch quests and item puzzles.</p>

<p>Need a vacuum in the future - put a flyer in the suggestion box in the past that says all basements must have vacuums. Need a hamster in the future - put one in the ice box in the present and then thaw him out in the future and give him a sweater to warm him up.</p>

<p>Though a little contrived, these puzzles are typically pretty straightforward and the game gives you plenty of clues as to how they need to be solved.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00022.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Though I love this game it’s important to note it’s not perfect. The voice acting can be rough to listen to at times, but the writing is so good you’ll likely let this one slide. There are a handful of characters you can interact with, but most of them offer extremely limited conversation trees and typically exist as a barrier between you and some item you need for some puzzle.</p>

<p>The solution to certain puzzles requires you to be aware of certain concepts that a child likely wouldn’t understand. The notion that <em>“it always rains right after I was my car”</em> is needed to solve a puzzle in the past, but this is not something a child would be aware of and would result in the puzzle being unnecessarily complex. I played this game for the first time when I was 14 and I seem to remember getting past this just based on in-game clues, but the cause and effect of washing the carriage resulting in rain made zero sense to me then.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00031.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Day of the Tentacle is an extremely approachable adventure game for new players to the genre. It has the right mix of humor to keep the plot progression enjoyable, is well structured and balanced and doesn’t contain dead ends or unwinnable scenarios.</p>

<p>A really cool easter egg you can find is that the original Maniac Mansion game is hidden on the computer in Ed’s room. Just clicking <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LOOK</code> on the computer will allow you to play though the entire game if you want - though this didn’t work for me during this playthough. When I tried to play the embedded Maniac Mansion my instance of ScummVM crashed:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="rouge-gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
</pre></td><td class="rouge-code"><pre>Assertion failed: (endP &gt;= beginP), function BaseString, file str-base.cpp, line 118.
[1]    22698 abort      scummvm
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></div></div>

<p>I ended up have to restart from the beginning because I didn’t save my game once … oops. I also filed this with the ScummVM team as <a href="https://bugs.scummvm.org/ticket/14892"><em>#14892 - DOTT: Crash when trying to play MM on Ed’s computer</em></a>.</p>

<p>If it were possible to play more games in this series or in this universe I’d be all in, but unfortunately it doesn’t look like this will be the case anytime soon. As a result, if you haven’t played Day of the Tentacle I’d highly recommend either the original version or picking up the <a href="https://www.gog.com/index.php/en/game/day_of_the_tentacle_remastered">remastered version on GOG</a></p>

<h2 id="game-information">Game Information</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game</em></td>
      <td>Day of the Tentacle</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Developer</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LucasArts">LucasArts</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Publisher</em></td>
      <td>LucasArts</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Release Date</em></td>
      <td>June 25, 1993</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Systems</em></td>
      <td>DOS, Mac OS</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game Engine</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=SCUMM">SCUMM</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="my-playthrough">My Playthrough</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://howlongtobeat.com/game/2285"><em>How Long To Beat?</em></a></td>
      <td>6.5 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Version Played</em></td>
      <td>DOS via <a href="https://www.scummvm.org/">ScummVM</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Notes</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://www.ign.com/wikis/maniac-mansion-day-of-the-tentacle">Walkthrough</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="score">Score</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/#scoring">here</a> for a refresher on how we’re scoring these games.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Atmosphere (20)</strong></td>
      <td>18</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Story (25)</strong></td>
      <td>23</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Experience (15)</strong></td>
      <td>14</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Impact (10)</strong></td>
      <td>9</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>91%</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gallery">Gallery</h3>

<div id="inline-gallery-container" class="inline-gallery-container"></div>
<script type="module">import lightGallery from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0";import lgZoom from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/zoom";import lgThumbnail from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/thumbnail";const $lgContainer = document.getElementById("inline-gallery-container");const inlineGallery = lightGallery($lgContainer, {  container: $lgContainer,  licenseKey: "C2D2C2BD-16BC4564-A4EAE653-401CB884",  dynamic: true,  hash: false,  closable: false,  showMaximizeIcon: true,  slideDelay: 10,  plugins: [lgZoom, lgThumbnail],  dynamicEl: [{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00001.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00001.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00003.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00003.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00004.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00004.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00006.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00006.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00007.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00007.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00009.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00009.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00010.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00010.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00011.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00011.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00012.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00012.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00013.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00013.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00014.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00014.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00016.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00016.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00017.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00017.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00018.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00018.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00020.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00020.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00021.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00021.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00023.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00023.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00024.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00024.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00025.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00025.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00027.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00027.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00028.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00028.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00029.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00029.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00030.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00030.png' },]});inlineGallery.openGallery();</script>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Description from <a href="https://www.mobygames.com/game/719/maniac-mansion-day-of-the-tentacle/">Moby Games</a></small> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Let&apos;s Adventure!" /><category term="adventure" /><category term="LucasArts" /><category term="SCUMM" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This review is part of the “Let’s Adventure!” series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00002.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/dott/scummvm-tentacle-00002.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tass Times in Tonetown (Interplay Productions, Brainwave Creations) - 1986</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/27/tass-times-in-tonetown/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tass Times in Tonetown (Interplay Productions, Brainwave Creations) - 1986" /><published>2023-12-27T20:58:27-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-28T08:49:52-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/27/tass-times-in-tonetown</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/27/tass-times-in-tonetown/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>This review is part of the <a href="/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/">“Let’s Adventure!”</a> series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating <a href="/blog/2021/08/08/adventure-games-1980-1999-sorted-by-score/">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tass_Times_in_Tonetown">Tass Times in Tonetown</a> is an adventure game published by Activision in 1986. It was designed by Michael Berlyn and Muffy McClung Berlyn and programmed by Rebecca Heineman of Interplay (credited as Bill Heineman) in cooperation with Brainwave Creations.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tbqh.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Your grandfather has invented a device which makes real everything he can see in his dream. All the strange places and creatures he can dream about really exist in an alternate reality. One of those creatures, named Franklin Snarl, traveled through the device to our reality and kidnapped Gramps, teleporting him into the crazy world of Tonetown. He hopes that Gramps will always remain asleep, which assures Snarl’s own existence!</p>

<p>Now it’s up to you, the hero of the game to travel to the alternate dimension of Tonetown and to rescue your grandfather. You interact with the environment by either typing in commands, or choosing one of the action icons available as interface. The game, therefore, combines text-based interaction with the more modern “point and click” approach.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-teni.png" alt="" />
<em>Would you consider this dude “tass”?</em></p>

<p>In the fall of 1986, Apple debuted the final computer in their Apple II line, the Apple IIgs. “GS” stood for graphics and sound, and Apple needed an impressive launch title to demonstrate the machine’s new multimedia capabilities. For this, they turned to a quirky new game published by Activision and developed by Interplay, Tass Times in Tonetown, which became the first game commercially available for the Apple IIgs.<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tfhh.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The game’s opening location, an abandoned cabin, provides players a non-threatening area to familiarize themselves with its unique controls. The upper-left quadrant of the screen shows pictures of the player’s location. The pictures are mostly static, but occasionally contain simple animations. To the right of those pictures are a series of clickable “command icons” which act as shortcuts to common commands such as GET, DROP, and LOOK AT. Separating the screen horizontally is a strip that displays the player’s inventory, and a compass that can be used for navigation. The bottom portion of the screen displays detailed text descriptions and has a prompt for typing commands. The pictures and text descriptions aren’t always in sync; for example, characters are frequently mentioned in the text that don’t appear in the graphics. To find every object, players will need to scour both the graphics and the accompanying text.</p>

<p>After exploring grandfather’s cabin, players will quickly discover something is missing: grandfather. Behind a locked door, players find one of Gramps’ inventions — a magical hoop that doubles as a portal to Tonetown, a crazy, futuristic world full of people with wild haircuts and radical clothes who hang out in totally tubular locations. Everyone in Tonetown speaks in totally tass slang, a combination of Valley Girl slang and made up future babble. Denizens of Tonetown wear hooplets, strive to look Troppo, talk on floatfones, and use guitar picks for currency.<sup id="fnref:2:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tgad.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>For a launch title released for the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_IIGS">Apple IIGS</a> I have to say I’m pretty impressed with both the graphics and sound - which is what the “GS” is IIGS stands for - so I guess that’s hardly a surprise. Though there were ports to multiple platforms, I chose to play through the original IIGS release as this gave me a chance to try out <a href="https://apple2.gs/plus/">GSPLUS</a> - an emulator I’ve never had an opportunity to dig into.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231228-hnaq.png" alt="" />
<em>GSPLUS disk image configuration screen</em></p>

<p>Getting the game up and running just involved getting the emulator started (you’ll need a <a href="https://archive.org/details/Apple_II_GS_TOSEC_2012_04_23">2GS ROM set</a> first), then configured point your s5d1/d2 disk drives to the images for your game. Once set and saved, quit and restart GSPLUS and it should boot directly to the game.</p>

<p>This took me a bit of trial and error which is why I wanted to share it in the article. Having an excuse to fiddle around with some lesser known systems and emulators without having to resort to <a href="https://www.retroarch.com/">RetroArch</a> is a big part fo the fun for me when navigating this series.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tcll.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>After reading through the game’s <a href="https://retro-commodore.eu/files/downloads/amigamanuals-xiik.net/Games/Tass%20Times%20in%20Tonetown%20-%20Manual-ENG.pdf">manual</a> you get a brief synopsis of the game you’re about to play - but it’s really not super clear:</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231228-hrmf.png" alt="" />
<em>Are you tass? Are you tone? What’s “tass” or “tone” mean???</em></p>

<p>The description above actually does outline what your objective is for the game, though in the most obtuse and cryptic way imaginable. Once you boot up the disk images, you’ll find yourself in an empty cabin where the game begins. This area acts as a good training ground to get you used to the text parser, the buttons that act as shortcuts for certain verbs and the scene window.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rmge.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>You can click on the verb buttons to pre-fill the text parser, or you can click on the picture window to also prefill the parser. This is actually pretty novel for 1986 as it makes the game a lot more approachable - especially when you need to interact with a character and you don’t know their name. You can just click on them and fill in the rest.</p>

<p>The game will also show you inventory items on the screen that you can pick up. You have a limited number of inventory slots so you’ll need to leave items behind periodically to make sure you don’t run out of room. When you drop an item it will be visible on the screen, so next time you come back it’s obvious that you have left something here.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rkua.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Like any good retro text-based adventure game, it is VERY easy to die. Most puzzles only have a single solution, and require you to complete a series of fetch quests to complete. Unfortunately this game can also leave you in unwinnable situations if you forget to pick up certain items. For example, the book you can pick up in the cabin before you enter the hoop - if you leave it behind you cannot win the game, and there’s no way to go back to pick it up.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-sbuc.png" alt="" />
<em>Game over. Something about animals and evil or something …</em></p>

<p>Though the puzzles can be a bit frustrating as it’s not usually obvious <em>what</em> you need to do to progress in this game, there is so little you can interact with and so few screens to navigate it’s not all that difficult to brute-force your way through. The game gives you multiple save slots, so you can easily save every few screens, look at everything, pick up everything, buy everything and wear everything.</p>

<p>Eventually you’ll find Gramps, save him from an island fortress, take him to Snarl’s and push Snarl back through the hoop. This sets everything back to normal and the game ends there.</p>

<p>Since I didn’t have an Apple II (or GS) as a kid I was never exposed to this game, so I have no hidden fondness for it. It looks and sounds pretty good for what it is, and the game engine (called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ADVENT</code> in the about screen, but apparently also <a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=Mindshadow">Mindshadow</a>) was used for a couple other games of that era.</p>

<p>This game has a bit of a cyberpunk feel to it, but in the opposite way. Though it’s futuristic and “punky”, everything is extremely bright, upbeat and vibrant. I honestly really enjoyed the aesthetic, even if the story itself didn’t really resonate with me.</p>

<p>If you enjoy parser-based adventure games this is not a bad entry and is quite approachable. The music is better than I expected, the visuals are better than I expected - but the gameplay was a bit boring.</p>

<h2 id="game-information">Game Information</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game</em></td>
      <td>Tass Times in Tonetown</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Developer</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interplay_Productions">Interplay Productions</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brainwave_Creations">Brainwave Creations</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Publisher</em></td>
      <td>Activision</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Release Date</em></td>
      <td>1986</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Systems</em></td>
      <td>Atari ST, Amiga, Apple II, Apple IIGS, Commodore 64, DOS, Macintosh</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game Engine</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=Mindshadow">Mindshadow</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="my-playthrough">My Playthrough</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>How Long To Beat?</em></td>
      <td>5 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Version Played</em></td>
      <td>Apple IIGS via <a href="https://apple2.gs/plus/">GSPLUS</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Notes</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://www.walkthroughking.com/text/tasstimesintonetown.aspx">Walkthrough</a>, <a href="https://retro-commodore.eu/files/downloads/amigamanuals-xiik.net/Games/Tass%20Times%20in%20Tonetown%20-%20Manual-ENG.pdf">Manual</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="score">Score</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/#scoring">here</a> for a refresher on how we’re scoring these games.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Atmosphere (20)</strong></td>
      <td>13</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Story (25)</strong></td>
      <td>11</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Experience (15)</strong></td>
      <td>6</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Impact (10)</strong></td>
      <td>2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>46%</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gallery">Gallery</h3>

<div id="inline-gallery-container" class="inline-gallery-container"></div>
<script type="module">import lightGallery from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0";import lgZoom from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/zoom";import lgThumbnail from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/thumbnail";const $lgContainer = document.getElementById("inline-gallery-container");const inlineGallery = lightGallery($lgContainer, {  container: $lgContainer,  licenseKey: "C2D2C2BD-16BC4564-A4EAE653-401CB884",  dynamic: true,  hash: false,  closable: false,  showMaximizeIcon: true,  slideDelay: 10,  plugins: [lgZoom, lgThumbnail],  dynamicEl: [{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tbgh.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tbgh.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tbxn.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tbxn.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tccy.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tccy.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tevd.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-tevd.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-thwz.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-thwz.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-timo.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-timo.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rjkd.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rjkd.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rkig.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rkig.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rlog.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rlog.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rmyk.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rmyk.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rnki.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-rnki.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-sagh.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-sagh.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-saxq.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-saxq.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-sbpn.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-sbpn.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-sbwq.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231227-sbwq.png' },]});inlineGallery.openGallery();</script>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Description from <a href="https://www.mobygames.com/game/90/tass-times-in-tonetown">Moby Games</a></small> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Except(s) from <a href="https://www.everythingamiga.com/2020/10/all-that-blitters-tass-times-in-tonetown.html">All That Blitters: Tass Times in Tonetown</a></small> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a> <a href="#fnref:2:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;<sup>2</sup></a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Let&apos;s Adventure!" /><category term="adventure" /><category term="Interplay Productions" /><category term="Brainwave Creations" /><category term="Activision" /><category term="Mindshadow" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This review is part of the “Let’s Adventure!” series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-hfmu.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/tass/SCR-20231223-hfmu.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Combine GoPro Files with FFmpeg</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/21/combine-gopro-files-with-ffmpeg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combine GoPro Files with FFmpeg" /><published>2023-12-21T09:14:28-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-21T09:55:45-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/21/combine-gopro-files-with-ffmpeg</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/21/combine-gopro-files-with-ffmpeg/"><![CDATA[<p>I have a <a href="https://gopro.com/en/ca/shop/cameras/hero10-black/CHDHX-101-master.html">HERO10 Black</a> that I use to record video from my kids hockey games (<a href="https://youtu.be/nvAMBfcpHJY">such as this one</a>), but since I typically move around with the camera between periods, the videos end up being “chaptered”, or multiple single videos. Though you’d think you could just sort these files by filename, GoPro’s <a href="https://community.gopro.com/s/article/GoPro-Camera-File-Naming-Convention?language=en_US">file naming convention</a> doesn’t actually lend itself well to this, and doing so results in out of sequence video.</p>

<p>For example, a recent video that I took had a directory listing like the following:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="rouge-gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22
23
</pre></td><td class="rouge-code"><pre>$ ll

-rwx------  1 alex  staff   265M 20 Dec 19:14 GL010118.LRV
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   265M 20 Dec 19:35 GL010119.LRV
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   265M 20 Dec 20:08 GL010120.LRV
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   194M 20 Dec 19:22 GL020118.LRV
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   234M 20 Dec 19:46 GL020119.LRV
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   265M 20 Dec 20:20 GL020120.LRV
-rwx------  1 alex  staff    48M 20 Dec 20:22 GL030120.LRV
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 19:14 GX010118.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff    10K 20 Dec 19:02 GX010118.THM
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 19:35 GX010119.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff    10K 20 Dec 19:24 GX010119.THM
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 20:08 GX010120.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff    10K 20 Dec 19:56 GX010120.THM
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   2.7G 20 Dec 19:22 GX020118.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff    10K 20 Dec 19:14 GX020118.THM
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.3G 20 Dec 19:46 GX020119.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff    10K 20 Dec 19:35 GX020119.THM
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 20:20 GX020120.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff    10K 20 Dec 20:08 GX020120.THM
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   696M 20 Dec 20:22 GX030120.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff    10K 20 Dec 20:20 GX030120.THM
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></div></div>

<p>GoPro creates additional <a href="https://community.gopro.com/s/article/What-are-thm-and-lrv-files?language=en_US"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LRV</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">THM</code> files</a> when recording video so that you can quickly preview thumbnails and video on the camera itself. If we filter these out and just view the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MP4</code> files you’ll see these aren’t necessarily in order:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="rouge-gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
</pre></td><td class="rouge-code"><pre>$ ls *.MP4

-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 19:14 GX010118.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 19:35 GX010119.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 20:08 GX010120.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   2.7G 20 Dec 19:22 GX020118.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.3G 20 Dec 19:46 GX020119.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 20:20 GX020120.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   696M 20 Dec 20:22 GX030120.MP4
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></div></div>

<p>An easy way to get the videos into a “correct” order would be to sort them chronologically by create date:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="rouge-gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
</pre></td><td class="rouge-code"><pre>$ ll -tr *.MP4

-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 19:14 GX010118.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   2.7G 20 Dec 19:22 GX020118.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 19:35 GX010119.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.3G 20 Dec 19:46 GX020119.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 20:08 GX010120.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   3.7G 20 Dec 20:20 GX020120.MP4
-rwx------  1 alex  staff   696M 20 Dec 20:22 GX030120.MP4
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></div></div>

<p>Since I want to upload these videos to YouTube for the team to review, I need a single video file. After hunting around for scripts that could do this for me, I did find a few that looked promising - such as <a href="https://github.com/scuc/GoPro-Concat-Automation">GoPro-Concat-Automation</a> and <a href="https://github.com/KonradIT/gopro-linu">gopro-linux</a>. Ultimately I wanted to be able to just do this myself with a single command, so though these tools got me most of the way there, I ended up opting for my own script instead:</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><table class="rouge-table"><tbody><tr><td class="rouge-gutter gl"><pre class="lineno">1
2
3
4
5
</pre></td><td class="rouge-code"><pre><span class="c"># run from the directory where your videos are located</span>
<span class="c"># ex: /Volumes/SDCARD/DCIM/100GOPRO/</span>
ffmpeg <span class="nt">-f</span> concat <span class="nt">-safe</span> 0 <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-i</span> &lt;<span class="o">(</span><span class="k">for </span>f <span class="k">in</span> <span class="sb">`</span><span class="nb">ls</span> <span class="nt">-tr</span> <span class="k">*</span>.MP4<span class="sb">`</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">do </span><span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"file '</span><span class="nv">$PWD</span><span class="s2">/</span><span class="nv">$f</span><span class="s2">'"</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">done</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="se">\</span>
    <span class="nt">-c</span> copy output.mp4
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></pre></div></div>

<p>This uses <a href="https://ffmpeg.org/">FFmpeg</a> to concatenate the videos and copy them to a new file called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">output.mp4</code>. The input list for the videos is just a bash command to generate a list of MP4 files with the full path to the file in chronological order by create date.</p>

<p>Note that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">safe</code> mode is disabled (see <a href="https://www.ffmpeg.org/ffmpeg-formats.html#Options"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ffmpeg</code> options</a>) as having it enabled can result in the video creation failing for file-naming reasons. Why is this enabled by default and not disabled you might ask … <a href="https://trac.ffmpeg.org/ticket/5558">#5558 <em>concat protocol should run in “-safe 0” mode by default</em></a> has more info on that topic.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="video" /><category term="ffmpeg" /><category term="video" /><category term="scripting" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have a HERO10 Black that I use to record video from my kids hockey games (such as this one), but since I typically move around with the camera between periods, the videos end up being “chaptered”, or multiple single videos. Though you’d think you could just sort these files by filename, GoPro’s file naming convention doesn’t actually lend itself well to this, and doing so results in out of sequence video.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/camera-banner.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/camera-banner.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Police Quest III: The Kindred (Sierra On-Line) - 1991</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/16/police-quest-iii/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Police Quest III: The Kindred (Sierra On-Line) - 1991" /><published>2023-12-16T08:34:11-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T06:33:37-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/16/police-quest-iii</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/16/police-quest-iii/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>This review is part of the <a href="/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/">“Let’s Adventure!”</a> series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating <a href="/blog/2021/08/08/adventure-games-1980-1999-sorted-by-score/">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Police_Quest_III:_The_Kindred">Police Quest III: The Kindred</a> is a 1991 police procedural point-and-click adventure video game developed and published by Jim Walls and Sierra On-Line.</p>

<p>Sonny Bonds, the sergeant of Lytton police department, thought he could finally enjoy peaceful life with his wife Marie after the drug lord Jessie Bains has been put away for good. However, a series of gruesome murders perpetrated by a sinister cult known as “The Kindred” shocks the city. Marie becomes a victim of their attack and falls into a coma. It becomes Sonny’s very personal mission to track down the attackers and make them pay for their crimes.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00035.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The Kindred is the third installment of the Police Quest series, its events taking place after those described in <a href="/blog/2023/02/21/police-quest-2/">Police Quest II: The Vengeance</a>. The game brings back some of the elements of the first game, such as a modified version of driving sequences and police procedures unrelated to the main plot the protagonist must go through. Computer work is particularly emphasized, requiring the player to perform tasks such as using facial composite software or figuring out murder patterns by studying a map. Like other Sierra adventures of the time, the game uses an icon-based interface for interaction with the environment.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00002.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Sonny has been promoted following the events of Police Quest II, and the game starts off with you giving a briefing to the other detectives to kick things off. There are multiple narrative threads in this title which gives it some additional depth, and you dive right into one of them as soon as the game starts. Detective Pat Morales has apparently got a complaint lodged against her for use of abusive language. Since these games are effectively police procedure simulators, you’re going to need to start off by interviewing her, then deciding what to do about said complaint and file the appropriate paperwork.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00005.png" alt="" />
<em>Picking the wrong option when filing paperwork can lead to a game over</em></p>

<p>Following the proper protocol at all times is a requirement to being successful in any Police Quest game, and luckily for you these protocols are well documented in the game’s <a href="https://archive.org/details/Police_Quest_3_-_Manual">manual</a>. There are all sorts of procedures outlined here such as how to handle felony situations, obtaining entry into private property, courtroom procedures and forceful entry into dwellings. If it’s in the manual, you’re likely going to need to do it at some point in the game so it’s not a bad idea to do the reading up front so you know what you’re dealing with.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00013.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Detective Morales will prove to be a pain in your ass throughout the game. Once you find your way downstairs on the first day and get into the squad car you’ll have to drive out to observe a failure to sign, as the driver that the detective pulled over doesn’t want to sign a citation because the officer was being rude. Yup … it’s Morales again.</p>

<p>This is another segment of the game where you’re presented with a couple options as to how you can respond, and if you pick the wrong one - it’s game over. You can send the pregnant woman to jail (which is what Detective Morales suggests), but doing so gets the department sued for $1 million and you lose your job (game over).</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00041.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Being a Sierra game, expect almost every decision you make to potentially result in death. This actually makes the game a little easier to complete as exercising good game save hygiene will allow you to trial-and-error your way through most scenarios. Just save, try something, fail, reload, try the other option and move along … rinse and repeat.</p>

<p>You’ll still need to pay attention and take notes though - especially when characters mention things like case numbers, serial numbers and addresses.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00028.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>There’s a computer you’ll need to use to look up case details or search for items by serial number. These pieces of information are typically mentioned during conversations with other characters and may only be referenced once. If you miss a case number when the chief is briefing you, it may not be available again and you’ll have to reload a previous save and repeat the conversation to get that piece of information (or use a walkthrough).</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00032.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The computer is actually used for a number of scenarios in this game. My favourite is the scene where you bring a homeless woman back to the office because she claims she saw someone suspicious and wants to describe them to you. Instead of a police artist generating a composite image based on her description, you use the computer to generate a face based on her prompts. This is actually kind of fun and breaks up some of the monotony of police procedure.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00026.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Along with the ongoing issues with Detective Morales (who ends up being assigned as your partner on Day 2) is the subplot involving the attempted murder of your wife. Mary is stabbed in the parking lot of the mall, and your captain knows you won’t rest until the case is solved so he assigns it to you to investigate.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00039.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Investigating the case involves a lot of driving back and forth between locations and the police station. The tedious manual driving from <a href="/blog/2022/03/15/police-quest-1/">Police Quest: In Pursuit of the Death Angel</a> is back, but this time without any visual differentiation on the map (as the VGA remake of PQ1 provided). You just drive in a direction and wait for the road signs to tell you where you are - and if you’re approaching a location.</p>

<p>I did not enjoy this at all. It honestly felt like filler most of the time and was there to slow you down.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00021.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>You’ll have to deal with a handful of highway patrol scenarios early on, which aren’t too difficult but require you to drive back and forth until the relevant event triggers. You’ll also have to drive back and forth to various locations and the police station to advance the story as the game progresses. There is a lot of driving in this game, and honestly I would have appreciated a “fast travel” type of option near the end …</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00046.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The locations you drive to will require investigation, and this involves more police procedure (properly collecting and handling evidence). You have a field kit in the trunk of your car that you need to open and take everything out of each time you visit a crime scene. Once you collect and bag evidence you need to return the field kit items back to the kit before you can leave the scene. This just seems like something they could have automated for you, as it artificially delays you from progressing to get a message like “You can’t get into the car until you return the field kit items to their respective slots in the kit”, or something like that.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00023.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>After each scene you will either return to the police station or the hospital. If you go back to the station you’ll either be booking a perpetrator (if you arrested someone) or booking evidence. When booking evidence you’ll need to enter the case number the evidence belongs to, so make sure you’ve taken note of these. If you book a perp, you’ll need to provide the correct booking code. These are all in the manual, so you just need to make sure you pick the right one (it’s not that hard).</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00037.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The subplot about your wife actually leads into a thread about multiple murders that have some kind of occult ties to them. You’ll need to keep track of the locations of these murders as there’s a final segment on the computer where you need to plot the crimes on a map of the city and draw a pattern to try to tie them together. Assuming you do this correctly you’ll draw a pentagram that will give you the location of the final crime scene.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00044.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>It’ll come as no surprise that Detective Morales is tied up in all of this (there are signs throughout the game). The game also manages to link the series antagonist (Jesse Bains) to this game as well by introducing his brother near the end as being affiliated with one of the perpetrators you were trying to hunt down.</p>

<p>Though I may not love the driving in this game and find it overused, the strong story more than makes up for it. This is no surprise as the game was written by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jane_Jensen">Jane Jensen</a>, who would also go on to write <a href="/blog/2023/06/14/gabriel-knight-sins-of-the-fathers/">Gabriel Knight: Sins of the Fathers</a>, so you know you’re in for some twists and turns and a sprinkling of the occult.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00051.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I have very fond memories of this game, and I really enjoyed going back to it - but it’s not as good as I remembered. Though there are a lot of digitized sound effects, and occasionally there is background music most of the time you just have generic background noise. The driving segments of the game are overused and just make everything feel slower as a result.</p>

<p>You do get to use the gun near the end of the game (exactly twice), but it’s not really obvious either time that this is necessary until you die and are prompted that maybe you should be “more prepared” next time.</p>

<p>Although I did find some aspects of this game entertaining, overall I was just trying to get to the end so that I could move on. If not for the strong story I would probably recommend skipping this game, but if you’ve played the first 2 entries in the series you might as experience the conclusion of Sonny Bonds’ story arc.</p>

<h2 id="game-information">Game Information</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game</em></td>
      <td>Police Quest III: The Kindred</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Developer</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sierra_Entertainment">Sierra On-Line</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Publisher</em></td>
      <td>Sierra On-Line</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Release Date</em></td>
      <td>1991</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Systems</em></td>
      <td>DOS, Amiga</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game Engine</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=SCI">SCI</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="my-playthrough">My Playthrough</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://howlongtobeat.com/game/7195"><em>How Long To Beat?</em></a></td>
      <td>4.5 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Version Played</em></td>
      <td>DOS via <a href="https://www.scummvm.org/">ScummVM</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Notes</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://gamerwalkthroughs.com/police-quest-3-the-kindred/">Walkthrough</a>, <a href="https://archive.org/details/Police_Quest_3_-_Manual">Manual</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="score">Score</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/#scoring">here</a> for a refresher on how we’re scoring these games.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Atmosphere (20)</strong></td>
      <td>10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Story (25)</strong></td>
      <td>20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Experience (15)</strong></td>
      <td>7</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Impact (10)</strong></td>
      <td>4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>59%</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gallery">Gallery</h3>

<div id="inline-gallery-container" class="inline-gallery-container"></div>
<script type="module">import lightGallery from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0";import lgZoom from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/zoom";import lgThumbnail from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/thumbnail";const $lgContainer = document.getElementById("inline-gallery-container");const inlineGallery = lightGallery($lgContainer, {  container: $lgContainer,  licenseKey: "C2D2C2BD-16BC4564-A4EAE653-401CB884",  dynamic: true,  hash: false,  closable: false,  showMaximizeIcon: true,  slideDelay: 10,  plugins: [lgZoom, lgThumbnail],  dynamicEl: [{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00001.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00001.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00003.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00003.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00004.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00004.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00006.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00006.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00007.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00007.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00008.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00008.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00009.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00009.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00010.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00010.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00011.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00011.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00012.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00012.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00014.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00014.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00015.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00015.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00016.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00016.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00017.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00017.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00018.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00018.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00019.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00019.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00020.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00020.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00022.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00022.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00024.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00024.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00025.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00025.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00027.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00027.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00029.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00029.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00030.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00030.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00031.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00031.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00033.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00033.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00034.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00034.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00036.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00036.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00038.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00038.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00040.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00040.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00042.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00042.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00043.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00043.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00045.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00045.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00047.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00047.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00048.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00048.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00049.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00049.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00050.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00050.png' },]});inlineGallery.openGallery();</script>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Description from <a href="https://www.mobygames.com/game/148/police-quest-3-the-kindred/">Moby Games</a></small> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Let&apos;s Adventure!" /><category term="adventure" /><category term="Sierra On-Line" /><category term="SCI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This review is part of the “Let’s Adventure!” series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00000.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/pq3/scummvm-pq3-00000.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Dark Crystal (On-Line Systems) - 1983</title><link href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/08/the-dark-crystal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dark Crystal (On-Line Systems) - 1983" /><published>2023-12-08T11:59:49-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T19:43:25-05:00</updated><id>https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/08/the-dark-crystal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2023/12/08/the-dark-crystal/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="prompt-info">
  <p>This review is part of the <a href="/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/">“Let’s Adventure!”</a> series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating <a href="/blog/2021/08/08/adventure-games-1980-1999-sorted-by-score/">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dark_Crystal_(video_game)">The Dark Crystal</a> is a graphic adventure game based on Jim Henson’s 1982 fantasy film, The Dark Crystal. The game was designed by Roberta Williams and was the first Hi-Res Adventure directly released under the SierraVenture label in 1983.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00004.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The Dark Crystal is closely based on Jim Henson’s film of the same name. The game is set in Thra, a world with three suns, which come together every thousand years in an event known as “The Great Conjunction”. The player controls Jen, the last survivor of the Gelfings, a race of mole-like people. He must find a dark crystal and its broken shard, and repair it to end the reign of a tyrannical lord.</p>

<p>Like other installments of the Hi-Res Adventures series, the game is entirely text-based, with non-animated graphics to illustrate the areas. Movement between areas and interaction with the game world is performed by typing commands consisting of either one or two words (a combination of a verb and an object).<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00010.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>You interact with the game world via the text parser. Though the verb/noun combinations you need to identify to progress from screen to screen are pretty easy to figure out, I did find myself getting stuck on occasion when the game expected an obtuse sequence of commands. Navigation is handled by going in a direction (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">EAST</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NORTH</code>) and typically when you enter a new screen (or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LOOK</code> at it) everything you need to know or interact with is called out pretty clearly.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00019.png" alt="" />
<em>This screen took me forever to get past</em></p>

<p>This game follows the plot of the movie <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dark_Crystal">The Dark Crystal</a>, so I’m guessing if you’re a fan - or have seen it recently - maybe some of these puzzles would make a bit more sense. There is one section where you need to get into the castle where the solution is to get <a href="https://darkcrystal.fandom.com/wiki/Fizzgig_(Character)">Fizzgig</a> to climb through the bars of a door to get a key that’s on the other side.</p>

<p>On the surface this type of puzzle isn’t really challenging, but up to this point in the game you have not had to interact with a multi-part prompt where you issue multiple commands with <em>no feedback</em> after entering the first. You have to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SEND FIZZGIG</code> through the bars, but when you send him it just says something like “Where?”. The response is then <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SEND BARS</code> (or maybe just <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">BARS</code>) but if you do this wrong you have to start over and it’s not clear you were even on the right track to begin with.</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00015.png" alt="" />
<em>Oh look, I’ve died again</em></p>

<p>Being such an early adventure game I’m ok with slightly obtuse puzzles, and being a Sierra game, I expect death around every corner. And you will die on most screens.</p>

<p>Though there isn’t any music throughout the game and limited sound effects, the scene drawing for a game released in 1983 really isn’t that bad. My main complaint would be that there are so few colours presented that it’s basically monochrome, but this is likely due to the Apple II only having 6 colors to choose from (Ken Williams would enhance the ADL interpreter to support dithering and expand that palette to 21 colours<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>).</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00023.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>There are a handful of items you can pick up and use throughout the game, but these are few and far between. It does vary the gameplay a little and add some depth to a couple puzzles. Unlike later Sierra titles you won’t find yourself overwhelmed with options, and every item you pick up is almost immediately useful, so try everything you pick up on the screen you found it!</p>

<p><img src="/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00025.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The movie this game is based on isn’t something I have fond memories of (or really any memory of), so playing through this game doesn’t really stir up any nostalgia. I’m sure it follows the plot pretty closely, and if you enjoyed the movie you’ll likely enjoy the game.</p>

<p>For a very early graphical adventure game it’s definitely well done and really shows off the power of the ADL engine. If you’re an interactive fiction fan you’ll likely enjoy this experience, but otherwise this one’s probably not worth playing through.</p>

<h2 id="game-information">Game Information</h2>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game</em></td>
      <td>The Dark Crystal</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Developer</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-Line_Systems">On-Line Systems</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Publisher</em></td>
      <td>On-Line Systems</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Release Date</em></td>
      <td>1983</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Systems</em></td>
      <td>Apple II, Atari 8-bit</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Game Engine</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php?title=ADL">ADL</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="my-playthrough">My Playthrough</h3>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://howlongtobeat.com/game/57460"><em>How Long To Beat?</em></a></td>
      <td>3 hours</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Version Played</em></td>
      <td>Apple II via <a href="https://www.scummvm.org/">ScummVM</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Notes</em></td>
      <td><a href="https://www.sierrachest.com/index.php?a=games&amp;id=199&amp;title=dark-crystal&amp;fld=walkthrough&amp;pid=100">Walkthrough</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="score">Score</h3>

<p>See <a href="https://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2021/07/28/adventure-games-1980-1999/#scoring">here</a> for a refresher on how we’re scoring these games.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Atmosphere (20)</strong></td>
      <td>9</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Story (25)</strong></td>
      <td>13</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Experience (15)</strong></td>
      <td>6</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Impact (10)</strong></td>
      <td>3</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td> </td>
      <td><strong>31%</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="gallery">Gallery</h3>

<div id="inline-gallery-container" class="inline-gallery-container"></div>
<script type="module">import lightGallery from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0";import lgZoom from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/zoom";import lgThumbnail from "https://cdn.skypack.dev/lightgallery@2.4.0/plugins/thumbnail";const $lgContainer = document.getElementById("inline-gallery-container");const inlineGallery = lightGallery($lgContainer, {  container: $lgContainer,  licenseKey: "C2D2C2BD-16BC4564-A4EAE653-401CB884",  dynamic: true,  hash: false,  closable: false,  showMaximizeIcon: true,  slideDelay: 10,  plugins: [lgZoom, lgThumbnail],  dynamicEl: [{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00001.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00001.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00002.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00002.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00003.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00003.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00005.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00005.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00006.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00006.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00007.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00007.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00008.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00008.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00009.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00009.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00011.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00011.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00012.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00012.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00013.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00013.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00014.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00014.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00016.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00016.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00017.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00017.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00018.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00018.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00020.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00020.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00021.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00021.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00022.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00022.png' },{ src: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00024.png', thumb: '/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00024.png' },]});inlineGallery.openGallery();</script>

<p><strong>Footnotes</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small>Description from <a href="https://www.mobygames.com/game/16877/hi-res-adventure-6-the-dark-crystal/">Moby Games</a></small> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><small><a href="https://sierrachest.com/index.php?a=engines&amp;id=18">The Sierra Chest</a></small> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Let&apos;s Adventure!" /><category term="adventure" /><category term="On-Line Systems" /><category term="ADL" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This review is part of the “Let’s Adventure!” series. See all reviewed games sorted by rating here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00000.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.alexbevi.com/images/adventure/dark/scummvm-hires6-apple2-00000.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>