<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: jrpg | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/jrpg/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-29T04:36:37-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summer RPG Update 2016]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/09/05/summer-update-2016/"/>
        <updated>2016-09-05T14:08:29-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/09/05/summer-update-2016</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I don't really have much progress to report for the last month, so I thought I'd throw out a few of the games I've been working through to see if I can generate any interest in the next article ;)

<img class="left" src="/images/goldensun/goldensun.016.png">

First off, I've been playing through [Golden Sun](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Sun) for the GBA.

I really like the psyenergy system and how you use it for puzzle solving. It makes this game a bit more of an ARPG along the same lines as [Lufia 2](/blog/2015/09/23/just-finished-lufia-2/).

I've made it as far as [Kraken](http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Kraken), but I'm finding beating him is proving to be more difficult that I'd expected. Probably going to have to back out and grind for a while, which I don't have a lot of time for ...

<img class="right" src="/images/7th-saga/7th-saga.019.png">

Next, I'm pretty sure I've given up on [the 7th Saga](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7th_Saga). I'm still at Telaine with a party at level 17, but I'm pretty sure that to progress, there is grinding in my future.

Similar to the situation I'm having above with Golden Sun, i just need to set many hours aside to level up in order to proceed, but with the amount of time I've got these days to devote to these games, that may never happen.

<!-- more -->

Finally, I've decided to bite the bullet and dive into [Super Mario RPG](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Mario_RPG). This, along with Final Fantasy Tactics is one of those games that I've heard nothing but good things about for the last 20 years, but have never bothered to investigate myself.

<img class="left" src="/images/mariorpg/mariorpg.011.png">

I'm currently at level 10 with 3 star pieces recovered and have just rescued Princess Toadstool and had her join the party.

I'm really enjoying the story and gameplay, but since this was developed by Square, I'm not surprised that this is right up my alley :P

I'm most likely going to be able to finish this game off, and then circle back around to Golden Sun, as I really want to beat that game.

Now, assuming I can make some progress on those two games, I'd like to start getting some feedback on where to take this series next.

There are a number of games that I've finished previously that I didn't write about. Some of the more notable ones would be:

* [Mother 3](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother_3)
* Final Fantasy VIII
* Final Fantasy IX
* Chrono Trigger

Then there's the list of games that I really want to tackle, but since they all require a sizable time investment I'm not sure which to hit up:

* Xenogears
* Breath of Fire 3
* [Shin Megami Tensei: Persona 3](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shin_Megami_Tensei:_Persona_3) - *I'd likely play the PSP release*
* [Danganronmpa](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danganronpa:_Trigger_Happy_Havoc) - *I started this a while back but never finished it*
* [Shin Megami Tensei 2](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shin_Megami_Tensei_II) - *There's a great fan translation of the Super Famicom release*
* [Final Fantasy IV: After Years](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_IV:_The_After_Years)
* [Vagrant Story](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vagrant_Story)

If you've got any insight into which I should tackle next, feel free to leave me a comment below ;)
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Dragon Quest I]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/07/27/just-finished-dragon-quest-i/"/>
        <updated>2016-07-27T22:26:01-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/07/27/just-finished-dragon-quest-i</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I actually finished this game around the end of June, but haven't really had a chance to write about it until now. I'm currently sitting out by the lake at the cottage and figured it was about time :P

<img class="left" src="/images/dq1/dq1.000.png">

The last time I played through Dragon Quest was likely in the late 80's. I'm pretty sure I either heard about it, or got a copy of it through Nintendo Power, and like most kids in North America at the time, this would have been my first introduction to what would become known as JRPGs.

I decided to go with the SNES re-release of this title for my playthrough as I wanted some updated graphics and music. Although the SNES version was never officially localized for North America, there is an [excellent fan translation](http://www.romhacking.net/translations/337/) available.

It threw me off a bit when they refer to the legendary hero as Roto (as opposed to Erdrick), but I'm assuming this is a better translation than what we got in the 80's so that's probably what the name should have been in the first place.

<img class="right" src="/images/dq1/dq1.001.png">

Dragon Quest was essentially the first JRPG. As a result, there are a lot of concepts introduced here that would be adapted and refined by other titles and series over the years. This means that some parts of this game feel a bit rough or unbalanced.

I originally played the NES version of this title, and have fond memories of just how brutally hard it was. This game introduced me to what I would come to know as "grinding", as you couldn't progress through the game unless your character was sufficiently leveled up in order to tackle the monsters in the areas you were exploring.

This meant walking back and forth and fighting random monsters. 

Enemy encounter rates are high. Very high. I think the SNES version actually optimized this a bit, but the rates are still high. This is useful for grinding, but gets tedious when you want to explore, or really need to get back to a town to heal.

The story is pretty simple.

You're the descendant of the legendary hero, and have been tasked with rescuing the princess and defeating the Dragon Lord.

<!-- more -->

<img class="left" src="/images/dq1/dq1.001.png">

To defeat the Dragon Lord, you need to get three pieces of equipment of the legendary hero which are scattered across the world.

Beat the dragon. Save the princess. Beat the Dragon Lord. Done.

Gameplay is pretty straightforward. You start off in the castle, where the king explains your quest. You can talk to people in the castle, or leave and move on to the nearest town.

Here you'll get a bit more info, or can buy supplies.

I think it's kind of cool that the first time you leave the castle you can see the Dragon Lord's castle on the world map. This gives you your target right away and you know what you're working towards.

You interact with NPCs and the world via a command menu. One of the nice additions to the SNES version is that you no longer have to use a STAIRS command to go up and down stairs; just walk over them.

<img class="right" src="/images/dq1/dq1.012.png">

As you roam around the overworld and dungeouns, you'll get into random encounters. You interact with these using a command menu as well, where you can select to either attack, use magic, use an item, or run. 

Dragon Quest is a pretty short game. Being one of the first of this genre it introduced a lot of gameplay elements that would shape the genre, but when you look at it as a standalone title, there's not all that much there.

This isn't meant to be a knock at the game. I had a great time playing through it, but that playthrough was only a few hours.

I used an emulator to do this, so most of my level grinding was done in fast-forward, so it felt even faster to get through this title.

If you're playing the "classics", I'd definitely recommend this title. Playing these early games gives you more of an appreciation for the later RPGs, as well as giving you a feel for how it all started.

Have you had a chance to play this title? How do you think it holds up nowadays, especially with the release of the mobile ports? Have any DQ memories you want to share? Let me know in the comments.

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.000.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.000.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.001.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.001.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.002.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.002.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.003.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.003.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.004.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.004.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.005.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.005.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.006.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.006.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.007.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.007.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.008.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.008.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.009.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.009.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.010.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.010.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.011.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.011.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.012.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.012.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.013.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.013.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.014.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.014.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.015.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.015.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.016.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.016.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.017.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.017.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.018.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.018.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.019.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.019.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.020.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.020.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.021.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.021.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.022.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.022.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.023.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.023.png" /><img src="/images/dq1/dq1.024.png" data-title=" /images/dq1/dq1.024.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Seiken Densetsu 3]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/04/19/just-finished-seiken-densetsu-3/"/>
        <updated>2016-04-19T14:30:20-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/04/19/just-finished-seiken-densetsu-3</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="left" src="/images/sd3/sd3.026.png">

[Seiken Densetsu 3 (聖剣伝説3)](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seiken_Densetsu_3) is the third installment in the [Mana series](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mana_\(series\)). It's the sequel to [Secret of Mana](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_of_Mana), which is the entry into the series that most North American gamers would be familiar with.

Once again, I played through this game on my phone using the fantastic [Snes9x EX](http://www.explusalpha.com/home/snes9x-ex). Please support this dev as he provides a fantastic product. For some reason though, most of the screenshots I took came out stretched. This hasn't happened before, and I've been playing a couple other games that this isn't happening for either, so I'll chalk this up to bad luck :|

<img src="/images/sd3/sd3.005.png">

*NOTE* I ran these screenshots through [pngcrush](http://pmt.sourceforge.net/pngcrush/) (`ls *.png | while read line; do pngcrush -ow -brute $line; done`) to get the size down a bit ;)

I'm leaving these images in here as they were part of my "journey", though hopefully they don't deter anyone from playing this game, as the game is *fantastic*.

First off, if you're a fan of [Secret of Mana](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_of_Mana), the initial "feel" of the game will be familiar, as will the art style and sound.

<!-- more -->

Whereas SoM had you gradually encounter the two other playable characters at set points in the game, SD3 has you selecting your 3 main characters before you even begin.

I decided to go with Duran, Carlie and Kevin (something about a werewolf named Kevin made me chuckle :P). Duran's story starts off with the castle where he lives being invaded by a wizard who almost kills him. The wizard lets Duran live, so naturally Duran has to set off on a quest to find and defeat the wizard.

<img src="/images/sd3/sd3.004.png">

On this journey, he'll run into the other characters I selected (Kevin and Carlie), and each of their stories will mix into Duran's. This is actually a really cool element of this game as it gives it a lot of replay value. No matter what combination of characters you pick, their stories will all overlap. Also, you'll run into all the other characters you didn't pick, so every character makes an appearance throughout the game.

<img class="right" src="/images/sd3/sd3.010.png">

You travel around the game mostly on foot initially, but eventually new methods of travel will open up. As with SoM, you can get to certain areas via Cannon Travel (though there's a couple of fetch-quests before you can actually take advantage of this). There's also a ship, a weird turtle thing, and eventually Flammie the dragon.

The combat system is reminiscent of SoM as well, though this time around it feels a lot more "button mash-ey". I found that I just spammed the B button throughout most of this game and didn't really use any strategy during combat; aside from healing periodically.

<img class="left" src="/images/sd3/sd3.014.png">

You get experience by killing enemies, which will allow you to level up your characters. Leveling up lets you increase various stats, that should make your characters perform better in future battles.

As you make your way through the game, you'll start finding these pillars that are guarded by stronger enemies. These are the Mana stones, and apparently contain God-beasts that will be awakened if you shatter the stones.

These stones can also be used to change your character's class. This is another cool aspect of this game, as it give the leveling system a bit more flavour. You can change classes twice in this game; once at level 18, and again at level 38. Each of these classes is aligned with either "Light" or "Dark", and gives the character new skills/improvements.

<img src="/images/sd3/sd3.017.png">

The game can feel a bit "grindy" due to the need to constantly trudge back and forth between areas, and there are enemies on each screen. These battles are all avoidable, but you'll want to level up for the boss fights, and eventually the God Beasts.

While you're trekking though, you get to enjoy some really good background music. If you like Secret of Mana, you'll love Seiken Densetsu 3. You can have a listen over at [YouTube](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qrywwZ7oL2w&index=30&list=PL4649F0DBF0FC09E3) to get an idea what's in store for you ;)

<img class="right" src="/images/sd3/sd3.031.png">

The artwork is also top notch. It's really a shame this game never made it to North America as this is possibly one of the best looking SNES games out there. The background design, character design and monster sprites are all very, very well done. There is a lot of variety to the various regions of the world.

Once you've shattered all the Mana stones, you unleash the God Beasts. Their position is shown on the world map, and they can be fought in any order, but it's a good idea to start from the top left of the map and work your way through them sequentially.

I learned this the hard way as I only play this game on occasion, and ended up forgetting where I was. This resulted in A LOT of backtracking to find the last couple of beasts.

I thoroughly enjoyed playing this game and would highly recommend this to anyone out there that likes JRPGs, action RPGs and 8/16-bit gaming in general. The graphics, music and gameplay are all very well done, and the story lines are interesting, even if there is occasionally some cheesy dialog :P

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.000.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.000.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.001.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.001.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.002.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.002.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.003.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.003.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.006.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.006.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.007.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.007.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.008.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.008.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.011.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.011.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.012.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.012.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.013.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.013.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.015.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.015.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.016.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.016.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.018.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.018.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.019.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.019.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.020.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.020.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.021.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.021.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.022.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.022.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.023.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.023.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.024.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.024.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.025.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.025.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.027.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.027.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.028.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.028.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.029.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.029.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.030.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.030.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.032.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.032.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.033.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.033.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.034.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.034.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.035.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.035.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.036.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.036.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.037.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.037.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.038.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.038.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.039.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.039.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.040.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.040.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.041.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.041.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.042.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.042.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.043.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.043.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.044.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.044.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.045.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.045.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.046.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.046.png" /><img src="/images/sd3/sd3.047.png" data-title="/images/sd3/sd3.047.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>

I finished this game over a month ago, so I'm still pretty slow cranking out these reviews ...

I'm currently working my way through [The 7th Saga](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7th_Saga) for SNES since I clearly need *more* pain and frustration in my life :P When that game is annoying me, I'm also working on Sega Genesis version of [Shadowrun](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadowrun_\(1994_video_game\)).

That game was recommended by some of my readers on Reddit so I figured I had to give it a whirl. So far I'm actually really enjoying it, and it is VERY different the the SNES game of the same name.

Hopefully I'll have more for you in the near(er) future :)
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Final Fantasy V]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/11/07/just-finished-final-fantasy-v/"/>
        <updated>2015-11-07T19:15:57-05:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/11/07/just-finished-final-fantasy-v</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="right" src="/images/ffv/ffv.001.png">

I've been waiting write this review for a very long time. I love the Final Fantasy series, and although I got the original back in '90, I didn't really fall in love with the series until I played IV for the SNES. Then I played VI. Then I was REALLY hooked.

Since I didn't grow up in Japan, FF IV and VI were numbered II and III when I first got my hands on them. This means that I didn't know there was a [Final Fantasy V](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_V); at least not until much later.

The game starts off with the king of Tycoon heading off to check on the wind crystal, only to watch it shatter. The hero Bartz (Butz when I played the fan translation :P) sees a meteorite fall from the sky and heads off to investigate. Bartz and his Chocobo go to check it out, and find an old man who's suffering from amnesia.

The king's daughter, Lenna, heads out to find her father and runs into Bartz and Galuf. They team up and the adventure begins.

<img class="left" src="/images/ffv/ffv.003.png">

Once at the wind shrine, they find that the crystal has shattered and within each shard is the power of a job class.

This introduces you to the job ability system. If you've ever had a chance to play [Final Fantasy III](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_III), you've see this system in action, but in FFV, it's done to perfection :)

<!-- more -->

Each character can be assigned to a job class. As they defeat enemies, they gain ability points, which levels up the job class. As the classes level up, you gain abilities associated with that class.

These abilities can then be applied to a character regardless of the class they're assigned to. For example, you can give a white mage black magic abilities (if you've leveled up a black mage for that character).

This gives you a lot of control over how you build your characters as the game progresses.

<img class="right" src="/images/ffv/ffv.002.png">

The storytelling in this game is very well done. Although the plot is pretty standard Final Fantasy fare (crystals, amnesia, evil emperor, main characters dying), the writing was pretty good and the character emotion pop-ups added a nice touch as well.

I enjoyed the elements of comedy they tried to incorporate into some of the scenarios and characters. After playing this game, Gilgamesh is probably my new favourite non-player character in the series. This might also have to do with [Clash on the Big Bridge](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6CMTXyExkeI)
being my favourite song from this game ;)

<img class="left" src="/images/ffv/ffv.022.png">

The battle system is the same as in FFIV ([Active Time Battle system](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Battle_System#Active_Time_Battle)). You can fight, use items, or up to 2 abilities you've learned from gaining AP and leveling up your classes.

I didn't find the battles overly difficult during this play-through, but I've been focusing a lot on grinding in the last few games I've covered, so this could just be a result of me over leveling.

So as you progress through the game, you discover that the ultimate evil, Exdeath, was banished to your world by the four warriors of dawn. Now you and your party need to become the new warriors of dawn to fight him again.

<img class="right" src="/images/ffv/ffv.046.png">

You have to get the ultimate weapons for each character class, you can go on some side quests to get some powerful summons and eventually go after Exdeath.

There is one fight in Exdeath's tower that I just couldn't win, and that was [Shinryu](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Shinryu_(Final_Fantasy_V)). I didn't bother to upgrade my equipment after a while as I just hoarded my money to use Gil Toss against everybody. As a result, Shinryu just decimated me every time I tried ... so I just gave up.

I found that magic and summons in this game proved to be effective until the very end. This is different than my experience with FF II, where you bust your ass to get Ultima, then it does like 900 damage to enemies (even after being leveled up a few times :|).

I thought the story was really compelling, and I found the whole alternate worlds overlapping "thing" to be a nice twist, though it felt a bit like what happened in FF III. Actually, just like FF III, you even have to race a chocobo around the world to get an item ...

<img class="left" src="/images/ffv/ffv.037.png">

I teared up (just a bit) when Galuf's flame was extinguished by Exdeath. I was a bit worried that since this game follows FF IV it was possible they would do the whole "everyone who died is magically back to fight again for no reason" that happened with Yang, Cid, Edward, Tellah ... etc. Fortunately (?), this wasn't the case and it's actually a very emotional point in the story.

I would strongly recommend any fan of JRPGs spend some time on this title. If I were ranking my favourite FFs now, Final Fantasy V would probably show up in the top 5 :)

As for where I'm going from here, I'm currently about 6-8 hours into [Pokémon Emerald](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pok%C3%A9mon_Emerald). I'm sort of enjoying it, though it feels like a watered down version of [Earthbound](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EarthBound) (just my initial impression).

I'm also about 4-5 hours into [Tales of Destiny](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tales_of_Destiny), but I'm not really enjoying this title and likely won't go back to it.

Feel free to leave me some feedback on whether or not I should continue the above, or if you've got a recommendation for the next title I tackle.

Cheers!

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.000.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.000.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.004.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.004.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.005.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.005.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.006.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.006.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.007.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.007.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.008.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.008.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.009.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.009.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.010.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.010.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.011.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.011.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.012.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.012.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.013.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.013.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.014.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.014.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.015.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.015.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.016.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.016.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.017.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.017.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.018.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.018.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.019.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.019.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.020.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.020.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.021.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.021.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.023.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.023.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.024.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.024.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.025.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.025.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.026.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.026.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.027.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.027.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.028.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.028.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.029.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.029.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.030.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.030.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.031.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.031.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.032.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.032.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.033.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.033.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.034.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.034.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.035.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.035.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.036.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.036.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.038.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.038.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.039.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.039.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.040.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.040.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.041.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.041.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.042.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.042.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.043.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.043.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.044.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.044.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.045.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.045.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.047.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.047.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.048.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.048.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.049.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.049.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.050.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.050.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.051.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.051.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.052.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.052.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.053.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.053.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.054.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.054.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Lufia 2]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/09/23/just-finished-lufia-2/"/>
        <updated>2015-09-23T20:04:59-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/09/23/just-finished-lufia-2</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.000.png">

This review has been a long time coming; a *VERY* long time coming. I heard about [Lufia 2: Rise of the Sinistrals](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia_II:_Rise_of_the_Sinistrals) when I was still in high school, and have been meaning to play it ever since.

Back then, I was just starting to get into JRPGs (though I probably just thought they were RPGs at the time) and was completely infatuated with anything that Square or Enix could crank out (except for [Earthbound](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EarthBound), which is still one of my all-time faves).

In the decade(s) since my teens, I've picked up Lufia 2 a good dozen times, but have never really given it a fair shake. This time around though, since I'm doing this "Just Finished" series, I thought I'd finally sit down and do a full playthrough.

For anyone that has not played this game: PLAY IT! Lufia 2 is now in the top 10 of my favourite 16-bit JRPGs of all time. Hopefully after reading my synopsis here, anyone that was on the fence will also take the plunge (you'll thank me later!).

<!-- more -->

## Overview

Lufia 2 (aka. Estpolis Denki II, aka. エストポリス伝記II) is a hybrid of traditional JRPG and [Action RPG](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Action_role-playing_game). You control one to four characters at a time throughout the adventure, with enemy encounters being handled via fade-away to a turn-based combat system.

It turns out you (Maxim) are destined to fight the Sinistrals, so you embark on a journey to save the world. Cliché? Yup :P

Don't get me wrong, I love a good "destined to save the world" story, but after playing a handful of JRPGs in succession, I was getting a bit numb to the same story over and over again.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.026.png">

I decided to give this a fair chance though, and went along with it. I had never played the original [Lufia](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia) for more than 5-10 minutes, but I do remember the intro segment where you have the four heroes already in the Fortress of Doom getting ready to fight the Sinistrals.

I'm going to skip around a bit here because I just want to cover one thing, which is the end of the game ... first. The final battle with Daos for Maxim, Artea, Guy and Selan is the EXACT scene from the first game. This made me REALLY want to go back and play the first game, as I now had a connection with the characters.

Also, I thought I was a really cool transition as it tied the two games together seamlessly.

### Combat

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.032.png">

Enemy encounters on the overworld are random. As you're walking around, suddenly the screen will zoom in and boom, it's go time! For anyone familiar with JRPGs, this is pretty common.

Unlike traditional RPGs, Lufia 2 doesn't have "random" encounters in dungeons. All enemies are visible as you explore the dungeons, and though most will chase you, a lot of these battles can be avoided if you so choose.

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.005.png">

Once a battle is initiated, as opposed to a text-based menu of `Fight | Magic | Item | Run` as you might see in some games, you're presented with an icon cross (reminiscent of [Breath of Fire](/blog/2015/06/10/just-finished-breath-of-fire/)).

Aside from the standard Attack, Item and Magic options, there is also and Abilities option for each party member. This additional entry gives each character access to various offensive or defensive abilities that are linked to their weapons and armour. This adds another dimension to battles as you have to keep track of what skills are linked to your equipment (don't just hit 'optimize' each time) as weaker items may provide added benefits against certain enemies.

### Puzzles

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.004.png">

What I really enjoyed about this game from the moment I entered the first dungeon was the puzzles. Littered throughout each dungeon are puzzles that you need to solve in order to open a door and proceed.

Generally, these puzzles aren't all that complex, but they break up the dungeons a bit so it doesn't feel monotonous as you basically do the same things over and over in order to progress the story.

As you move further through the game, you also collect various key items, that can be used in order to help solve the various puzzles (bombs, arrows, hook shot, etc.)

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.021.png">

These add another dimension to the puzzles that keeps them interesting. I honestly didn't find most puzzles to be very challenging, but I will admit to having to use a walkthrough for at least 2 of them ... (thankfully there are excellent [guides on rpgclassics](http://shrines.rpgclassics.com/snes/lufia2/puzzles.shtml) for just these instances where you need a tiny bit of help)

### Party

Your party is made up of Maxim, and at various points Tia, Guy, Selan, Dekar and Arty.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.019.png">

Tia is from your home village and follows you on the initial leg of the quest. You think she's going to end up being Maxim's love interest, but that changes once Selan enters the story ;)

Maxim and Selan fall in love, get married, and have a baby. This all happens around the mid-point of the game, acting as a bit of an intermission. Once they have the kid, they decide to go back out and fight so that the world is safe for their baby (and everyone else ... I guess).

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.028.png">

Guy joins as he's a good fighter and wants to help defeat the Sinistrals. Dekar's reasons are basically the same.

### Capsule Monsters

Your party can also include capsule monsters. These are optional encounters throughout the game that if you seek out result in an additional character being able to join you in battle.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.018.png">

Each monster has an elemental affiliation, and can level up with you as you fight enemies. If the capsule monster dies in battle though, they respawn for the next fight, so there's no need to worry about their health (you can't heal them). They do tend to run from a lot of battles automatically though, which can be annoying.

Capsule monsters can also be made stronger by leveling them up through feeding them weapons, armour and items.

This got a bit annoying as I had to hear a lot of "Yuk"s from the monsters while trying to find the right items to feed them.

### Music

I just quickly wanted to touch on the music in this game. For a JRPG not composed by [Nobuo](http://vgmdb.net/artist/77), the soundtrack is pretty solid.

If you've got a minute, check out a couple of songs below to get a taste of what's in store for you ;)

* [Final Battle](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-Fzm2O4Zt-k&index=44&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48)
* [Peace of Mind](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7E-AD-OUxKg&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=10)
* [The Lost World](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fk3omXPfuVM&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=41)
* [Battle Theme 3](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BLIrE5ivseQ&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=46)

In case you're wondering, composition credit goes to [Yasunori Shiono](http://vgmdb.net/artist/313).

### Ancient Cave

This is a completely optional dungeon, but if you're going to play Lufia 2, you HAVE to try and clear it ;)

The ancient cave is 99 randomly generated floors, and you start the cave at level 1 (no matter where you actually are in the game). As you level up and descend further into the cave, you find various treasures and spells that you can only use within the cave.

If you warp out, you lose all experience and items you've found; aside from items in blue chests (which are few).

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.038.png">

Once you make it to the last level of the cave, you fight the Master Jelly. This is a brutal fight, as you only have 3 turns in order to beat him, and if you don't, he just runs and that's the end of it (you have to warp out).

Note that I basically cheated to beat him. If you can kill your entire party before he runs, you'll actually win the fight.

I did this, but I didn't find all the Iris Treasures in the cave so it didn't really matter.

## Summary

As great as you probably think I think this game is by now, it is not without its faults.

First off, this game is *extremely* linear. The plot progresses as follows:

* Go to <tower name> tower to find <plot point>
* Climb tower and fight enemy
* Go back to town to learn where next town is
* Go to shrine to advance to next town

Sure you get a boat at a certain point and it "opens" up the map, but you still basically go from town to town and tower to tower without much variety.

Also, it may be that I'm just a bit more experienced in the genre and know how to level grind, but I found this game to be very, very easy. By the final dungeon, every battle was essentially the same (the final boss included): fight, fight, valor, fight.

All in all though, I really enjoyed this game. Although the story seemed like it was going to be pretty basic at the outset turned out the be really compelling.

There was actually quite a bit of character development. I think this is why at the end when you realize you're basically setting up the intro of Lufia I, you really want to go back and play that game to see if the story continues to be as strong.

I'll probably give this game another run through in a few years, as it really was enjoyable. I tend to do this with RPGs i enjoy as I forget specifics of the story over the years and enjoy rediscovering them. Final Fantasy IV and VI have had this treatment now probably a good 4-5 times each ;)


<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.001.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.001.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.002.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.002.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.003.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.003.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.006.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.006.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.007.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.007.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.008.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.008.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.009.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.009.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.010.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.010.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.011.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.011.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.012.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.012.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.013.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.013.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.014.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.014.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.015.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.015.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.016.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.016.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.017.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.017.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.020.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.020.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.022.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.022.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.023.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.023.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.024.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.024.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.025.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.025.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.027.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.027.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.029.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.029.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.030.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.030.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.031.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.031.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.033.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.033.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.034.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.034.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.035.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.035.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.036.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.036.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.037.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.037.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.039.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.039.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.040.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.040.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.041.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.041.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.042.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.042.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.043.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.043.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.044.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.044.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.045.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.045.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.046.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.046.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.047.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.047.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.048.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.048.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.049.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.049.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.050.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.050.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.051.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.051.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.052.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.052.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.053.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.053.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.054.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.054.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.055.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.055.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.056.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.056.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.057.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.057.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.058.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.058.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.059.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.059.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.060.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.060.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.061.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.061.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>

<br/>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
