<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: jrpg | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/jrpg/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-20T22:21:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Lufia 2]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/09/23/just-finished-lufia-2/"/>
        <updated>2015-09-23T20:04:59-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/09/23/just-finished-lufia-2</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.000.png">

This review has been a long time coming; a *VERY* long time coming. I heard about [Lufia 2: Rise of the Sinistrals](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia_II:_Rise_of_the_Sinistrals) when I was still in high school, and have been meaning to play it ever since.

Back then, I was just starting to get into JRPGs (though I probably just thought they were RPGs at the time) and was completely infatuated with anything that Square or Enix could crank out (except for [Earthbound](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EarthBound), which is still one of my all-time faves).

In the decade(s) since my teens, I've picked up Lufia 2 a good dozen times, but have never really given it a fair shake. This time around though, since I'm doing this "Just Finished" series, I thought I'd finally sit down and do a full playthrough.

For anyone that has not played this game: PLAY IT! Lufia 2 is now in the top 10 of my favourite 16-bit JRPGs of all time. Hopefully after reading my synopsis here, anyone that was on the fence will also take the plunge (you'll thank me later!).

<!-- more -->

## Overview

Lufia 2 (aka. Estpolis Denki II, aka. エストポリス伝記II) is a hybrid of traditional JRPG and [Action RPG](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Action_role-playing_game). You control one to four characters at a time throughout the adventure, with enemy encounters being handled via fade-away to a turn-based combat system.

It turns out you (Maxim) are destined to fight the Sinistrals, so you embark on a journey to save the world. Cliché? Yup :P

Don't get me wrong, I love a good "destined to save the world" story, but after playing a handful of JRPGs in succession, I was getting a bit numb to the same story over and over again.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.026.png">

I decided to give this a fair chance though, and went along with it. I had never played the original [Lufia](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia) for more than 5-10 minutes, but I do remember the intro segment where you have the four heroes already in the Fortress of Doom getting ready to fight the Sinistrals.

I'm going to skip around a bit here because I just want to cover one thing, which is the end of the game ... first. The final battle with Daos for Maxim, Artea, Guy and Selan is the EXACT scene from the first game. This made me REALLY want to go back and play the first game, as I now had a connection with the characters.

Also, I thought I was a really cool transition as it tied the two games together seamlessly.

### Combat

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.032.png">

Enemy encounters on the overworld are random. As you're walking around, suddenly the screen will zoom in and boom, it's go time! For anyone familiar with JRPGs, this is pretty common.

Unlike traditional RPGs, Lufia 2 doesn't have "random" encounters in dungeons. All enemies are visible as you explore the dungeons, and though most will chase you, a lot of these battles can be avoided if you so choose.

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.005.png">

Once a battle is initiated, as opposed to a text-based menu of `Fight | Magic | Item | Run` as you might see in some games, you're presented with an icon cross (reminiscent of [Breath of Fire](/blog/2015/06/10/just-finished-breath-of-fire/)).

Aside from the standard Attack, Item and Magic options, there is also and Abilities option for each party member. This additional entry gives each character access to various offensive or defensive abilities that are linked to their weapons and armour. This adds another dimension to battles as you have to keep track of what skills are linked to your equipment (don't just hit 'optimize' each time) as weaker items may provide added benefits against certain enemies.

### Puzzles

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.004.png">

What I really enjoyed about this game from the moment I entered the first dungeon was the puzzles. Littered throughout each dungeon are puzzles that you need to solve in order to open a door and proceed.

Generally, these puzzles aren't all that complex, but they break up the dungeons a bit so it doesn't feel monotonous as you basically do the same things over and over in order to progress the story.

As you move further through the game, you also collect various key items, that can be used in order to help solve the various puzzles (bombs, arrows, hook shot, etc.)

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.021.png">

These add another dimension to the puzzles that keeps them interesting. I honestly didn't find most puzzles to be very challenging, but I will admit to having to use a walkthrough for at least 2 of them ... (thankfully there are excellent [guides on rpgclassics](http://shrines.rpgclassics.com/snes/lufia2/puzzles.shtml) for just these instances where you need a tiny bit of help)

### Party

Your party is made up of Maxim, and at various points Tia, Guy, Selan, Dekar and Arty.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.019.png">

Tia is from your home village and follows you on the initial leg of the quest. You think she's going to end up being Maxim's love interest, but that changes once Selan enters the story ;)

Maxim and Selan fall in love, get married, and have a baby. This all happens around the mid-point of the game, acting as a bit of an intermission. Once they have the kid, they decide to go back out and fight so that the world is safe for their baby (and everyone else ... I guess).

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.028.png">

Guy joins as he's a good fighter and wants to help defeat the Sinistrals. Dekar's reasons are basically the same.

### Capsule Monsters

Your party can also include capsule monsters. These are optional encounters throughout the game that if you seek out result in an additional character being able to join you in battle.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.018.png">

Each monster has an elemental affiliation, and can level up with you as you fight enemies. If the capsule monster dies in battle though, they respawn for the next fight, so there's no need to worry about their health (you can't heal them). They do tend to run from a lot of battles automatically though, which can be annoying.

Capsule monsters can also be made stronger by leveling them up through feeding them weapons, armour and items.

This got a bit annoying as I had to hear a lot of "Yuk"s from the monsters while trying to find the right items to feed them.

### Music

I just quickly wanted to touch on the music in this game. For a JRPG not composed by [Nobuo](http://vgmdb.net/artist/77), the soundtrack is pretty solid.

If you've got a minute, check out a couple of songs below to get a taste of what's in store for you ;)

* [Final Battle](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-Fzm2O4Zt-k&index=44&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48)
* [Peace of Mind](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7E-AD-OUxKg&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=10)
* [The Lost World](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fk3omXPfuVM&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=41)
* [Battle Theme 3](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BLIrE5ivseQ&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=46)

In case you're wondering, composition credit goes to [Yasunori Shiono](http://vgmdb.net/artist/313).

### Ancient Cave

This is a completely optional dungeon, but if you're going to play Lufia 2, you HAVE to try and clear it ;)

The ancient cave is 99 randomly generated floors, and you start the cave at level 1 (no matter where you actually are in the game). As you level up and descend further into the cave, you find various treasures and spells that you can only use within the cave.

If you warp out, you lose all experience and items you've found; aside from items in blue chests (which are few).

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.038.png">

Once you make it to the last level of the cave, you fight the Master Jelly. This is a brutal fight, as you only have 3 turns in order to beat him, and if you don't, he just runs and that's the end of it (you have to warp out).

Note that I basically cheated to beat him. If you can kill your entire party before he runs, you'll actually win the fight.

I did this, but I didn't find all the Iris Treasures in the cave so it didn't really matter.

## Summary

As great as you probably think I think this game is by now, it is not without its faults.

First off, this game is *extremely* linear. The plot progresses as follows:

* Go to <tower name> tower to find <plot point>
* Climb tower and fight enemy
* Go back to town to learn where next town is
* Go to shrine to advance to next town

Sure you get a boat at a certain point and it "opens" up the map, but you still basically go from town to town and tower to tower without much variety.

Also, it may be that I'm just a bit more experienced in the genre and know how to level grind, but I found this game to be very, very easy. By the final dungeon, every battle was essentially the same (the final boss included): fight, fight, valor, fight.

All in all though, I really enjoyed this game. Although the story seemed like it was going to be pretty basic at the outset turned out the be really compelling.

There was actually quite a bit of character development. I think this is why at the end when you realize you're basically setting up the intro of Lufia I, you really want to go back and play that game to see if the story continues to be as strong.

I'll probably give this game another run through in a few years, as it really was enjoyable. I tend to do this with RPGs i enjoy as I forget specifics of the story over the years and enjoy rediscovering them. Final Fantasy IV and VI have had this treatment now probably a good 4-5 times each ;)


<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.001.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.001.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.002.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.002.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.003.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.003.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.006.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.006.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.007.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.007.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.008.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.008.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.009.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.009.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.010.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.010.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.011.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.011.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.012.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.012.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.013.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.013.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.014.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.014.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.015.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.015.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.016.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.016.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.017.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.017.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.020.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.020.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.022.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.022.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.023.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.023.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.024.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.024.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.025.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.025.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.027.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.027.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.029.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.029.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.030.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.030.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.031.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.031.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.033.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.033.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.034.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.034.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.035.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.035.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.036.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.036.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.037.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.037.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.039.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.039.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.040.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.040.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.041.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.041.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.042.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.042.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.043.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.043.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.044.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.044.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.045.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.045.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.046.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.046.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.047.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.047.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.048.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.048.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.049.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.049.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.050.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.050.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.051.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.051.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.052.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.052.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.053.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.053.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.054.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.054.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.055.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.055.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.056.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.056.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.057.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.057.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.058.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.058.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.059.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.059.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.060.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.060.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.061.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.061.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>

<br/>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Final Fantasy II]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/07/22/just-finished-final-fantasy-ii/"/>
        <updated>2015-07-22T13:21:52-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/07/22/just-finished-final-fantasy-ii</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="center" src="/images/ff2/ff2-box.jpg">

I'm excited to finally be able to review this game, as it's the direct sequel to the game that got me into RPGs way back in 1990-91.

When I say Final Fantasy II, I literally mean the second game in the franchise; not the [SNES translation of Final Fantasy IV](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_IV#North_American_localization) ;)

I actually played a bit of this game in the late 90's using the [Demiforce](http://www.romhacking.net/translations/139/) translation patch (back in the good ol' [NESticle](http://bloodlust.zophar.net/NESticle/nes.html) days :D), but didn't make it very far.

For the actual play-through, I decided to go with the [Dawn of Souls](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Final_Fantasy_I_%26_II:_Dawn_of_Souls) version for GBA, as this includes updated graphics, an "official" translation and an updated soundtrack.

<!-- more -->

Note that since I'm reviewing a remake, I'm not sure if some of the gameplay elements below were available in the original. If you happen to have actually completed the original NES version and spot an error, please let me know ;)

<h4>Story</h4>

The story is pretty standard JRPG fare. The Emperor of Palamecia is trying to take over the world. He summons some monsters that destroy the home town of Firion, Maria, Guy and Leon. The first three are rescued by a rebel faction and taken to another town (where they join the rebellion).

Leon goes missing. The party wants to find him. Off they go.

<img class="left" src="/images/ff2/ff2.010.png">

You'll meet various characters along the way that will join your party and fight with you. (**SPOILERS!** they usually die by sacrificing themselves so you can continue the quest ...)

As you go along, you find out more about the Emperors plan, fight with the Dark Knight who turns out the be Leon, have him join up with you and eventually make your way down to the castle of hell (aka Pandaemonium) to fight the Emperor.

<h4>What's Cool</h4>

<img class="right" src="/images/ff2/ff2.004.png">

FFII introduces a couple of interesting gameplay elements that were not reused in any future entries in the series.

First, key character conversations allowed you to *Learn* keywords, which you could then *Ask* other key characters about. This mechanic helps advance the story as you have to ask various characters about plot points you learn as you go, and they then point you in the direction of your next objective.

<img class="left" src="/images/ff2/ff2.009.png">

FFII has multiple modes of travel on the overworld. As with the original, there are ships and an airship, but FFII introduces the [chocobo](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chocobo).

There is also a bunch of "cut-scenes" added to this incarnation (which would not have been available in the original NES version). These are nice as they aren't excessive or long, but help advance the plot.

<img class="right" src="/images/ff2/ff2.005.png">

Instead of leveling up your characters by fighting and gaining EXP, FFII opted for a system where the more you use a skill, the better you get at it.

For example, the more Firion attacks with a sword, the higher his sword level would go. The more Maria uses the Cure spell, the higher her magic level ... and Cure spell level would go.

This also applied to taking damage. The more damage a player took, the higher their strength and HP levels would go.

I thought this was a very interesting mechanic, and I'm not really sure why this didn't make it into any future games.

<h4>What's Not Cool</h4>

<img class="left" src="/images/ff2/ff2.019.png">

For some reason, this installation in the series decided to introduce an Inn system that charged based on how much healing you required. This proved to be a bit annoying until you realize it's a LOT cheaper to just use cure spells to get everyone's HP back up, THEN rest at the inn ;)

<img class="right" src="/images/ff2/ff2.031.png">

Another annoyance is that throughout the game, in *any* dungeon you visit, there are doors that lead to empty rooms. LOTS of doors that lead to empty rooms. What's annoying is that these rooms have higher encounter rates, so the first step you take to head back towards the exit generally results in a battle.

The battles aren't necessarily difficult, it's just a pain in the ass to have to wade through all these useless rooms.

On battles in general, once again I'm happy to be playing this game using an emulator, as the 8x fast-forward was my best friend.

The encounter rates in this game seem to be pretty high in most areas, and the fights are kind of sluggish. I found that for most non-boss fights, I'd just hit fast-forward and hold down the A button (thankfully, you don't have to mash A in this game; just holding it down works :D).

<h4>Summary</h4>

Overall, I really enjoyed the game. The story (I feel) was much better than that of the original, or even [FF III](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_III) (not [FF VI](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_VI), which is still my favourite installment in the series!)

I really liked the leveling system, and found that since I didn't run from many fights, I didn't have to game the system by just attacking my own party members to boost their HP/defense/stamina stats.

I'm glad I jumped back into the Final Fantasy series for a bit; especially with a game I actually haven't beaten before. Whenever I sit down with FF, it's usually either IV, VI or VII.

I'm thinking the next Final Fantasy I tackle will likely be V, as I haven't previously finished this (though I've gotten close). Not sure when that'll happen, because I'm currently balls-deep in [Lufia II](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia_II:_Rise_of_the_Sinistrals) ;)

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.000.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.000.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.001.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.001.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.002.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.002.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.003.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.003.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.006.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.006.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.007.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.007.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.008.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.008.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.011.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.011.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.012.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.012.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.013.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.013.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.014.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.014.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.015.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.015.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.016.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.016.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.017.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.017.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.018.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.018.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.020.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.020.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.021.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.021.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.022.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.022.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.023.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.023.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.024.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.024.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.025.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.025.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.026.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.026.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.027.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.027.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.028.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.028.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.029.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.029.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.030.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.030.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.032.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.032.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.033.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.033.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.034.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.034.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.035.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.035.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.036.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.036.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>
<br />

Note that since I've finished the Dawn of Souls version of FFII, I have access to the [Soul of Rebirth](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Soul_of_Rebirth) additional dungeon. 

I'm hoping to actually play this and add to this review, or just publish a minor post to cover what was added therein.]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Breath of Fire 2]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/29/just-finished-breath-of-fire-2/"/>
        <updated>2015-06-29T13:17:02-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/29/just-finished-breath-of-fire-2</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[Following on the heels of my playthrough of the original Breath of Fire, I've just finished [Breath of Fire II](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breath_of_Fire_II).

Originally released for the Super Nintendo Entertainment System in 1994, BoF2 is the direct sequel to the original. Although the protagonist is named the same (Ryu) as in the original, I don't think he's supposed to be the same person (the story takes place hundreds of years after the original).

<img class="left" src="/images/bof2/bof2.000.png">

You start off as a kid in a small town with your buddy Bow. You go visit the outskirts of town where there is a dragon sleeping and blocking a gate. You're attacked by a demon named Barubary, who knocks the two out then disappears.

The story picks up 10 years later with the two trying to make it as rangers and taking odd jobs. You take a job trying to find someone's lost pet, and from there, the game begins.

You save the pet (pig) in an old house where a hermit lives. This house introduces an interesting dynamic to the game as this becomes the location known as TownShip. As you make your may through the game, various people join your town or can be hired to improve it. 

<img class="right" src="/images/bof2/bof2.002.png">

You can recruit builders, weapon/item shop keepers and magicians that teach you new skills and abilities. Also as your party grows, they can be stashed here in a big house and you can go talk to them at any point to get clues as to what needs to be done next.

<!-- more -->

The battle system is the same as the original, and most JRPGs of the era; enemies to the left, characters to the right. A menu system controls your actions, which should all be well known by now (Attack, Defend, Magic, Item, Run).

<img class="left" src="/images/bof2/bof2.028.png">

As you progress, you will learn that Ryu is a member of the Dragon Clan (as was the case in the original BoF as well), and can learn to summon various dragons.

In BoF2, you don't need to venture too far off track in order to get the dragons. You actually get the majority of them in groups of three, which is convenient.

You meet a whole cast of characters that can join your party along the way, and each one has a special overworld ability that helps you progress the story.

For example, Sten can reach across some cliffs to grab a pole and drag the party across, Katt can smash rocks to open up pathways, Rand can roll into a ball and get you across vast stretches of the overworld without being attacked.

This last one is convenient as the random enemy encounter rate is pretty high in this game. I'm really thankful I was playing this on an emulator that supported fast-forwarding, as the majority of the battles I just auto-fought at 800x speed ;)

<img class="right" src="/images/bof2/bof2.012.png">

There are also multiple ways to get around the world. You can walk, ride on a whale, ride on a giant bird, or fly TownShip around. This last one, I didn't actually get to do as I killed the old guy hooked up to the machine on one of the quests :(.

While playing, depending on the decisions you make, you can affect the type of ending you'll get. Like some other RPGs (ex. [Chrono Trigger](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chrono_Trigger)), there are multiple endings you can get.

I didn't get the best ending, but I didn't get the worst ending either (I chose to go into the gate and fight the end boss).

<img class="left" src="/images/bof2/bof2.038.png">

BoF2 has a lot more "cut scenes" than the original did. I'm not sure if this was the case on the SNES version, but as I was playing the GBA remake, this stood out for me.

The cut-scenes are just still images, but they do provide a nice break from the gameplay and tend to actually contribute to the story at hand (as opposed to just being randomly inserted).

The underlying story of the game is about a religious cult (St. Eva) that is sending souls to the ultimate evil. Once you infiltrate the cult and discover this plot, you can go to the underworld to fight Detheven, but first you have to beat the demon from the beginning of the game: Barubary.

<img class="right" src="/images/bof2/bof2.042.png">

You can choose to fight Barubary alone, or as a group. I believe the choice you make here influences the ending you get, but I'm not positive ...

I went it alone, and found it to be a very long, difficult fight. You basically have to attack once, heal once, repeat.

When I'd knocked off about 3000 points of damage, I finally summoned a dragon to finish him off. This was the recommended strategy as the first few times I fought I used my dragon right away and had my ass kicked shortly thereafter. This [walkthrough](http://shrines.rpgclassics.com/snes/bof2/walkthroughs/bof2walkb.txt) really helped ;)

The final battle with Detheven didn't prove to be all that difficult, and once you defeat him and the credits roll, Ryu chooses to take the form of a dragon and sacrifice himself to seal off the doorway to the underworld.

I quite enjoyed this game, though I did find the battle system to be excruciatingly slow. Without fast-forward on, I doubt I would have finished this game. Also, after a battle completes there is a delay before you can move your characters again, which also made the game feel sluggish.

Overall though, I would recommend this to any JRPG fan as the story is solid, the gameplay is fun, and if you like, you can take a break from the action and go fishing for treasure.

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.001.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.001.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.003.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.003.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.005.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.005.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.006.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.006.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.007.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.007.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.008.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.008.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.009.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.009.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.010.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.010.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.011.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.011.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.013.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.013.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.014.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.014.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.015.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.015.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.016.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.016.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.017.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.017.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.018.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.018.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.019.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.019.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.020.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.020.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.021.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.021.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.022.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.022.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.023.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.023.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.024.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.024.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.025.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.025.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.026.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.026.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.027.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.027.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.029.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.029.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.030.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.030.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.031.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.031.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.032.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.032.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.033.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.033.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.034.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.034.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.035.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.035.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.036.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.036.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.037.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.037.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.039.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.039.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.040.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.040.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.041.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.041.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.043.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.043.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.044.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.044.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.045.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.045.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.046.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.046.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.047.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.047.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.048.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.048.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.049.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.049.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.050.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.050.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.051.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.051.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.052.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.052.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>

As usual, here's the gallery of screenshots. Let me know which one's your favourite in the comments below ;)

For my next playthrough, I'm working on [Final Fantasy II: Dawn of Souls](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Final_Fantasy_I_%26_II:_Dawn_of_Souls). Shouldn't be too much longer now, as I'm already at the Jade Passage, which I believe is the final section of the game.

Did you like Breath of Fire II? Which is your favourite of the series? What should I play next? Is my writing getting any better? Let me know in the comments below if you have any feedback.

Cheers!]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
