<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: redmine-plugins-book | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
  <link href="http://alexbevi.com/blog/categories/redmine-plugins-book/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alexbevi.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-09T22:55:02-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://alexbevi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexbevi@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Round of Rewrites Completed!]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexbevi.com/blog/2014/02/09/first-round-of-rewrites-completed/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-09T21:48:29-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexbevi.com/blog/2014/02/09/first-round-of-rewrites-completed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is just a quick update that I&rsquo;ve finally finished the first round of rewrites for the upcoming <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book">Redmine Plugin Extension and Development</a> book.</p>

<p>The issue I was struggling with was little more than a complete lack of motivation. Since I work full time and do contract development on the side (plus have a wife and kids), yet another distraction can be difficult to find time for; especially if it&rsquo;s not a primary source of income.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.packtpub.com">Packt Publishing</a> has been very patient with me though so I&rsquo;m going to try to find the time in the coming week to get through the second round of revisions and rewrites and hopefully get this puppy to market ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My First Book: Almost Ready for Production]]></title>
    <link href="http://alexbevi.com/blog/2014/01/27/my-first-book-is-almost-ready-for-production/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T15:37:10-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://alexbevi.com/blog/2014/01/27/my-first-book-is-almost-ready-for-production</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the last 4 months I&rsquo;ve been working with <a href="http://www.packtpub.com">Packt Publishing</a> on a book about <a href="http://www.redmine.org">Redmine</a> plugin extension and development.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/8748OS_mockupcover_normal_0.jpg"></p>

<p>Although it likely won&rsquo;t be ready until February 2014, the book is now available for <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book">pre-order on Packt&rsquo;s site</a>.</p>

<p>Since the book is <em>almost</em> through the first stage of rewrites, I though it might be a good idea to start documenting the process.</p>

<p>What I&rsquo;m going to write about initially are my first impressions on writing a book, as well as a few notes (which may sound like complaints) about what I did &ldquo;wrong&rdquo; and could improve upon in the future.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Originally, I wasn&rsquo;t sure that I would be a good choice as an author as I didn&rsquo;t have the community recognition that some other plugin developers had, and I hadn&rsquo;t been &ldquo;on the scene&rdquo; for more than a few years.</p>

<p>After much consideration, I decided to dive in and start writing.</p>

<p>The first step was to provide the publisher with a rough outline that also included the page count. Initially, I just threw together a handful of topics that I wanted to cover, then (very generically) estimated how many pages I would need to completely cover those topics.</p>

<p>Once approved, and I actually <em>started</em> writing, I very quickly realized that meeting my page estimates was almost impossible; some chapters would be way too short, and others WAY too long.</p>

<p>I also had to provide a rough outline as to how long I thoght it would take me to write each chapter. This step, in retrospect, I wish I had taken more time to properly prepare.</p>

<p>Writing a technically-oriented book involves a lot more research than you may think (no matter how well you think you know the source material). As such, the further I got into the book, the more time I found myself researching, writing code, testing code, then writing about the code I&rsquo;d built.</p>

<p>This process took a good 3x longer than I anticipated, and as such, my deadlines tended to slip by. As a result, the tentative release date for the final book of January 2014 is not very likely.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m hoping that this blog post will also serve as a motivator to get my ass in gear and finish the final revisions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
