<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: snes | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/snes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-11T10:52:12-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Breath of Fire]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/10/just-finished-breath-of-fire/"/>
        <updated>2015-06-10T08:34:06-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/10/just-finished-breath-of-fire</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[My original plan for my next playthrough was going to be [Daganronpa](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danganronpa:_Trigger_Happy_Havoc), but after making it to chapter 5, I got caught up in an phone upgrade bricking (at least [Wind ended up replacing my phone](http://mobilesyrup.com/2015/01/22/wind-mobile-users-complaining-of-problems-with-moto-x-lollipop-soak-test/)) fiasco and lost all my progress.

I didn't really feel like starting all over again, so I started [Lufia II](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia_II:_Rise_of_the_Sinistrals) and the original [Breath of Fire](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breath_of_Fire_(video_game).

I ended up sticking with Breath of Fire, though I want to get through both Lufia and Lufia II eventually ;)

I wasn't really planning on writing about this game, but decided at the last minute, so all my screenshots are from the very end ;)

I played the Game Boy Advance remake on my phone using [GBA.emu](http://www.explusalpha.com/home/gba-emu). Although I'm perfectly capable of compiling from source and side-loading the APK, I bought the version on the Play store as the developer deserves the support.

<img class="left" src="/images/bof/bof.005.png">

The story starts off the main character, Ryu's hometown. He is one of the last members of the Light Dragon Clan, and the Dark Dragon Clan has just come to eradicate them.

When they set the town ablaze, Ryu's sister Sara turns everyone to stone and ventures out alone to stop the invasion. She is captured, and the game begins with you setting out to fight the Dark Dragons and get her back.

<!-- more -->

<img class="right" src="/images/bof/bof.006.png">

As you make your way through the game, you meet up with additional character that add a new twist to how you solve puzzles. For example, Bo can hunt animals that appear randomly on the overworld map, Karn can open locked doors, Ox can smash certain walls, Gobi can swim under water and Nina eventually morphs into a bird.

I thought this angle was pretty cool, as it makes the game more of an Action-RPG (ala Zelda or Secret of Mana) than a traditional Final Fantasy style JRPG.

Each character has a unique skill that is required to progress the story at some point, so you feel more attached to them than supporting characters from certain other series.

The combat system is a traditional turn-based, menu-driven, pick your attacks and wait for the enemy implementation. If you've played any other JRPG from this era, you'll feel right at home.

<img class="left" src="/images/bof/bof.000.png">

The main quest progresses in a pretty linear fashion. You're trying to find a bunch of Goddess keys that were used to lock up Tyr long ago, but the Dark dragons are trying to find them as well to let Tyr out to wreak havoc on the world.

You get these keys, fight members of the Dark Dragons, meet characters, unlock more of the map and eventually have to fight Tyr once and for all.

There are side-quests as well that you have to do if you want to learn dragon techniques for Ryu, or fusion techniques for Karn.

If you go to the trouble of getting all the Dragon equipment and finding the final dragon form, Agni, you basically have a Win Stick(tm) for the rest of the game (I highly recommend this :P).

### Summary

This game wasn't overly difficult, and really didn't take that long to complete.

The learning curve wasn't very steep, but this could just be due to having played a lot of other games from the JRPG, Action RPG genres previously.

Since the majority of games that I play nowadays are from [Square Enix](http://www.square-enix.com/), it was nice to run through something from another publisher.

I really enjoyed this game, and am currently working my way through the sequel, [Breath of Fire II](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breath_of_Fire_II).

Assuming I don't brick my phone again, hopefully I'll have a review for that next :D.

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/bof/bof.001.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/bof/bof.002.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/bof/bof.003.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/bof/bof.004.png" data-title="" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Robotrek]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/10/17/just-finished-robotrek/"/>
        <updated>2014-10-17T09:00:00-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/10/17/just-finished-robotrek</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I was planning on writing this review a while ago, but it turns out I nuked my phone and lost my progress so I had to start all over again. I originally started this on 2014-09-26, but I kind of lost my motivation ... and I started playing [Terranigma](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terranigma), which is pretty awesome so far.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/220px-Robotrekboxart.jpg">

In my ongoing series of articles about old games that I never got around to playing, today I'm going to tackle [Robotrek](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robotrek).

Robotrek is a silly RPG that revolves around "getting to the bottom" of a situation involving a group calling themselves the "hackers" who are disrupting the peace of your home town of Rococo.

The story follows your character, who wants to be an inventor, and right off the bat learns how to make robots. As you progress through the game, you'll eventually be able to build three robots, which can be swapped in an out during battle.

<!-- more -->

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).012.png">

These robots can be upgraded with better weapons and armour by reading books you find throughout the game.

You'll also learn how to make items and some useful tools that will help you solve various puzzles.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).017.png">

Since you're an inventor in this game, one of your main tasks is to *combine* items you find in order to potentially make new items. Although this is useful a couple times, I found I didn't really need to use it beyond the first part of the game where you make the drill.

You can sometimes combine scraps with each other to produce weapons, or combine scraps with weapons to produce upgraded weapons, but only trial and error yield results. I couldn't find any information in the game that helped lead you towards proper combinations (and I wanted to avoid walkthroughs).

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).027.png">

Battles in this game are pretty straightforward. You equip weapons to your robots, then use them in battle either directly, or you can program sequences that allow you to run multiple attacks in succession. This approach can kill enemies faster, but will require you to charge up for longer, and therefore be vulnerable for longer as well.

The fights are extremely repetitive, and it doesn't help that there only appears to be a single battle theme that loops constantly. I played most of the game with the volume off due to this :P

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).010.png">

Once you get to the volcano and find the *Sword 4* in a chest, the random battles become exceedingly easy (for at least the next 3/4 of the game). This weapon is just ridiculously overpowered at this point and you'll find yourself just spamming it in order to quickly proceed through the story.

Boss battles tend to be very dependent on what level you're at when you enter the fight. Most battles I had to redo at least once as I found I was far too low of a level to have a chance.

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).022.png">

I found this to be the most true when I got to **De Rose**. This was the boss I reached during my last playthrough, and after grinding for a good 2 hours, I found I just couldn't beat her, gave up and moved on to another game.

This time around, I actually checked a walkthrough, which recommended I be at about level 50 before entering the fight. I was at level 37. I was going to have to grind ... and grinding in this game is TEDIOUS. I ended up grinding to about level 44 before beating her, but this took a good 4-5 hours. 

The story progresses: the Hackers leader (a crab) is defeated, Dr. Einst's plot is foiled, a new Hackers leader emerges (Blackmore), the story jumps back and forwards in time, a spaceship emerges so you can visit another planet and you end up having to save the world.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).035.png">

The final battle is against Gateau (the "food"-naming convention for characters and places is used throughout the game), who had something to do with using the Tetron to build a weapon or something (I can't remember the exact story; play the game for a better description :P).

He takes two forms, but isn't overly difficult to defeat at this point.

Overall, this game was pretty easy. The story progressed in a very linear fashion, and most puzzles were pretty straightforward to solve.

It was fun though, and though I probably won't replay this game again in the future, I'm glad that I went through it at least once.

My screenshots are below, though it seems that the emulator I was using ([Snes9x EX](http://www.explusalpha.com/home/snes9x-ex) on my Moto G) overwrote some of my earlier images. Oh well. Enjoy :P

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).000.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).001.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).002.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).003.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).004.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).005.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).006.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).007.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).008.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).009.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).010.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).011.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).012.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).013.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).014.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).015.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).016.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).017.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).018.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).019.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).020.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).021.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).022.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).023.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).024.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).025.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).026.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).027.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).028.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).029.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).030.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).031.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).032.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).033.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).034.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).035.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).036.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).037.png" data-title="" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
