<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: snes | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/snes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-10T15:54:03-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Lufia 2]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/09/23/just-finished-lufia-2/"/>
        <updated>2015-09-23T20:04:59-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/09/23/just-finished-lufia-2</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.000.png">

This review has been a long time coming; a *VERY* long time coming. I heard about [Lufia 2: Rise of the Sinistrals](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia_II:_Rise_of_the_Sinistrals) when I was still in high school, and have been meaning to play it ever since.

Back then, I was just starting to get into JRPGs (though I probably just thought they were RPGs at the time) and was completely infatuated with anything that Square or Enix could crank out (except for [Earthbound](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EarthBound), which is still one of my all-time faves).

In the decade(s) since my teens, I've picked up Lufia 2 a good dozen times, but have never really given it a fair shake. This time around though, since I'm doing this "Just Finished" series, I thought I'd finally sit down and do a full playthrough.

For anyone that has not played this game: PLAY IT! Lufia 2 is now in the top 10 of my favourite 16-bit JRPGs of all time. Hopefully after reading my synopsis here, anyone that was on the fence will also take the plunge (you'll thank me later!).

<!-- more -->

## Overview

Lufia 2 (aka. Estpolis Denki II, aka. エストポリス伝記II) is a hybrid of traditional JRPG and [Action RPG](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Action_role-playing_game). You control one to four characters at a time throughout the adventure, with enemy encounters being handled via fade-away to a turn-based combat system.

It turns out you (Maxim) are destined to fight the Sinistrals, so you embark on a journey to save the world. Cliché? Yup :P

Don't get me wrong, I love a good "destined to save the world" story, but after playing a handful of JRPGs in succession, I was getting a bit numb to the same story over and over again.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.026.png">

I decided to give this a fair chance though, and went along with it. I had never played the original [Lufia](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia) for more than 5-10 minutes, but I do remember the intro segment where you have the four heroes already in the Fortress of Doom getting ready to fight the Sinistrals.

I'm going to skip around a bit here because I just want to cover one thing, which is the end of the game ... first. The final battle with Daos for Maxim, Artea, Guy and Selan is the EXACT scene from the first game. This made me REALLY want to go back and play the first game, as I now had a connection with the characters.

Also, I thought I was a really cool transition as it tied the two games together seamlessly.

### Combat

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.032.png">

Enemy encounters on the overworld are random. As you're walking around, suddenly the screen will zoom in and boom, it's go time! For anyone familiar with JRPGs, this is pretty common.

Unlike traditional RPGs, Lufia 2 doesn't have "random" encounters in dungeons. All enemies are visible as you explore the dungeons, and though most will chase you, a lot of these battles can be avoided if you so choose.

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.005.png">

Once a battle is initiated, as opposed to a text-based menu of `Fight | Magic | Item | Run` as you might see in some games, you're presented with an icon cross (reminiscent of [Breath of Fire](/blog/2015/06/10/just-finished-breath-of-fire/)).

Aside from the standard Attack, Item and Magic options, there is also and Abilities option for each party member. This additional entry gives each character access to various offensive or defensive abilities that are linked to their weapons and armour. This adds another dimension to battles as you have to keep track of what skills are linked to your equipment (don't just hit 'optimize' each time) as weaker items may provide added benefits against certain enemies.

### Puzzles

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.004.png">

What I really enjoyed about this game from the moment I entered the first dungeon was the puzzles. Littered throughout each dungeon are puzzles that you need to solve in order to open a door and proceed.

Generally, these puzzles aren't all that complex, but they break up the dungeons a bit so it doesn't feel monotonous as you basically do the same things over and over in order to progress the story.

As you move further through the game, you also collect various key items, that can be used in order to help solve the various puzzles (bombs, arrows, hook shot, etc.)

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.021.png">

These add another dimension to the puzzles that keeps them interesting. I honestly didn't find most puzzles to be very challenging, but I will admit to having to use a walkthrough for at least 2 of them ... (thankfully there are excellent [guides on rpgclassics](http://shrines.rpgclassics.com/snes/lufia2/puzzles.shtml) for just these instances where you need a tiny bit of help)

### Party

Your party is made up of Maxim, and at various points Tia, Guy, Selan, Dekar and Arty.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.019.png">

Tia is from your home village and follows you on the initial leg of the quest. You think she's going to end up being Maxim's love interest, but that changes once Selan enters the story ;)

Maxim and Selan fall in love, get married, and have a baby. This all happens around the mid-point of the game, acting as a bit of an intermission. Once they have the kid, they decide to go back out and fight so that the world is safe for their baby (and everyone else ... I guess).

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.028.png">

Guy joins as he's a good fighter and wants to help defeat the Sinistrals. Dekar's reasons are basically the same.

### Capsule Monsters

Your party can also include capsule monsters. These are optional encounters throughout the game that if you seek out result in an additional character being able to join you in battle.

<img class="left" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.018.png">

Each monster has an elemental affiliation, and can level up with you as you fight enemies. If the capsule monster dies in battle though, they respawn for the next fight, so there's no need to worry about their health (you can't heal them). They do tend to run from a lot of battles automatically though, which can be annoying.

Capsule monsters can also be made stronger by leveling them up through feeding them weapons, armour and items.

This got a bit annoying as I had to hear a lot of "Yuk"s from the monsters while trying to find the right items to feed them.

### Music

I just quickly wanted to touch on the music in this game. For a JRPG not composed by [Nobuo](http://vgmdb.net/artist/77), the soundtrack is pretty solid.

If you've got a minute, check out a couple of songs below to get a taste of what's in store for you ;)

* [Final Battle](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-Fzm2O4Zt-k&index=44&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48)
* [Peace of Mind](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7E-AD-OUxKg&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=10)
* [The Lost World](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fk3omXPfuVM&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=41)
* [Battle Theme 3](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BLIrE5ivseQ&list=PL6BB4862ADAA12E48&index=46)

In case you're wondering, composition credit goes to [Yasunori Shiono](http://vgmdb.net/artist/313).

### Ancient Cave

This is a completely optional dungeon, but if you're going to play Lufia 2, you HAVE to try and clear it ;)

The ancient cave is 99 randomly generated floors, and you start the cave at level 1 (no matter where you actually are in the game). As you level up and descend further into the cave, you find various treasures and spells that you can only use within the cave.

If you warp out, you lose all experience and items you've found; aside from items in blue chests (which are few).

<img class="right" src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.038.png">

Once you make it to the last level of the cave, you fight the Master Jelly. This is a brutal fight, as you only have 3 turns in order to beat him, and if you don't, he just runs and that's the end of it (you have to warp out).

Note that I basically cheated to beat him. If you can kill your entire party before he runs, you'll actually win the fight.

I did this, but I didn't find all the Iris Treasures in the cave so it didn't really matter.

## Summary

As great as you probably think I think this game is by now, it is not without its faults.

First off, this game is *extremely* linear. The plot progresses as follows:

* Go to <tower name> tower to find <plot point>
* Climb tower and fight enemy
* Go back to town to learn where next town is
* Go to shrine to advance to next town

Sure you get a boat at a certain point and it "opens" up the map, but you still basically go from town to town and tower to tower without much variety.

Also, it may be that I'm just a bit more experienced in the genre and know how to level grind, but I found this game to be very, very easy. By the final dungeon, every battle was essentially the same (the final boss included): fight, fight, valor, fight.

All in all though, I really enjoyed this game. Although the story seemed like it was going to be pretty basic at the outset turned out the be really compelling.

There was actually quite a bit of character development. I think this is why at the end when you realize you're basically setting up the intro of Lufia I, you really want to go back and play that game to see if the story continues to be as strong.

I'll probably give this game another run through in a few years, as it really was enjoyable. I tend to do this with RPGs i enjoy as I forget specifics of the story over the years and enjoy rediscovering them. Final Fantasy IV and VI have had this treatment now probably a good 4-5 times each ;)


<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.001.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.001.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.002.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.002.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.003.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.003.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.006.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.006.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.007.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.007.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.008.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.008.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.009.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.009.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.010.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.010.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.011.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.011.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.012.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.012.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.013.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.013.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.014.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.014.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.015.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.015.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.016.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.016.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.017.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.017.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.020.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.020.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.022.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.022.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.023.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.023.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.024.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.024.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.025.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.025.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.027.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.027.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.029.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.029.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.030.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.030.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.031.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.031.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.033.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.033.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.034.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.034.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.035.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.035.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.036.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.036.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.037.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.037.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.039.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.039.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.040.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.040.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.041.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.041.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.042.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.042.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.043.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.043.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.044.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.044.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.045.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.045.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.046.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.046.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.047.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.047.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.048.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.048.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.049.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.049.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.050.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.050.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.051.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.051.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.052.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.052.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.053.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.053.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.054.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.054.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.055.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.055.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.056.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.056.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.057.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.057.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.058.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.058.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.059.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.059.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.060.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.060.png" /><img src="/images/lufia2/lufia2.061.png" data-title="/images/lufia2/lufia2.061.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>

<br/>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Breath of Fire 2]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/29/just-finished-breath-of-fire-2/"/>
        <updated>2015-06-29T13:17:02-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/29/just-finished-breath-of-fire-2</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[Following on the heels of my playthrough of the original Breath of Fire, I've just finished [Breath of Fire II](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breath_of_Fire_II).

Originally released for the Super Nintendo Entertainment System in 1994, BoF2 is the direct sequel to the original. Although the protagonist is named the same (Ryu) as in the original, I don't think he's supposed to be the same person (the story takes place hundreds of years after the original).

<img class="left" src="/images/bof2/bof2.000.png">

You start off as a kid in a small town with your buddy Bow. You go visit the outskirts of town where there is a dragon sleeping and blocking a gate. You're attacked by a demon named Barubary, who knocks the two out then disappears.

The story picks up 10 years later with the two trying to make it as rangers and taking odd jobs. You take a job trying to find someone's lost pet, and from there, the game begins.

You save the pet (pig) in an old house where a hermit lives. This house introduces an interesting dynamic to the game as this becomes the location known as TownShip. As you make your may through the game, various people join your town or can be hired to improve it. 

<img class="right" src="/images/bof2/bof2.002.png">

You can recruit builders, weapon/item shop keepers and magicians that teach you new skills and abilities. Also as your party grows, they can be stashed here in a big house and you can go talk to them at any point to get clues as to what needs to be done next.

<!-- more -->

The battle system is the same as the original, and most JRPGs of the era; enemies to the left, characters to the right. A menu system controls your actions, which should all be well known by now (Attack, Defend, Magic, Item, Run).

<img class="left" src="/images/bof2/bof2.028.png">

As you progress, you will learn that Ryu is a member of the Dragon Clan (as was the case in the original BoF as well), and can learn to summon various dragons.

In BoF2, you don't need to venture too far off track in order to get the dragons. You actually get the majority of them in groups of three, which is convenient.

You meet a whole cast of characters that can join your party along the way, and each one has a special overworld ability that helps you progress the story.

For example, Sten can reach across some cliffs to grab a pole and drag the party across, Katt can smash rocks to open up pathways, Rand can roll into a ball and get you across vast stretches of the overworld without being attacked.

This last one is convenient as the random enemy encounter rate is pretty high in this game. I'm really thankful I was playing this on an emulator that supported fast-forwarding, as the majority of the battles I just auto-fought at 800x speed ;)

<img class="right" src="/images/bof2/bof2.012.png">

There are also multiple ways to get around the world. You can walk, ride on a whale, ride on a giant bird, or fly TownShip around. This last one, I didn't actually get to do as I killed the old guy hooked up to the machine on one of the quests :(.

While playing, depending on the decisions you make, you can affect the type of ending you'll get. Like some other RPGs (ex. [Chrono Trigger](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chrono_Trigger)), there are multiple endings you can get.

I didn't get the best ending, but I didn't get the worst ending either (I chose to go into the gate and fight the end boss).

<img class="left" src="/images/bof2/bof2.038.png">

BoF2 has a lot more "cut scenes" than the original did. I'm not sure if this was the case on the SNES version, but as I was playing the GBA remake, this stood out for me.

The cut-scenes are just still images, but they do provide a nice break from the gameplay and tend to actually contribute to the story at hand (as opposed to just being randomly inserted).

The underlying story of the game is about a religious cult (St. Eva) that is sending souls to the ultimate evil. Once you infiltrate the cult and discover this plot, you can go to the underworld to fight Detheven, but first you have to beat the demon from the beginning of the game: Barubary.

<img class="right" src="/images/bof2/bof2.042.png">

You can choose to fight Barubary alone, or as a group. I believe the choice you make here influences the ending you get, but I'm not positive ...

I went it alone, and found it to be a very long, difficult fight. You basically have to attack once, heal once, repeat.

When I'd knocked off about 3000 points of damage, I finally summoned a dragon to finish him off. This was the recommended strategy as the first few times I fought I used my dragon right away and had my ass kicked shortly thereafter. This [walkthrough](http://shrines.rpgclassics.com/snes/bof2/walkthroughs/bof2walkb.txt) really helped ;)

The final battle with Detheven didn't prove to be all that difficult, and once you defeat him and the credits roll, Ryu chooses to take the form of a dragon and sacrifice himself to seal off the doorway to the underworld.

I quite enjoyed this game, though I did find the battle system to be excruciatingly slow. Without fast-forward on, I doubt I would have finished this game. Also, after a battle completes there is a delay before you can move your characters again, which also made the game feel sluggish.

Overall though, I would recommend this to any JRPG fan as the story is solid, the gameplay is fun, and if you like, you can take a break from the action and go fishing for treasure.

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.001.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.001.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.003.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.003.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.005.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.005.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.006.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.006.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.007.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.007.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.008.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.008.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.009.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.009.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.010.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.010.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.011.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.011.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.013.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.013.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.014.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.014.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.015.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.015.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.016.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.016.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.017.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.017.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.018.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.018.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.019.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.019.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.020.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.020.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.021.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.021.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.022.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.022.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.023.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.023.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.024.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.024.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.025.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.025.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.026.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.026.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.027.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.027.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.029.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.029.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.030.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.030.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.031.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.031.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.032.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.032.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.033.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.033.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.034.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.034.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.035.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.035.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.036.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.036.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.037.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.037.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.039.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.039.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.040.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.040.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.041.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.041.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.043.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.043.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.044.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.044.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.045.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.045.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.046.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.046.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.047.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.047.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.048.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.048.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.049.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.049.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.050.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.050.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.051.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.051.png" /><img src="/images/bof2/bof2.052.png" data-title="/images/bof2/bof2.052.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>

As usual, here's the gallery of screenshots. Let me know which one's your favourite in the comments below ;)

For my next playthrough, I'm working on [Final Fantasy II: Dawn of Souls](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Final_Fantasy_I_%26_II:_Dawn_of_Souls). Shouldn't be too much longer now, as I'm already at the Jade Passage, which I believe is the final section of the game.

Did you like Breath of Fire II? Which is your favourite of the series? What should I play next? Is my writing getting any better? Let me know in the comments below if you have any feedback.

Cheers!]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Breath of Fire]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/10/just-finished-breath-of-fire/"/>
        <updated>2015-06-10T08:34:06-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/10/just-finished-breath-of-fire</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[My original plan for my next playthrough was going to be [Daganronpa](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danganronpa:_Trigger_Happy_Havoc), but after making it to chapter 5, I got caught up in an phone upgrade bricking (at least [Wind ended up replacing my phone](http://mobilesyrup.com/2015/01/22/wind-mobile-users-complaining-of-problems-with-moto-x-lollipop-soak-test/)) fiasco and lost all my progress.

I didn't really feel like starting all over again, so I started [Lufia II](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia_II:_Rise_of_the_Sinistrals) and the original [Breath of Fire](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breath_of_Fire_(video_game).

I ended up sticking with Breath of Fire, though I want to get through both Lufia and Lufia II eventually ;)

I wasn't really planning on writing about this game, but decided at the last minute, so all my screenshots are from the very end ;)

I played the Game Boy Advance remake on my phone using [GBA.emu](http://www.explusalpha.com/home/gba-emu). Although I'm perfectly capable of compiling from source and side-loading the APK, I bought the version on the Play store as the developer deserves the support.

<img class="left" src="/images/bof/bof.005.png">

The story starts off the main character, Ryu's hometown. He is one of the last members of the Light Dragon Clan, and the Dark Dragon Clan has just come to eradicate them.

When they set the town ablaze, Ryu's sister Sara turns everyone to stone and ventures out alone to stop the invasion. She is captured, and the game begins with you setting out to fight the Dark Dragons and get her back.

<!-- more -->

<img class="right" src="/images/bof/bof.006.png">

As you make your way through the game, you meet up with additional character that add a new twist to how you solve puzzles. For example, Bo can hunt animals that appear randomly on the overworld map, Karn can open locked doors, Ox can smash certain walls, Gobi can swim under water and Nina eventually morphs into a bird.

I thought this angle was pretty cool, as it makes the game more of an Action-RPG (ala Zelda or Secret of Mana) than a traditional Final Fantasy style JRPG.

Each character has a unique skill that is required to progress the story at some point, so you feel more attached to them than supporting characters from certain other series.

The combat system is a traditional turn-based, menu-driven, pick your attacks and wait for the enemy implementation. If you've played any other JRPG from this era, you'll feel right at home.

<img class="left" src="/images/bof/bof.000.png">

The main quest progresses in a pretty linear fashion. You're trying to find a bunch of Goddess keys that were used to lock up Tyr long ago, but the Dark dragons are trying to find them as well to let Tyr out to wreak havoc on the world.

You get these keys, fight members of the Dark Dragons, meet characters, unlock more of the map and eventually have to fight Tyr once and for all.

There are side-quests as well that you have to do if you want to learn dragon techniques for Ryu, or fusion techniques for Karn.

If you go to the trouble of getting all the Dragon equipment and finding the final dragon form, Agni, you basically have a Win Stick(tm) for the rest of the game (I highly recommend this :P).

### Summary

This game wasn't overly difficult, and really didn't take that long to complete.

The learning curve wasn't very steep, but this could just be due to having played a lot of other games from the JRPG, Action RPG genres previously.

Since the majority of games that I play nowadays are from [Square Enix](http://www.square-enix.com/), it was nice to run through something from another publisher.

I really enjoyed this game, and am currently working my way through the sequel, [Breath of Fire II](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breath_of_Fire_II).

Assuming I don't brick my phone again, hopefully I'll have a review for that next :D.

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/bof/bof.001.png" data-title="/images/bof/bof.001.png" /><img src="/images/bof/bof.002.png" data-title="/images/bof/bof.002.png" /><img src="/images/bof/bof.003.png" data-title="/images/bof/bof.003.png" /><img src="/images/bof/bof.004.png" data-title="/images/bof/bof.004.png " /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Robotrek]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/10/17/just-finished-robotrek/"/>
        <updated>2014-10-17T09:00:00-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/10/17/just-finished-robotrek</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I was planning on writing this review a while ago, but it turns out I nuked my phone and lost my progress so I had to start all over again. I originally started this on 2014-09-26, but I kind of lost my motivation ... and I started playing [Terranigma](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terranigma), which is pretty awesome so far.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/220px-Robotrekboxart.jpg">

In my ongoing series of articles about old games that I never got around to playing, today I'm going to tackle [Robotrek](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robotrek).

Robotrek is a silly RPG that revolves around "getting to the bottom" of a situation involving a group calling themselves the "hackers" who are disrupting the peace of your home town of Rococo.

The story follows your character, who wants to be an inventor, and right off the bat learns how to make robots. As you progress through the game, you'll eventually be able to build three robots, which can be swapped in an out during battle.

<!-- more -->

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).012.png">

These robots can be upgraded with better weapons and armour by reading books you find throughout the game.

You'll also learn how to make items and some useful tools that will help you solve various puzzles.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).017.png">

Since you're an inventor in this game, one of your main tasks is to *combine* items you find in order to potentially make new items. Although this is useful a couple times, I found I didn't really need to use it beyond the first part of the game where you make the drill.

You can sometimes combine scraps with each other to produce weapons, or combine scraps with weapons to produce upgraded weapons, but only trial and error yield results. I couldn't find any information in the game that helped lead you towards proper combinations (and I wanted to avoid walkthroughs).

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).027.png">

Battles in this game are pretty straightforward. You equip weapons to your robots, then use them in battle either directly, or you can program sequences that allow you to run multiple attacks in succession. This approach can kill enemies faster, but will require you to charge up for longer, and therefore be vulnerable for longer as well.

The fights are extremely repetitive, and it doesn't help that there only appears to be a single battle theme that loops constantly. I played most of the game with the volume off due to this :P

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).010.png">

Once you get to the volcano and find the *Sword 4* in a chest, the random battles become exceedingly easy (for at least the next 3/4 of the game). This weapon is just ridiculously overpowered at this point and you'll find yourself just spamming it in order to quickly proceed through the story.

Boss battles tend to be very dependent on what level you're at when you enter the fight. Most battles I had to redo at least once as I found I was far too low of a level to have a chance.

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).022.png">

I found this to be the most true when I got to **De Rose**. This was the boss I reached during my last playthrough, and after grinding for a good 2 hours, I found I just couldn't beat her, gave up and moved on to another game.

This time around, I actually checked a walkthrough, which recommended I be at about level 50 before entering the fight. I was at level 37. I was going to have to grind ... and grinding in this game is TEDIOUS. I ended up grinding to about level 44 before beating her, but this took a good 4-5 hours. 

The story progresses: the Hackers leader (a crab) is defeated, Dr. Einst's plot is foiled, a new Hackers leader emerges (Blackmore), the story jumps back and forwards in time, a spaceship emerges so you can visit another planet and you end up having to save the world.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).035.png">

The final battle is against Gateau (the "food"-naming convention for characters and places is used throughout the game), who had something to do with using the Tetron to build a weapon or something (I can't remember the exact story; play the game for a better description :P).

He takes two forms, but isn't overly difficult to defeat at this point.

Overall, this game was pretty easy. The story progressed in a very linear fashion, and most puzzles were pretty straightforward to solve.

It was fun though, and though I probably won't replay this game again in the future, I'm glad that I went through it at least once.

My screenshots are below, though it seems that the emulator I was using ([Snes9x EX](http://www.explusalpha.com/home/snes9x-ex) on my Moto G) overwrote some of my earlier images. Oh well. Enjoy :P

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).000.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).000.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).001.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).001.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).002.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).002.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).003.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).003.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).004.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).004.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).005.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).005.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).006.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).006.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).007.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).007.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).008.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).008.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).009.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).009.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).010.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).010.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).011.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).011.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).012.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).012.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).013.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).013.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).014.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).014.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).015.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).015.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).016.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).016.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).017.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).017.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).018.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).018.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).019.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).019.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).020.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).020.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).021.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).021.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).022.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).022.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).023.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).023.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).024.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).024.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).025.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).025.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).026.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).026.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).027.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).027.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).028.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).028.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).029.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).029.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).030.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).030.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).031.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).031.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).032.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).032.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).033.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).033.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).034.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).034.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).035.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).035.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).036.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).036.png" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).037.png" data-title="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).037.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
