<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: waddap | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/waddap/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-10T05:20:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's Up - May/June 2016]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/06/14/whats-up-may-slash-june-2016/"/>
        <updated>2016-06-14T20:38:02-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/06/14/whats-up-may-slash-june-2016</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[It's been a while since I posted the [Seiken Densetsu 3](/blog/2016/04/19/just-finished-seiken-densetsu-3/) review, so I figured as it might be a while before I get around to posting more content, I'll just throw up a quick update.

## Gaming

<img class="left" src="/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.015.png">

I'm currently working my way through three games. After finishing the [Shadowrun](/blog/2016/02/23/just-finished-shadowrun/) play-through for SNES, I got some good feedback about the [Genesis version](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadowrun_(1994_video_game\)). I decided to give that a go, and I've currently made it to the last boss, but am having no luck beating him.

I'm pretty sure I'm going to have to save up some nuyen and grind it out with some better runners in order to be able to beat Thon. This is a bit of a pain in the ass, and is the reason I ended up abandoning [Terranigma](/blog/2015/01/16/just-finished-terranigma/) previously.

I really enjoyed that game, but since I've got very limited time decided to move on to the next challenge.

By challenge, I meant *CHALLENGE*. I decided to give [The 7th Saga](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7th_Saga) another shot, and have now officially made it MUCH further than I ever have before.

<!-- more -->

<img class="right" src="/images/7th-saga/7th-saga.009.png">

This game was alway brutally hard for me when I was a kid, and it still is. You've got limited inventory for healing items, everything is expensive and the enemies are generally overpowered.

On top of that, it takes forever to level up, and when you do it doesn't really make all that much of a difference.

I've made it as far as [Telaine](http://mikesrpgcenter.com/7thsaga/maps/telaine.html) and have the Wind, Water and Star runes. Still a ways to go, but I don't know that I'll continue ...

Finally, since I haven't played through this since the late '80s, I'm diving back into [Dragon Quest](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragon_Quest_(video_game\)). I'm going to be playing through the fan-translated SNES port, which I think is the superior port (I don't like the mobile remakes of these games ...).

I think I should have this one done relatively soon as it's not a very long game, and although it's a bit grind-heavy, I've got 8x fast-forward on my emulator :P

## Anime

Just a quick update on the series I've burned through recently.

**[Log Horizon](http://myanimelist.net/anime/17265/Log_Horizon) - Season 1**

This reminded me or SAO a bit, but with a lot less "Asuna! Kirito! <repeat>", and a lot more "Lens flare from glasses" and "Pushing glasses back into place".

Story was enjoyable. Characters were interesting. I'd recommend it.

**[Darker than Black](http://myanimelist.net/anime/2025/Darker_than_Black__Kuro_no_Keiyakusha) - Season 1+2**

REALLY enjoyed this. Good action. Interesting plot. Good dialog. I'd recommend it.

**[One Punch Man](http://myanimelist.net/anime/30276/One_Punch_Man) - Season 1**

I LOVE this. Saitama is OP AF!!! The story is a bit goofy, but the characters are interesting and the plot keeps you interested. Would totally recommend this.

I think that's all for now.]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
