<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: reddit | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/reddit/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-24T20:40:47-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Submit Content to Reddit because people WILL see it]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/12/submit-content-to-reddit-because-people-will-see-it/"/>
        <updated>2015-06-12T09:15:44-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/06/12/submit-content-to-reddit-because-people-will-see-it</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I just wanted to share a quick story as someone who occasionally publishes stuff (both in [print](https://www.packtpub.com/big-data-and-business-intelligence/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development) and on the [internets](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internets)).

I've never really given [Reddit](http://www.reddit.com) a fair chance. Every time I would go there, it seemed like the front page just had random links to news stories, or links to pictures.

I didn't really bother to dive in and actually *look* for content, or bother to checkout the subreddits to see what sorts of communities I might be more inclined to interact with.

Yesterday, I took a couple of my articles from this blog and submitted them ([here](http://www.reddit.com/r/JRPG/comments/39dg8d/just_finished_breath_of_fire/), [here](http://www.reddit.com/r/commandline/comments/39fz7c/accessing_a_running_process_stdout/) and [here](http://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/39g909/keeping_pry_breakpoints_out_of_git/)) to see what sort of feedback/engagement I might see.

<img src="/images/20150612-ga002.png">

Generally, I see anywhere from 5-25 users a day pass through here. That all changed very, VERY quickly once I submitted my content.

Within 12 hours of posting, I'd managed to get up to ~ 900 unique users, and by the end of the day, it was over 1000! ([over 9000](http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/its-over-9000) would have been sweeter :P)

<img src="/images/20150612-ga001.png">

I had some really great conversations around my content, and got some useful feedback as well.

I've posted content to Twitter, LinkedIn, Facebook and elsewhere, but never really got any good engagement. After this experience though, I know the first place I'll be dropping my new articles, and am even slightly more motivated to get them completed as I know what I can expect from the community :)

Please let me know if there are other communities you've found that generate good conversations around your content.]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
