<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: gba | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/gba/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-19T22:20:18-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Final Fantasy V]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/11/07/just-finished-final-fantasy-v/"/>
        <updated>2015-11-07T19:15:57-05:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/11/07/just-finished-final-fantasy-v</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="right" src="/images/ffv/ffv.001.png">

I've been waiting write this review for a very long time. I love the Final Fantasy series, and although I got the original back in '90, I didn't really fall in love with the series until I played IV for the SNES. Then I played VI. Then I was REALLY hooked.

Since I didn't grow up in Japan, FF IV and VI were numbered II and III when I first got my hands on them. This means that I didn't know there was a [Final Fantasy V](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_V); at least not until much later.

The game starts off with the king of Tycoon heading off to check on the wind crystal, only to watch it shatter. The hero Bartz (Butz when I played the fan translation :P) sees a meteorite fall from the sky and heads off to investigate. Bartz and his Chocobo go to check it out, and find an old man who's suffering from amnesia.

The king's daughter, Lenna, heads out to find her father and runs into Bartz and Galuf. They team up and the adventure begins.

<img class="left" src="/images/ffv/ffv.003.png">

Once at the wind shrine, they find that the crystal has shattered and within each shard is the power of a job class.

This introduces you to the job ability system. If you've ever had a chance to play [Final Fantasy III](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_III), you've see this system in action, but in FFV, it's done to perfection :)

<!-- more -->

Each character can be assigned to a job class. As they defeat enemies, they gain ability points, which levels up the job class. As the classes level up, you gain abilities associated with that class.

These abilities can then be applied to a character regardless of the class they're assigned to. For example, you can give a white mage black magic abilities (if you've leveled up a black mage for that character).

This gives you a lot of control over how you build your characters as the game progresses.

<img class="right" src="/images/ffv/ffv.002.png">

The storytelling in this game is very well done. Although the plot is pretty standard Final Fantasy fare (crystals, amnesia, evil emperor, main characters dying), the writing was pretty good and the character emotion pop-ups added a nice touch as well.

I enjoyed the elements of comedy they tried to incorporate into some of the scenarios and characters. After playing this game, Gilgamesh is probably my new favourite non-player character in the series. This might also have to do with [Clash on the Big Bridge](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6CMTXyExkeI)
being my favourite song from this game ;)

<img class="left" src="/images/ffv/ffv.022.png">

The battle system is the same as in FFIV ([Active Time Battle system](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Battle_System#Active_Time_Battle)). You can fight, use items, or up to 2 abilities you've learned from gaining AP and leveling up your classes.

I didn't find the battles overly difficult during this play-through, but I've been focusing a lot on grinding in the last few games I've covered, so this could just be a result of me over leveling.

So as you progress through the game, you discover that the ultimate evil, Exdeath, was banished to your world by the four warriors of dawn. Now you and your party need to become the new warriors of dawn to fight him again.

<img class="right" src="/images/ffv/ffv.046.png">

You have to get the ultimate weapons for each character class, you can go on some side quests to get some powerful summons and eventually go after Exdeath.

There is one fight in Exdeath's tower that I just couldn't win, and that was [Shinryu](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Shinryu_(Final_Fantasy_V)). I didn't bother to upgrade my equipment after a while as I just hoarded my money to use Gil Toss against everybody. As a result, Shinryu just decimated me every time I tried ... so I just gave up.

I found that magic and summons in this game proved to be effective until the very end. This is different than my experience with FF II, where you bust your ass to get Ultima, then it does like 900 damage to enemies (even after being leveled up a few times :|).

I thought the story was really compelling, and I found the whole alternate worlds overlapping "thing" to be a nice twist, though it felt a bit like what happened in FF III. Actually, just like FF III, you even have to race a chocobo around the world to get an item ...

<img class="left" src="/images/ffv/ffv.037.png">

I teared up (just a bit) when Galuf's flame was extinguished by Exdeath. I was a bit worried that since this game follows FF IV it was possible they would do the whole "everyone who died is magically back to fight again for no reason" that happened with Yang, Cid, Edward, Tellah ... etc. Fortunately (?), this wasn't the case and it's actually a very emotional point in the story.

I would strongly recommend any fan of JRPGs spend some time on this title. If I were ranking my favourite FFs now, Final Fantasy V would probably show up in the top 5 :)

As for where I'm going from here, I'm currently about 6-8 hours into [Pokémon Emerald](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pok%C3%A9mon_Emerald). I'm sort of enjoying it, though it feels like a watered down version of [Earthbound](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EarthBound) (just my initial impression).

I'm also about 4-5 hours into [Tales of Destiny](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tales_of_Destiny), but I'm not really enjoying this title and likely won't go back to it.

Feel free to leave me some feedback on whether or not I should continue the above, or if you've got a recommendation for the next title I tackle.

Cheers!

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.000.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.000.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.004.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.004.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.005.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.005.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.006.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.006.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.007.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.007.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.008.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.008.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.009.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.009.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.010.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.010.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.011.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.011.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.012.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.012.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.013.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.013.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.014.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.014.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.015.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.015.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.016.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.016.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.017.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.017.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.018.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.018.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.019.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.019.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.020.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.020.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.021.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.021.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.023.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.023.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.024.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.024.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.025.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.025.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.026.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.026.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.027.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.027.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.028.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.028.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.029.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.029.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.030.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.030.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.031.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.031.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.032.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.032.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.033.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.033.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.034.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.034.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.035.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.035.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.036.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.036.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.038.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.038.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.039.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.039.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.040.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.040.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.041.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.041.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.042.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.042.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.043.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.043.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.044.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.044.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.045.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.045.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.047.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.047.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.048.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.048.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.049.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.049.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.050.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.050.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.051.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.051.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.052.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.052.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.053.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.053.png" /><img src="/images/ffv/ffv.054.png" data-title="/images/ffv/ffv.054.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Final Fantasy II]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/07/22/just-finished-final-fantasy-ii/"/>
        <updated>2015-07-22T13:21:52-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/07/22/just-finished-final-fantasy-ii</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="center" src="/images/ff2/ff2-box.jpg">

I'm excited to finally be able to review this game, as it's the direct sequel to the game that got me into RPGs way back in 1990-91.

When I say Final Fantasy II, I literally mean the second game in the franchise; not the [SNES translation of Final Fantasy IV](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_IV#North_American_localization) ;)

I actually played a bit of this game in the late 90's using the [Demiforce](http://www.romhacking.net/translations/139/) translation patch (back in the good ol' [NESticle](http://bloodlust.zophar.net/NESticle/nes.html) days :D), but didn't make it very far.

For the actual play-through, I decided to go with the [Dawn of Souls](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Final_Fantasy_I_%26_II:_Dawn_of_Souls) version for GBA, as this includes updated graphics, an "official" translation and an updated soundtrack.

<!-- more -->

Note that since I'm reviewing a remake, I'm not sure if some of the gameplay elements below were available in the original. If you happen to have actually completed the original NES version and spot an error, please let me know ;)

<h4>Story</h4>

The story is pretty standard JRPG fare. The Emperor of Palamecia is trying to take over the world. He summons some monsters that destroy the home town of Firion, Maria, Guy and Leon. The first three are rescued by a rebel faction and taken to another town (where they join the rebellion).

Leon goes missing. The party wants to find him. Off they go.

<img class="left" src="/images/ff2/ff2.010.png">

You'll meet various characters along the way that will join your party and fight with you. (**SPOILERS!** they usually die by sacrificing themselves so you can continue the quest ...)

As you go along, you find out more about the Emperors plan, fight with the Dark Knight who turns out the be Leon, have him join up with you and eventually make your way down to the castle of hell (aka Pandaemonium) to fight the Emperor.

<h4>What's Cool</h4>

<img class="right" src="/images/ff2/ff2.004.png">

FFII introduces a couple of interesting gameplay elements that were not reused in any future entries in the series.

First, key character conversations allowed you to *Learn* keywords, which you could then *Ask* other key characters about. This mechanic helps advance the story as you have to ask various characters about plot points you learn as you go, and they then point you in the direction of your next objective.

<img class="left" src="/images/ff2/ff2.009.png">

FFII has multiple modes of travel on the overworld. As with the original, there are ships and an airship, but FFII introduces the [chocobo](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chocobo).

There is also a bunch of "cut-scenes" added to this incarnation (which would not have been available in the original NES version). These are nice as they aren't excessive or long, but help advance the plot.

<img class="right" src="/images/ff2/ff2.005.png">

Instead of leveling up your characters by fighting and gaining EXP, FFII opted for a system where the more you use a skill, the better you get at it.

For example, the more Firion attacks with a sword, the higher his sword level would go. The more Maria uses the Cure spell, the higher her magic level ... and Cure spell level would go.

This also applied to taking damage. The more damage a player took, the higher their strength and HP levels would go.

I thought this was a very interesting mechanic, and I'm not really sure why this didn't make it into any future games.

<h4>What's Not Cool</h4>

<img class="left" src="/images/ff2/ff2.019.png">

For some reason, this installation in the series decided to introduce an Inn system that charged based on how much healing you required. This proved to be a bit annoying until you realize it's a LOT cheaper to just use cure spells to get everyone's HP back up, THEN rest at the inn ;)

<img class="right" src="/images/ff2/ff2.031.png">

Another annoyance is that throughout the game, in *any* dungeon you visit, there are doors that lead to empty rooms. LOTS of doors that lead to empty rooms. What's annoying is that these rooms have higher encounter rates, so the first step you take to head back towards the exit generally results in a battle.

The battles aren't necessarily difficult, it's just a pain in the ass to have to wade through all these useless rooms.

On battles in general, once again I'm happy to be playing this game using an emulator, as the 8x fast-forward was my best friend.

The encounter rates in this game seem to be pretty high in most areas, and the fights are kind of sluggish. I found that for most non-boss fights, I'd just hit fast-forward and hold down the A button (thankfully, you don't have to mash A in this game; just holding it down works :D).

<h4>Summary</h4>

Overall, I really enjoyed the game. The story (I feel) was much better than that of the original, or even [FF III](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_III) (not [FF VI](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_VI), which is still my favourite installment in the series!)

I really liked the leveling system, and found that since I didn't run from many fights, I didn't have to game the system by just attacking my own party members to boost their HP/defense/stamina stats.

I'm glad I jumped back into the Final Fantasy series for a bit; especially with a game I actually haven't beaten before. Whenever I sit down with FF, it's usually either IV, VI or VII.

I'm thinking the next Final Fantasy I tackle will likely be V, as I haven't previously finished this (though I've gotten close). Not sure when that'll happen, because I'm currently balls-deep in [Lufia II](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lufia_II:_Rise_of_the_Sinistrals) ;)

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.000.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.000.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.001.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.001.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.002.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.002.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.003.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.003.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.006.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.006.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.007.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.007.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.008.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.008.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.011.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.011.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.012.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.012.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.013.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.013.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.014.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.014.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.015.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.015.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.016.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.016.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.017.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.017.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.018.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.018.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.020.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.020.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.021.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.021.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.022.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.022.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.023.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.023.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.024.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.024.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.025.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.025.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.026.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.026.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.027.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.027.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.028.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.028.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.029.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.029.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.030.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.030.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.032.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.032.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.033.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.033.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.034.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.034.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.035.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.035.png" /><img src="/images/ff2/ff2.036.png" data-title="/images/ff2/ff2.036.png" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>
<br />

Note that since I've finished the Dawn of Souls version of FFII, I have access to the [Soul of Rebirth](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Soul_of_Rebirth) additional dungeon. 

I'm hoping to actually play this and add to this review, or just publish a minor post to cover what was added therein.]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Fire Emblem: The Sacred Stones]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/08/06/just-finished-fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones/"/>
        <updated>2014-08-06T17:58:55-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/08/06/just-finished-fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="left" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.003.png">

I've played a lot of RPGs over the years (JRPGs mostly) but have somehow managed to hear little to nothing about the [Fire Emblem](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_Emblem) series.

My focus was mostly on the Final Fantasy series, as well as other Square-Enix properties so it's possible this is why :P

This post isn't really meant to be a review; it's more just my thoughts on the game right after I finished it as (a) I didn't take any notes, and (b) I started this playthrough over a year ago.

<!--more-->

I'm using this as an opportunity to get back into writing a bit more frequently, so I apologize in advance if the subject matter isn't covered very well, or if the writing is all over the place.

<img class="right" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.004.png">

I managed to complete the game in about 19 hours, so at least I managed to finish over an hour a month (which by gaming standards is terrible, but I'm married with kids and have a job so *back off!* :P).

I played through on my Nexus 7 using [GBA.emu](https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.explusalpha.GbaEmu&hl=en) (which I would highly recommend buying to support the author), as I don't have an actual GBA (and prefer emulated games for convenience).

<img class="left" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.002.png">

The game is turn-based tactical combat. You can buy equipment for your team members at various shops, and there is a "world map" that ties the various locations together. This makes is seem as though you're playing a board game.

The story is pretty straightforward: a dark force was sealed with a bunch of magic stones which were then distributed for safe keeping. Now someone wants to get these stones and re-awaken the dark force.

The goals of each map are either to defeat an enemy or capture a location. Along the way there are various NPC characters that you can either fight or try to persuade to join you.

Fight outcome is determined purely mathematically (stats, resources, weapon selection, character skill level, enemy skill level, terrain) and is presented as 2 avatars on the map with health guages underneath that deplete based on the result of the last "turn" of combat.

For some special battles, the characters are shown as their avatar representations and the fights are animated. These fights are generally plot advancement battles.

<img class="right" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.005.png">

Once of the main differentiating factors between Fire Emblem and other RPG series is "permanent death". Once a character dies on the battle field, there is no way to revive them. This can make the game extremely difficult as you can potentially advance to a point where you cannot continue as you don't have enough players to clear a map without dying.

I found myself abusing save states as I didn't want my characters to die, and I didn't want to restart campaigns once I'd progressed beyond a certain point (usually about 10 minutes ...).

Overall I quite enjoyed the game. The story isn't terrible and there are enough characters to keep the campaigns interesting if you want or, if you're like me you stick with a core group of characters that end up being ridiculously over-leveled by the end.

<img class="left" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.000.png">

Once you finish the game, the final credits roll an epilogue unfolds that gives some final info about the characters that survived throughout the game. The characters that died in battle are also listed, and it summarizes where they died as well, which I thought was a nice touch.

I will likely take a stab at another entry in this series and take a bit more time (in game, not another year :P) to explore as I missed A LOT.

Once I finished the game I realized there was an entire Extras section where you can manage teams and practice battles (for points I think). Also I had a rogue with a members card and didn't notice any of the "?" shops until *after* beating the last area.

I also didn't spend much time in the optional dungeons, though I did use upgrade my characters to new classes whenever possible :) The next time I tackle a Fire Emblem title though I think I'll try to (a) explore more, (b) do more optional/side quests, (c) NOT restart campaigns once they're underway.

I'm currently also midway through a playthrough of [Robotrek](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robotrek) which I've been working on-again-off-again for about a year as well, so i may try to finish that off for the next *Just Finished&trade;* post. 

If anyone has suggestions for an RPG, leave a comment (currently I'm sticking with NES to PSP as the platform range).]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
