<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rpg | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/rpg/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-27T10:13:57-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Robotrek]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/10/17/just-finished-robotrek/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T09:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/10/17/just-finished-robotrek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[I was planning on writing this review a while ago, but it turns out I nuked my phone and lost my progress so I had to start all over again. I originally started this on 2014-09-26, but I kind of lost my motivation ... and I started playing [Terranigma](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terranigma), which is pretty awesome so far.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/220px-Robotrekboxart.jpg">

In my ongoing series of articles about old games that I never got around to playing, today I&#8217;m going to tackle [Robotrek](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robotrek).

Robotrek is a silly RPG that revolves around &#8220;getting to the bottom&#8221; of a situation involving a group calling themselves the &#8220;hackers&#8221; who are disrupting the peace of your home town of Rococo.

The story follows your character, who wants to be an inventor, and right off the bat learns how to make robots. As you progress through the game, you&#8217;ll eventually be able to build three robots, which can be swapped in an out during battle.

<!-- more -->

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).012.png">

These robots can be upgraded with better weapons and armour by reading books you find throughout the game.

You&#8217;ll also learn how to make items and some useful tools that will help you solve various puzzles.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).017.png">

Since you&#8217;re an inventor in this game, one of your main tasks is to *combine* items you find in order to potentially make new items. Although this is useful a couple times, I found I didn&#8217;t really need to use it beyond the first part of the game where you make the drill.

You can sometimes combine scraps with each other to produce weapons, or combine scraps with weapons to produce upgraded weapons, but only trial and error yield results. I couldn&#8217;t find any information in the game that helped lead you towards proper combinations (and I wanted to avoid walkthroughs).

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).027.png">

Battles in this game are pretty straightforward. You equip weapons to your robots, then use them in battle either directly, or you can program sequences that allow you to run multiple attacks in succession. This approach can kill enemies faster, but will require you to charge up for longer, and therefore be vulnerable for longer as well.

The fights are extremely repetetive, and it doesn&#8217;t help that there only appears to be a single battle theme that loops constantly. I played most of the game with the volume off due to this :P

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).010.png">

Once you get to the volcano and find the *Sword 4* in a chest, the random battles become exceedingly easy (for at least the next 3/4 of the game). This weapon is just ridiculously overpowered at this point and you&#8217;ll find yourself just spamming it in order to quickly proceed through the story.

Boss battles tend to be very dependant on what level you&#8217;re at when you enter the fight. Most battles I had to redo at least once as I found I was far too low of a level to have a chance.

<img class="right" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).022.png">

I found this to be the most true when I got to **De Rose**. This was the boss I reached during my last playthrough, and after grinding for a good 2 hours, I found I just couldn&#8217;t beat her, gave up and moved on to another game.

This time around, I actually checked a walkthrough, which recommended I be at about level 50 before entering the fight. I was at level 37. I was going to have to grind &#8230; and grinding in this game is TEDIOUS. I ended up grinding to about level 44 before beating her, but this took a good 4-5 hours. 

The story progresses: the Hackers leader (a crab) is defeated, Dr. Einst&#8217;s plot is foiled, a new Hackers leader emerges (Blackmore), the story jumps back and forwards in time, a spaceship emerges so you can visit another planet and you end up having to save the world.

<img class="left" src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).035.png">

The final battle is against Gateau (the &#8220;food&#8221;-naming convention for characters and places is used throughout the game), who had something to do with using the Tetron to build a weapon or something (I can&#8217;t remember the exact story; play the game for a better description :P).

He takes two forms, but isn&#8217;t overly difficult to defeat at this point.

Overall, this game was pretty easy. The story progressed in a very linear fashion, and most puzzles were pretty straightforward to solve.

It was fun though, and though I probably won&#8217;t replay this game again in the future, I&#8217;m glad that I went through it at least once.

My screenshots are below, though it seems that the emulator I was using ([Snes9x EX](http://www.explusalpha.com/home/snes9x-ex) on my Moto G) overwrote some of my earlier images. Oh well. Enjoy :P

<div id="galleria"><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).000.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).001.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).002.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).003.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).004.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).005.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).006.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).007.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).008.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).009.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).010.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).011.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).012.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).013.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).014.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).015.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).016.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).017.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).018.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).019.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).020.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).021.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).022.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).023.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).024.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).025.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).026.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).027.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).028.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).029.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).030.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).031.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).032.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).033.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).034.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).035.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).036.png" data-title="" /><img src="/images/robotrek/Robotrek_(USA).037.png" data-title="" /></div><script>  Galleria.configure('transition', 'fade');  Galleria.run('#galleria');</script>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Fire Emblem: The Sacred Stones]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/08/06/just-finished-fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-06T17:58:55-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/08/06/just-finished-fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="left" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.003.png">

I&#8217;ve played a lot of RPGs over the years (JRPGs mostly) but have somehow managed to hear little to nothing about the [Fire Emblem](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fire_Emblem) series.

My focus was mostly on the Final Fantasy series, as well as other Square-Enix properties so it&#8217;s possible this is why :P

This post isn&#8217;t really meant to be a review; it&#8217;s more just my thoughts on the game right after I finished it as (a) I didn&#8217;t take any notes, and (b) I started this playthrough over a year ago.

<!--more-->

I&#8217;m using this as an opportunity to get back into writing a bit more frequently, so I apologize in advance if the subject matter isn&#8217;t covered very well, or if the writing is all over the place.

<img class="right" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.004.png">

I managed to complete the game in about 19 hours, so at least I managed to finish over an hour a month (which by gaming standards is terrible, but I&#8217;m married with kids and have a job so *back off!* :P).

I played through on my Nexus 7 using [GBA.emu](https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.explusalpha.GbaEmu&hl=en) (which I would highly recommend buying to support the author), as I don&#8217;t have an actual GBA (and prefer emulated games for convenience).

<img class="left" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.002.png">

The game is turn-based tactical combat. You can buy equipment for your team members at various shops, and there is a &#8220;world map&#8221; that ties the various locations together. This makes is seem as though you&#8217;re playing a board game.

The story is pretty straightforward: a dark force was sealed with a bunch of magic stones which were then distributed for safe keeping. Now someone wants to get these stones and re-awaken the dark force.

The goals of each map are either to defeat an enemy or capture a location. Along the way there are various NPC characters that you can either fight or try to persuade to join you.

Fight outcome is determined purely mathematically (stats, resources, weapon selection, character skill level, enemy skill level, terrain) and is presented as 2 avatars on the map with health guages underneath that deplete based on the result of the last &#8220;turn&#8221; of combat.

For some special battles, the characters are shown as their avatar representations and the fights are animated. These fights are generally plot advancement battles.

<img class="right" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.005.png">

Once of the main differentiating factors between Fire Emblem and other RPG series is &#8220;permanent death&#8221;. Once a character dies on the battle field, there is no way to revive them. This can make the game extremely difficult as you can potentially advance to a point where you cannot continue as you don&#8217;t have enough players to clear a map without dying.

I found myself abusing save states as I didn&#8217;t want my characters to die, and I didn&#8217;t want to restart campaigns once I&#8217;d progressed beyond a certain point (usually about 10 minutes &#8230;).

Overall I quite enjoyed the game. The story isn&#8217;t terrible and there are enough characters to keep the campaigns interesting if you want or, if you&#8217;re like me you stick with a core group of characters that end up being ridiculously over-leveled by the end.

<img class="left" src="/images/fire-emblem-the-sacred-stones.000.png">

Once you finish the game, the final credits roll an epilogue unfolds that gives some final info about the characters that survived throughout the game. The characters that died in battle are also listed, and it summarizes where they died as well, which I thought was a nice touch.

I will likely take a stab at another entry in this series and take a bit more time (in game, not another year :P) to explore as I missed A LOT.

Once I finished the game I realized there was an entire Extras section where you can manage teams and practice battles (for points I think). Also I had a rogue with a members card and didn&#8217;t notice any of the &#8220;?&#8221; shops until *after* beating the last area.

I also didn&#8217;t spend much time in the optional dungeons, though I did use upgrade my characters to new classes whenever possible :) The next time I tackle a Fire Emblem title though I think I&#8217;ll try to (a) explore more, (b) do more optional/side quests, (c) NOT restart campaigns once they&#8217;re underway.

I&#8217;m currently also midway through a playthrough of [Robotrek](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robotrek) which I&#8217;ve been working on-again-off-again for about a year as well, so i may try to finish that off for the next *Just Finished&trade;* post. 

If anyone has suggestions for an RPG, leave a comment (currently I&#8217;m sticking with NES to PSP as the platform range).]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
