<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: rpg | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/rpg/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2020-01-17T07:57:12-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summer RPG Update 2016]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/09/05/summer-update-2016/"/>
        <updated>2016-09-05T14:08:29-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/09/05/summer-update-2016</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I don't really have much progress to report for the last month, so I thought I'd throw out a few of the games I've been working through to see if I can generate any interest in the next article ;)

{% img left /images/goldensun/goldensun.016.png %}

First off, I've been playing through [Golden Sun](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golden_Sun) for the GBA.

I really like the psyenergy system and how you use it for puzzle solving. It makes this game a bit more of an ARPG along the same lines as [Lufia 2]({% post_url 2015-09-23-just-finished-lufia-2 %}).

I've made it as far as [Kraken](http://goldensun.wikia.com/wiki/Kraken), but I'm finding beating him is proving to be more difficult that I'd expected. Probably going to have to back out and grind for a while, which I don't have a lot of time for ...

{% img right /images/7th-saga/7th-saga.019.png %}

Next, I'm pretty sure I've given up on [the 7th Saga](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7th_Saga). I'm still at Telaine with a party at level 17, but I'm pretty sure that to progress, there is grinding in my future.

Similar to the situation I'm having above with Golden Sun, i just need to set many hours aside to level up in order to proceed, but with the amount of time I've got these days to devote to these games, that may never happen.

<!-- more -->

Finally, I've decided to bite the bullet and dive into [Super Mario RPG](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Mario_RPG). This, along with Final Fantasy Tactics is one of those games that I've heard nothing but good things about for the last 20 years, but have never bothered to investigate myself.

{% img left /images/mariorpg/mariorpg.011.png %}

I'm currently at level 10 with 3 star pieces recovered and have just rescued Princess Toadstool and had her join the party.

I'm really enjoying the story and gameplay, but since this was developed by Square, I'm not surprised that this is right up my alley :P

I'm most likely going to be able to finish this game off, and then circle back around to Golden Sun, as I really want to beat that game.

Now, assuming I can make some progress on those two games, I'd like to start getting some feedback on where to take this series next.

There are a number of games that I've finished previously that I didn't write about. Some of the more notable ones would be:

* [Mother 3](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mother_3)
* Final Fantasy VIII
* Final Fantasy IX
* Chrono Trigger

Then there's the list of games that I really want to tackle, but since they all require a sizable time investment I'm not sure which to hit up:

* Xenogears
* Breath of Fire 3
* [Shin Megami Tensei: Persona 3](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shin_Megami_Tensei:_Persona_3) - *I'd likely play the PSP release*
* [Danganronmpa](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Danganronpa:_Trigger_Happy_Havoc) - *I started this a while back but never finished it*
* [Shin Megami Tensei 2](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shin_Megami_Tensei_II) - *There's a great fan translation of the Super Famicom release*
* [Final Fantasy IV: After Years](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_IV:_The_After_Years)
* [Vagrant Story](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vagrant_Story)

If you've got any insight into which I should tackle next, feel free to leave me a comment below ;)
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Gave Up On - Shadowrun (Genesis)]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/07/26/just-finished-shadowrun-genesis/"/>
        <updated>2016-07-26T05:25:39-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/07/26/just-finished-shadowrun-genesis</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[{% img left /images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.000.png %}

**UPDATE: 2016-09-05** - It was pointed out on [the Reddit thread](https://www.reddit.com/r/rpg_gamers/comments/4uxq5n/just_gave_up_on_shadowrun_genesis) and in the comments below that I might have used a cheat which prevented finishing the game. I didn't think I'd used one, but I think while doing research for the article i may have been testing it out :(

Note that you don't really need to cheat in this game to get more Nuyen; just grind ;)

Thanks to those who responded. It's worth noting that if you're going to play this game, *avoid the cheat menu* as it will bite you in the ass.

--------------------------------------------------------------------

As I work my way through the 8-bit and 16-bit games I grew up with, there are (and will continue to be) those that I just can't get through. [Shadowrun](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadowrun_(1994_video_game\)) for the Sega Genesis turned out to be one of those titles.

I've made it all the way to the final boss, and though he doesn't beat me, I empty all my clips (and my runner's clips) into him and just can't seem to kill him and trigger the endgame sequence.

This is extremely frustrating as I've effectively finished this game, but if I can't beat the last boss I can't in good conscience call this a "Just Finished" article.

Regardless, I've gone through enough of this game to be able to write about it, and based on my experience, recommend it to other players looking for some good retro cyberpunk action-RPG gaming.

<!-- more -->

{% img right /images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.001.png %}

This iteration of Shadowrun doesn't resemble the Super Nintendo's version of this title at all.

First off, you begin by selecting the type of player you want to run the game as: Samurai, Decker or Street Shaman. Each of these classes will give you different starting abilities and stats.

I chose to run as a Decker, as I wanted to get an idea as to how the matrix sequences differed between the games (plus I'm a programmer and felt drawn to this class :P).

The story starts off with you at a hotel trying to track down some information about what happened to your brother. You interact with characters in this game through conversation trees (select A, B, C) in order to advance the story or get clues.

{% img left /images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.002.png %}

A good chunk of the game is presented through these conversation views.

Once you leave the hotel, you start on your adventure into the world of Shadowrun.

Your character can walk around the initial city and go in and out of various buildings in order to trigger additional conversations with NPCs. It's a good idea to get a lay of the land as you'll be visiting each of these building repeatedly once you start shadowrunning, so it's worth taking the time to explore.

Some buildings will warn you that they contain ghouls. These buildings are where you can go to do some level grinding, or if you're on a run that has you clearing out ghouls, earn some money.

{% img right /images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.006.png %}

To level grind, you'll just be earning karma points which can be applied to the various stats your character has. These stats affect your weapons skills, magic skills, tech/computer skills or your aptitude with various weapon classes.

Although I started out as a Decker, I found myself maxing out my weapon skills early on to make the game a lot easier to progress through. It turns out there really isn't any demand for low level Deckers, so I didn't really have an opportunity to do any Matrix runs until much later in the game.

On the subject of shadowruns, the way you earn money (nuyen) in this game is by taking on various jobs (runs) from Mr. Johnson's. There are one or more Mr. Johnson's in each city you visit and they offer you work. Initially the types of work are either "escort <name> to <location>", "take package to <location>" or "clear out ghouls from abandoned building".

{% img left /images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.011.png %}

I found that the easiest runs to make money at early on where the ghoul runs. You basically just go into the building, find some ghouls and start running in circles. They'll just follow you so you can pick them off one at a time.

Although this became tedious pretty quickly, you get money and karma and can level up your weapon stats in order to make repeating this easier.

The escort runs are easy, and if you took the time to get an idea where each target is, it's even easier to do. It just takes time and the payout isn't that great.

Eventually you'll earn enough money to buy some info about where to go next and you have the opportunity to travel to a new city.

There are a handful of cities you can visit in this game, and each one offers it's own set of challenges, as well as opportunities for more advanced runs. 

You'll also meet other shadowrunners in bars and clubs throughout the game. These runners will give you more information about shadowrunning, the story, as well as background about the Shadowrun world.

These characters can also be hired to assist you on your runs. Each one has two rates; a single run rate or a lifetime rate.

I found I didn't really hire anyone until I hit the endgame as I didn't really need the help. If you're playing through the game as a shaman or samurai and don't bother upgrading your computer skills, it may be easier to hire a good decker than to upgrade your own stats and get a cyberdeck.

{% img right /images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.009.png %}

You'll meet new Mr. Johnson's who offer more difficult missions that involve traveling between the various cities in order to do more difficult quests such as infiltrating corporations to either steal secrets or extract employees, or running the matrix.

Both of these advanced run types offer their own challenges and require abilities to be leveled up in order to proceed.

When infiltrating corporations, you'll need to be able to have electronics skills in order to be able to break maglocks, and you'll want your weapon skills upgraded so as to be able to shoot guards without attracting more.

The infiltration jobs have you going through multiple floors of these buildings, with each floor having guards to deal with, security cameras to avoid and wall safes to plunder.

{% img left /images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.015.png %}

It helps to have computer skills when doing these runs as you can hack the computers to disable cameras, turn off alarms and open doors.

This takes us to decking and matrix running.

Unlike the SNES version of this game, the Genesis version actually has a bit more depth to the matrix.

You'll need to have computer skills first, then also have computer software for fighting with subsystems and identifying and avoiding various threats.

The fighting itself is pretty repetitive, but the concept is fun.

There are various types of components within a matrix system. You have to hack each of these as you move deeper into the system. The end goal is usually to hit a data store and download or delete a file.

{% img left /images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.021.png %}

One way to easily earn money is to hack into a system, download the maximum number of data files then try to sell them to a contact in [city]. Near the end of the game i was able to get upwards of 10K for some files, which made upgrading my equipment a lot easier to do ;)

Although I've been a huge fan of the SNES version of this game since I was a kid, I think I may have enjoyed the Genesis incarnation more. The music wasn't nearly as good, but the story was well laid out, there were a lot of options on how to progress and it didn't feel nearly as linear.

The addition of the classes gave you a sense of depth and replay-ability, though chances are you could just max out all stats for any player type and have same experience no matter how you started the game.

I also really enjoyed the shadowrunning aspect of this game. In the SNES version you could hire runners to help you get through the game, but you didn't actually participate in shadowruns for profit.

If you haven't given this game a shot, I would highly recommend it. It turned out to be a lot of fun, and an excellent addition to the limited field of cyberpunk games out there.

If you have any recommendations for other games in this genre I should check out, or if you want to share your opinion on this or the SNES title, please feel free to leave me a comment.

{% galleria %}
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.003.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.004.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.005.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.007.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.008.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.010.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.012.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.013.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.014.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.015.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.016.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.017.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.018.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.019.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.020.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.022.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.023.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.024.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.025.png
/images/shadowrun-gens/shadowrun.026.png
{% endgalleria %}]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Seiken Densetsu 3]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/04/19/just-finished-seiken-densetsu-3/"/>
        <updated>2016-04-19T14:30:20-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/04/19/just-finished-seiken-densetsu-3</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[{% img left /images/sd3/sd3.026.png %}

[Seiken Densetsu 3 (聖剣伝説3)](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seiken_Densetsu_3) is the third installment in the [Mana series](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mana_\(series\)). It's the sequel to [Secret of Mana](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_of_Mana), which is the entry into the series that most North American gamers would be familiar with.

Once again, I played through this game on my phone using the fantastic [Snes9x EX](http://www.explusalpha.com/home/snes9x-ex). Please support this dev as he provides a fantastic product. For some reason though, most of the screenshots I took came out stretched. This hasn't happened before, and I've been playing a couple other games that this isn't happening for either, so I'll chalk this up to bad luck :|

{% img /images/sd3/sd3.005.png %}

*NOTE* I ran these screenshots through [pngcrush](http://pmt.sourceforge.net/pngcrush/) (`ls *.png | while read line; do pngcrush -ow -brute $line; done`) to get the size down a bit ;)

I'm leaving these images in here as they were part of my "journey", though hopefully they don't deter anyone from playing this game, as the game is *fantastic*.

First off, if you're a fan of [Secret of Mana](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_of_Mana), the initial "feel" of the game will be familiar, as will the art style and sound.

<!-- more -->

Whereas SoM had you gradually encounter the two other playable characters at set points in the game, SD3 has you selecting your 3 main characters before you even begin.

I decided to go with Duran, Carlie and Kevin (something about a werewolf named Kevin made me chuckle :P). Duran's story starts off with the castle where he lives being invaded by a wizard who almost kills him. The wizard lets Duran live, so naturally Duran has to set off on a quest to find and defeat the wizard.

{% img /images/sd3/sd3.004.png %}

On this journey, he'll run into the other characters I selected (Kevin and Carlie), and each of their stories will mix into Duran's. This is actually a really cool element of this game as it gives it a lot of replay value. No matter what combination of characters you pick, their stories will all overlap. Also, you'll run into all the other characters you didn't pick, so every character makes an appearance throughout the game.

{% img right /images/sd3/sd3.010.png %}

You travel around the game mostly on foot initially, but eventually new methods of travel will open up. As with SoM, you can get to certain areas via Cannon Travel (though there's a couple of fetch-quests before you can actually take advantage of this). There's also a ship, a weird turtle thing, and eventually Flammie the dragon.

The combat system is reminiscent of SoM as well, though this time around it feels a lot more "button mash-ey". I found that I just spammed the B button throughout most of this game and didn't really use any strategy during combat; aside from healing periodically.

{% img left /images/sd3/sd3.014.png %}

You get experience by killing enemies, which will allow you to level up your characters. Leveling up lets you increase various stats, that should make your characters perform better in future battles.

As you make your way through the game, you'll start finding these pillars that are guarded by stronger enemies. These are the Mana stones, and apparently contain God-beasts that will be awakened if you shatter the stones.

These stones can also be used to change your character's class. This is another cool aspect of this game, as it give the leveling system a bit more flavour. You can change classes twice in this game; once at level 18, and again at level 38. Each of these classes is aligned with either "Light" or "Dark", and gives the character new skills/improvements.

{% img /images/sd3/sd3.017.png %}

The game can feel a bit "grindy" due to the need to constantly trudge back and forth between areas, and there are enemies on each screen. These battles are all avoidable, but you'll want to level up for the boss fights, and eventually the God Beasts.

While you're trekking though, you get to enjoy some really good background music. If you like Secret of Mana, you'll love Seiken Densetsu 3. You can have a listen over at [YouTube](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qrywwZ7oL2w&index=30&list=PL4649F0DBF0FC09E3) to get an idea what's in store for you ;)

{% img right /images/sd3/sd3.031.png %}

The artwork is also top notch. It's really a shame this game never made it to North America as this is possibly one of the best looking SNES games out there. The background design, character design and monster sprites are all very, very well done. There is a lot of variety to the various regions of the world.

Once you've shattered all the Mana stones, you unleash the God Beasts. Their position is shown on the world map, and they can be fought in any order, but it's a good idea to start from the top left of the map and work your way through them sequentially.

I learned this the hard way as I only play this game on occasion, and ended up forgetting where I was. This resulted in A LOT of backtracking to find the last couple of beasts.

I thoroughly enjoyed playing this game and would highly recommend this to anyone out there that likes JRPGs, action RPGs and 8/16-bit gaming in general. The graphics, music and gameplay are all very well done, and the story lines are interesting, even if there is occasionally some cheesy dialog :P

{% galleria %}
/images/sd3/sd3.000.png
/images/sd3/sd3.001.png
/images/sd3/sd3.002.png
/images/sd3/sd3.003.png
/images/sd3/sd3.006.png
/images/sd3/sd3.007.png
/images/sd3/sd3.008.png
/images/sd3/sd3.011.png
/images/sd3/sd3.012.png
/images/sd3/sd3.013.png
/images/sd3/sd3.015.png
/images/sd3/sd3.016.png
/images/sd3/sd3.018.png
/images/sd3/sd3.019.png
/images/sd3/sd3.020.png
/images/sd3/sd3.021.png
/images/sd3/sd3.022.png
/images/sd3/sd3.023.png
/images/sd3/sd3.024.png
/images/sd3/sd3.025.png
/images/sd3/sd3.027.png
/images/sd3/sd3.028.png
/images/sd3/sd3.029.png
/images/sd3/sd3.030.png
/images/sd3/sd3.032.png
/images/sd3/sd3.033.png
/images/sd3/sd3.034.png
/images/sd3/sd3.035.png
/images/sd3/sd3.036.png
/images/sd3/sd3.037.png
/images/sd3/sd3.038.png
/images/sd3/sd3.039.png
/images/sd3/sd3.040.png
/images/sd3/sd3.041.png
/images/sd3/sd3.042.png
/images/sd3/sd3.043.png
/images/sd3/sd3.044.png
/images/sd3/sd3.045.png
/images/sd3/sd3.046.png
/images/sd3/sd3.047.png
{% endgalleria %}

I finished this game over a month ago, so I'm still pretty slow cranking out these reviews ...

I'm currently working my way through [The 7th Saga](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7th_Saga) for SNES since I clearly need *more* pain and frustration in my life :P When that game is annoying me, I'm also working on Sega Genesis version of [Shadowrun](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadowrun_\(1994_video_game\)).

That game was recommended by some of my readers on Reddit so I figured I had to give it a whirl. So far I'm actually really enjoying it, and it is VERY different the the SNES game of the same name.

Hopefully I'll have more for you in the near(er) future :)
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Shadowrun]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/02/23/just-finished-shadowrun/"/>
        <updated>2016-02-23T20:20:11-05:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2016/02/23/just-finished-shadowrun</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[I had this game finished around Christmas, but I find my motivation for writing these articles is starting to languish. I'm hoping to get that spark back with the next couple of titles i'll be tackling, even though Shadownrun was one of my favourite SNES games of all time.

{% img right /images/shadowrun/shadowrun.001.png %}

You wake up on a slab in the morgue. You don't know who you are or how you got there. That's pretty much all you've got to go on when you start this game for the first time.

The intro shows you being gunned down, then a shapeshifter casts a spell on you and takes off. After getting out of the morgue, you run into "Dog", who appears to be a shamanistic totem.

This was the first 10 minutes of this game, and I remember playing this back in '94 and being hooked at this point.

[Shadowrun](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadowrun_(1993_video_game\)) is a cyberpunk action-RPG for the Super Nintendo. You control Jake Armitage, a courier who has something important uploaded to his head computer. 

<!-- more -->

You move around in an isometric fashion. You can interact with certain people by talking to them, or occasionally giving them a key item from your inventory.

{% img left /images/shadowrun/shadowrun.005.png %}

When talking to NPCs, some words will appear in bold. These can then be used as keywords in future conversations. These NPC interactions are how the story is progressed, and you'll spend a fair amount of time in this menu over the course of the game.

Once you learn the *Hiring* keyword, you can also try to hire additional shadowrunners. When they join your team, they will fight along side you ... for a while. If you've increased your leadership levels, they may stay longer.

Leveling up is done by spending karma when you rest on a bed (which also acts as a save point). You can spend your karma to boost various stats, or to level up your spells once you learn magic.

Karma is gained by fighting, which is done by moving a set of cross-hairs across the screen, and when placed over an enemy, mashing the A button. You then fire, wait, fire, wait ... etc.

{% img right /images/shadowrun/shadowrun.010.png %}

The combat in this game is pretty simple. Just stand in one place and fire. Once you're in combat mode, you can move your character, so there's not really any strategy (other than healing on occasion).

The same system is used for spells and items. You select the (spell/item) from the menu, the cursor becomes a hand icon, and you hover over your target and press a button again.

Navigating the screen using the D-pad can be a bit cumbersome; especially when fighting, but you get used to it after a while.

The game seems to be made up of a series of fetch quests that are used to get you from NPC to NPC in order to uncover more keywords, to then be used with other NPCs to trigger more fetch quests. Oh, and move the story along as well ;)

{% img left /images/shadowrun/shadowrun.006.png %}

The game is split up into 3 main areas that you can navigate to by train, one area you get to by boat, and the volcano you get to by helicopter. These areas are all opened up as the story moves along and you slowly uncover who was responsible for trying to geek you at the beginning of the game.

As you fight your way through the various areas, you'll find out that you were a courier with sensitive information in your head computer. You have a datajack in your head which is not working, so you can't access your brain by computer in order to get this information.

When you go find a street doc to fix your datajack, it triggers a cortex bomb that then needs to be defused. After this is done, you get some information about what's in your head and you can start decking (hacking) into computers.

{% img right /images/shadowrun/shadowrun.019.png %}

The decking segments are actually pretty dumb, but I love them. This is really what has kept me going back to this game time and again over the years, as I just really loved the concept.

You're physically wired into this machine, and have to battle various security countermeasures that have been installed in these systems. The battles are done by guessing when there is a hidden enemy on a grid and pressing the A button. Based on an RNG value and your computer skill level, you'll either miss or destroy the enemy.

That's it. That's all there is to it. I still love it though :P

Depending on why you were hacking in, you'll either trigger an elevator or get part of a data file. The data files are plot devices that give you bits of the story, or contain phone numbers you can use from vidphones throughout the game.

{% img left /images/shadowrun/shadowrun.024.png %}

After you've finally fought your way through the various sections of the game, you finally get to face off against Drake. He's apparently the one behind you almost being whacked. You beat him up, head back to Akimi building, fight your way up a handful of floors (fighting and decking) and finally find the AI you need to destroy.

Once done, things explode, and you can close the books on this adventure. 

The game alludes to there being a potential sequel in the works, but this never materialized. There was another Shadownrun title for [Sega Genesis](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shadowrun_(1994_video_game\)), but this was a completely different game. I might play through this and do a write up one day, but I've tried playing it a couple times over the years and could never get into it (if you think I should, or want to share an opinion, there is a comments section below ... :P).

{% img right /images/shadowrun/shadowrun.027.png %}

Overall I still love this game. This is where I was introduced to cyberpunk as a kid, and I even went as far as getting the Shadowrun books ([Never Deal with a Dragon](http://www.amazon.com/Never-Deal-Dragon-Shadownrun-Vol/dp/0451450787)) that this game was very loosely based on.

The music was also a fantastic complement to the dark atmosphere of the game. [3AM On A Summer Night](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ome6XI_KuIw&list=PL2D5FC9FCF1AEF68C&index=2) might actually be one of my favourite tracks from the 16-bit era that wasn't composed by Nobuo Uematsu ;)

If you're revisiting the SNES and looking for something you may have overlooked during the mid '90s, pick this up and give it a spin.

{% galleria %}
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.000.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.002.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.003.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.004.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.007.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.008.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.009.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.011.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.012.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.013.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.014.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.015.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.016.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.017.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.018.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.020.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.021.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.022.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.023.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.025.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.026.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.028.png
/images/shadowrun/shadowrun.029.png
{% endgalleria %}

Next up, [Seiken Densetsu 3](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seiken_Densetsu_3). This one will probably take me a while to complete, then a longer while to actually do a write up on.]]></content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Finished - Final Fantasy V]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/11/07/just-finished-final-fantasy-v/"/>
        <updated>2015-11-07T20:15:57-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/11/07/just-finished-final-fantasy-v</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[{% img right /images/ffv/ffv.001.png %}

I've been waiting write this review for a very long time. I love the Final Fantasy series, and although I got the original back in '90, I didn't really fall in love with the series until I played IV for the SNES. Then I played VI. Then I was REALLY hooked.

Since I didn't grow up in Japan, FF IV and VI were numbered II and III when I first got my hands on them. This means that I didn't know there was a [Final Fantasy V](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_V); at least not until much later.

The game starts off with the king of Tycoon heading off to check on the wind crystal, only to watch it shatter. The hero Bartz (Butz when I played the fan translation :P) sees a meteorite fall from the sky and heads off to investigate. Bartz and his Chocobo go to check it out, and find an old man who's suffering from amnesia.

The king's daughter, Lenna, heads out to find her father and runs into Bartz and Galuf. They team up and the adventure begins.

{% img left /images/ffv/ffv.003.png %}

Once at the wind shrine, they find that the crystal has shattered and within each shard is the power of a job class.

This introduces you to the job ability system. If you've ever had a chance to play [Final Fantasy III](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Final_Fantasy_III), you've see this system in action, but in FFV, it's done to perfection :)

<!-- more -->

Each character can be assigned to a job class. As they defeat enemies, they gain ability points, which levels up the job class. As the classes level up, you gain abilities associated with that class.

These abilities can then be applied to a character regardless of the class they're assigned to. For example, you can give a white mage black magic abilities (if you've leveled up a black mage for that character).

This gives you a lot of control over how you build your characters as the game progresses.

{% img right /images/ffv/ffv.002.png %}

The storytelling in this game is very well done. Although the plot is pretty standard Final Fantasy fare (crystals, amnesia, evil emperor, main characters dying), the writing was pretty good and the character emotion pop-ups added a nice touch as well.

I enjoyed the elements of comedy they tried to incorporate into some of the scenarios and characters. After playing this game, Gilgamesh is probably my new favourite non-player character in the series. This might also have to do with [Clash on the Big Bridge](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6CMTXyExkeI)
being my favourite song from this game ;)

{% img left /images/ffv/ffv.022.png %}

The battle system is the same as in FFIV ([Active Time Battle system](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Battle_System#Active_Time_Battle)). You can fight, use items, or up to 2 abilities you've learned from gaining AP and leveling up your classes.

I didn't find the battles overly difficult during this play-through, but I've been focusing a lot on grinding in the last few games I've covered, so this could just be a result of me over leveling.

So as you progress through the game, you discover that the ultimate evil, Exdeath, was banished to your world by the four warriors of dawn. Now you and your party need to become the new warriors of dawn to fight him again.

{% img right /images/ffv/ffv.046.png %}

You have to get the ultimate weapons for each character class, you can go on some side quests to get some powerful summons and eventually go after Exdeath.

There is one fight in Exdeath's tower that I just couldn't win, and that was [Shinryu](http://finalfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Shinryu_(Final_Fantasy_V)). I didn't bother to upgrade my equipment after a while as I just hoarded my money to use Gil Toss against everybody. As a result, Shinryu just decimated me every time I tried ... so I just gave up.

I found that magic and summons in this game proved to be effective until the very end. This is different than my experience with FF II, where you bust your ass to get Ultima, then it does like 900 damage to enemies (even after being leveled up a few times :|).

I thought the story was really compelling, and I found the whole alternate worlds overlapping "thing" to be a nice twist, though it felt a bit like what happened in FF III. Actually, just like FF III, you even have to race a chocobo around the world to get an item ...

{% img left /images/ffv/ffv.037.png %}

I teared up (just a bit) when Galuf's flame was extinguished by Exdeath. I was a bit worried that since this game follows FF IV it was possible they would do the whole "everyone who died is magically back to fight again for no reason" that happened with Yang, Cid, Edward, Tellah ... etc. Fortunately (?), this wasn't the case and it's actually a very emotional point in the story.

I would strongly recommend any fan of JRPGs spend some time on this title. If I were ranking my favourite FFs now, Final Fantasy V would probably show up in the top 5 :)

As for where I'm going from here, I'm currently about 6-8 hours into [Pokémon Emerald](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pok%C3%A9mon_Emerald). I'm sort of enjoying it, though it feels like a watered down version of [Earthbound](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EarthBound) (just my initial impression).

I'm also about 4-5 hours into [Tales of Destiny](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tales_of_Destiny), but I'm not really enjoying this title and likely won't go back to it.

Feel free to leave me some feedback on whether or not I should continue the above, or if you've got a recommendation for the next title I tackle.

Cheers!

{% galleria %}
/images/ffv/ffv.000.png
/images/ffv/ffv.004.png
/images/ffv/ffv.005.png
/images/ffv/ffv.006.png
/images/ffv/ffv.007.png
/images/ffv/ffv.008.png
/images/ffv/ffv.009.png
/images/ffv/ffv.010.png
/images/ffv/ffv.011.png
/images/ffv/ffv.012.png
/images/ffv/ffv.013.png
/images/ffv/ffv.014.png
/images/ffv/ffv.015.png
/images/ffv/ffv.016.png
/images/ffv/ffv.017.png
/images/ffv/ffv.018.png
/images/ffv/ffv.019.png
/images/ffv/ffv.020.png
/images/ffv/ffv.021.png
/images/ffv/ffv.023.png
/images/ffv/ffv.024.png
/images/ffv/ffv.025.png
/images/ffv/ffv.026.png
/images/ffv/ffv.027.png
/images/ffv/ffv.028.png
/images/ffv/ffv.029.png
/images/ffv/ffv.030.png
/images/ffv/ffv.031.png
/images/ffv/ffv.032.png
/images/ffv/ffv.033.png
/images/ffv/ffv.034.png
/images/ffv/ffv.035.png
/images/ffv/ffv.036.png
/images/ffv/ffv.038.png
/images/ffv/ffv.039.png
/images/ffv/ffv.040.png
/images/ffv/ffv.041.png
/images/ffv/ffv.042.png
/images/ffv/ffv.043.png
/images/ffv/ffv.044.png
/images/ffv/ffv.045.png
/images/ffv/ffv.047.png
/images/ffv/ffv.048.png
/images/ffv/ffv.049.png
/images/ffv/ffv.050.png
/images/ffv/ffv.051.png
/images/ffv/ffv.052.png
/images/ffv/ffv.053.png
/images/ffv/ffv.054.png
{% endgalleria %}]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
