<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: redmine | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/redmine/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-27T10:15:31-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Third Royalty Statement]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/12/22/third-royalty-statement/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-22T08:11:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/12/22/third-royalty-statement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[I'd love to say Christmas came early this year, but it looks like sales of [Redmine Plugin Extension and Development](http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book) didn't quite hit the numbers needed to actually result in a royalty cheque. Ah well, there's always Q1 of 2015 :D

I've added the latest numbers to those from [my previous post](/blog/2014/09/22/second-royalty-statement/) in order to show the running total of units sold this year.

| |Ebook Mini|Subscription Packtlib Mini|Print Book Mini|Subscription (3rd Party Mini)|
|-|----------|--------------------------|---------------|-----------------------------|
|Q1/2014|18|3|18|0|
|Q2/2014|73|1|33|2|
|Q3/2014|25|2|24|4|

<!-- more -->

<img class="left" src="/images/20141222-ss01.png">

The main reason I&#8217;ve been sharing these numbers (without sharing that actual &#8220;numbers&#8221;) is to show prospective authors what types of returns they can potentially expect.

The book I wrote falls into the &#8220;minibook&#8221; category, so the returns are lower than a full-on &#8220;book&#8221; (I think < 100 pages is a minibook), but at this rate, 2015 might result in a non-negative royalty statement that I can share :)

Happy Holidays Everyone!!!

<img class="left" src="/images/20141222-cat.png">
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Second Royalty Statement]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/09/22/second-royalty-statement/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-22T11:45:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/09/22/second-royalty-statement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Although I haven't really had much to write about lately, I just got another royalty update from Packt Publishing about [Redmine Plugin Extension and Development](http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book) so I wanted to share the latest sales figures ... sort of :P

In the table below, I've added the latest numbers to those from [my previous post](/blog/2014/07/15/8748os-first-royalty-statement/) in order to show the running total of units sold this year.

| |Ebook Mini|Subscription Packtlib Mini|Print Book Mini|Subscription (3rd Party Mini)|
|-|----------|--------------------------|---------------|-----------------------------|
|Q1/2014|18|3|18|0|
|Q2/2014|73|1|33|2|

<!-- more -->

<img class="left" src="/images/royalties20140630.png">

Once again, I&#8217;ve decided to remove the actual sales numbers from the statement, but I left in *TOTAL ROYALTIES TO BE PAID IN PERIOD* section. I did this to show the progress from time of publication to now in terms of how much of the advance has been consumed by **ACTUAL** sales.

At this rate, it&#8217;s possible I&#8217;ll see some additional money out of this title by the time 2014 is through .. which would be very exciting.

I&#8217;m sure there are others out there who have been approached by technical publications and asked to write about some topic or other. I&#8217;m sure the numbers I&#8217;m posting here will convince you it&#8217;s not worth quitting your job and writing full time, but it looks like it *could* become profitable over time.

If you&#8217;ve had anything published and are seeing a decent return on your &#8220;investment&#8221;, please share in the comments ;)]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Subversion + Ruby on Heroku via Buildpacks]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/07/07/subversion-plus-ruby-on-heroku-via-buildpacks/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-07T09:28:38-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/07/07/subversion-plus-ruby-on-heroku-via-buildpacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Back in 2012, I wrote a post about [Redmine and Subversion on Heroku](/blog/2012/11/21/fetching-changesets-in-redmine-from-heroku-using-svn/) that involved some funky hacks in order to build a working `svn` binary that could be uploaded as part of your Git payload.

This can be done a lot more cleanly by taking advantage of [Heroku Buildpacks](https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/buildpacks).

<!-- more -->

All of the instructions I provided in my previous post can now be distilled into a single buildpack install command.

If we want to leverage an existing solution, we just add the [Subversion Buildpack](https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/buildpacks) to our app.

The main &#8220;gotcha&#8221; here is that we can only have ONE buildpack defined at a time, which is problematic because our app&#8217;s environment (Ruby, PHP, Node .. etc) is managed as a buildpack (see https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/buildpacks for more details).

In order to get around this limitation though, we can leverage another buildpack, known as the [heroku-buildpack-multi](https://github.com/ddollar/heroku-buildpack-multi) buildpack which allows us to define multiple buildpacks.

For our purposes, we&#8217;re going to add Subversion and Ruby to our app:

    $ cd /path/to/app
    
    $ heroku config:add BUILDPACK_URL=https://github.com/ddollar/heroku-buildpack-multi.git
    
    $ cat .buildpacks
    https://github.com/cucumber-ltd/heroku-buildpack-subversion.git
    https://github.com/heroku/heroku-buildpack-ruby.git

    $ git commit .buildpacks -m &#8220;Add Buildpacks&#8221;
    $ git push heroku master

This has helped me with my Redmine deployment on Heroku. Did it help you at all? Did I get something wrong. Let me know ;)]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Redmine Plugin Extension and Development: Published!!!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/03/19/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development-published/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-19T06:08:02-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/03/19/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development-published</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img class="left" src="/images/balloons.png">

Well, it&#8217;s official. The journey I began over six months ago has finally come to an end, and [Redmine Plugin Extension and Development](http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book) has officially been published :)

I plan on doing a &#8220;post-mortem&#8221; on the process at some point, but for now I&#8217;m planning on taking a little time off from writing.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Production Timeline]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/03/03/8748os-production-timeline/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T08:22:30-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2014/03/03/8748os-production-timeline</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Well, it's been a long (longer than anticipated) journey, but [Redmine Plugin Extension and Development](http://www.packtpub.com/redmine-plugin-extension-and-development/book) (code number 8748OS) is in the final stages of production.

Since I wanted to share a bit more detail about what went into the production of this book, I'm attaching a (slightly edited) copy of the production timeline I received from my Technial Editor.

<!-- more -->

## Technical Editing / Copy Editing

We would be editing chapters for language and content-related clarity. There might be instances when we&#8217;ll require your assistance while we make any content-related changes. Even if there are no queries, we would be sending our first edited chapter (Per TE) to you to ensure that you are happy with the quality of editing. When chapter are sent across to you, the expected turnaround time will be 24 hours per chapter.

* Start of Editing: *21st February 2014*
* End of Editing: *6th March 2014*

After the chapters  are edited, they are indexed  and then laid out. The laid out chapters are then sent across to the Proof Reader, who are experts in English language. The Proof read chapters are then finalized and made into what we term as &#8220;Pre-Finals&#8221;. This is the stage where-in you will get to see the final chapters as you would see them in the book.

## Schedule for Pre-finals

2 to 4 Pre-Finals will be sent across to you in a batch. The expected turnaround time will be 24 hours for a batch of two chapters.

At this stage, you&#8217;ll be expected to just go through the chapters and provide feedback, if any. Any major content changes should be avoided. We plan to start sending these within 7-10 days from today and would continue to do so, until the day the book is clubbed and finalized.

## Upload Date

This is the day when the clubbed book will be finalized and then sent to our printers. We call it the upload day, since the files are transferred to our printers and we cannot make any changes here after.

* Current Upload Date: *17th March 2014*

## Publishing Date

The book gets published and will be available for purchase in five to eight working days from the day of upload.

So all going well, it looks like the book will officially be available by the end of March 2014. For those who were anticipating the original January 2014 release date, I sincerly apologize for the delay. I felt the delay resulted in a more cohesive final product, and hope that it meets (and even exceeds) your expectations!]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
