<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Category: asylum | ALEX BEVILACQUA]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/categories/asylum/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-22T21:57:59-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Alex Bevilacqua]]></name>
        <email><![CDATA[alex@alexbevi.com]]></email>
      </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asylum Engine Update]]></title>
        <link href="http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/04/08/asylum-engine-update/"/>
        <updated>2015-04-08T09:31:14-04:00</updated>
        <id>http://www.alexbevi.com/blog/2015/04/08/asylum-engine-update</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[It's been a number of years since I had a chance to look at this project, but recently I updated the codebase to the latest version (sync with upstream [ScummVM](https://github.com/scummvm/scummvm)) and found that the videos no longer worked.

<img src="/images/20150408-004.png">

It turned out to be a pretty simple fix (see [commit](https://github.com/alexbevi/scummvm/commit/1ed45a5802a7ab9603aa72f8e18196e980657c23)), but it rekindled my interest in the project.

<!-- more -->

I added some additional debug output and cleaned up the script debug loop so that there wasn't as much spamming of commands that were waiting for another event.

Also, thanks to [@xesf](https://github.com/xesf), we can now actually proceed up and down stairs via fixes he made to the script processor.

<img src="/images/20150408-003.png">

## TODO

**better pathfinding**

<img src="/images/20150408-001.png">

The path-finding in the original engine is a lot smarter and more forgiving than our implementation.

**inventory management**

<img src="/images/20150408-002.png">

We can currently pick up an item and remove the graphic from the screen, but there's no way to retrieve/use items once collected.

**clean up graphical glitches**

There are still a number of clipping issues, as well as incorrect behaviour when Max is standing still (wrong animation might play).

**fix encounters**

<img src="/images/20150408-005.png">

Encounters load, but you can't interact with keywords yet.

**save/load**

There was quite a bit of work done on this, but we still need to verify that everything is being restored properly on load.]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>
